PAUL: Yeah, hello everyone, am I audible? Please do confirm in the chats.
PAUL: Alright, so today we'll be starting the course, the actual content.
PAUL: All right, so let's start our session. I hope everybody has joined.
PAUL: Alright, I think no more messages here.
PAUL: Okay, everybody has joined, it looks like.
PAUL: So, today, we will start with the introduction to RAD. Okay, so we will try to understand, first of all, like, when RAD came. Okay, now this content, I think everybody has access to this site. Please let me know.
PAUL: With a yes?
PAUL: Because I've already told you to bookmark these things.
PAUL: Yes, I think the URL is long, I know. Nothing I can do, because it's from Notion.coms. Okay, I can do a tiny URL, and then I can make it short.
PAUL: That is the core idea, okay? So, let me just share the link once more in the chat, just that a few people might not have joined for them, okay? I have shared.
PAUL: Okay, I've shared the URL. Everyone, please do check.
PAUL: Okay, so, yesterday's session, so it was all about the tools and the installation part that we have discussed. In today's session.
PAUL: So this is the 9th, so… and here you can see. Okay, so right now, I have not kept any notes here very specifically. After the class, I'll be adding the notes.
PAUL: Based on the research paper discussion that we'll be doing, and very specifically for two things.
PAUL: Now, one main thing, because I know as we have gone through multiple discussions through multiple students, that yes, a few people already have the idea of RAM.
PAUL: But others, they have zero idea, okay? So we will take a journey, okay? So, this will be the first paper that we will be discussing.
PAUL: Yes, so…
PAUL: Let me just open the paper. I think everybody can access the papers. The links are provided. Please let me know.
PAUL: Yes?
PAUL: Everybody can open the paper, okay. Now, the idea is…
PAUL: To go through research always, okay? And, like.
PAUL: blogs and other stuff, it's good, okay, for fast learning, but really, you have to understand, okay, when RAC came, the first time the concept of RAC, the word, when it was first published, it came from Facebook AI Research, the FAIR team that we call it.
PAUL: Okay, as you can see here, Facebook AI research, and the main guy who was doing the research, he was Mike Pelvis. This is the… and…
PAUL: Those are basically, you can think about collaborators with him in the research, but this is the main guy.
PAUL: Mike Clevis, who brought the concept of RACA.
PAUL: Now, before starting that, okay, so let's talk about a few things in NLP that I feel you should know, because right now, there will be a lot of words, okay, that might be new for you. The idea is to be familiar with the terminology.
PAUL: Okay, now, how many of you are here who don't know anything about NL? Please let me know in the chat.
PAUL: I need to have an idea, like.
PAUL: how many of you know about NLP, okay? People, no idea, I have no idea, all right. Then, see, what I will do. Okay, so one thing, so here, I'll be adding some additional topics. If you have zero idea, okay, because you really need to
PAUL: Those topics, okay, because In this course, we won't be discussing those topics.
PAUL: Okay, because NLP started, like, back from 2014, so everything I cannot discuss, but I will tell you what are the topics that you guys need to learn. Okay, after the class, please go through those topics. I will just create a list of topics for you, okay?
PAUL: All right. So, first of all, let's start with the fundamentals of a NLP model, okay? So, let me just start sharing my notes screen. I will stop sharing my desktop now, okay? I will just get to my iPad.
PAUL: So advanced, I think.
PAUL: iPad via cable… okay, just check that you guys can see this one.
PAUL: the iPad screen.
PAUL: Can you guys see, please let me know in the chat, yes.
PAUL: Alright, so we'll start with… Mmm…
PAUL: Introduction.
PAUL: to rag.
PAUL: Got it. So, before starting with RAT, the first important thing is.
PAUL: You guys have heard so much about LLMs.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, what are LLMs, in simple terms? Just, like, two words or three words that you guys can let me know in the chat. What you think, like, what are LLMs?
PAUL: Okay, somebody is telling Breen, somebody is telling…
PAUL: large language models, okay? This is the full form, okay, so they are referred to as Large language models.
PAUL: Okay, so that is fine. Okay, so I think everybody knows the full form. Knowledge repository, collection of vector data, okay, so a lot of wrong things are also coming. It's not collection of vector data.
PAUL: Okay, containing public data. Okay, alright. Now, let's start with the most fundamental. It's not a token generator.
PAUL: Okay, large neural network, okay, now the neural network part, okay? So everybody leave the chats now, okay? And just focus on the note. Leave the chat, please, don't write on the chats.
PAUL: So, the first part, okay, so what are these? So, in simple terms, I can call them
PAUL: deep learning models.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: And why deep learning models I am calling? Okay, just because of two things. The most fundamental thing. Because of weights.
PAUL: Bye.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: This is the most fundamental thing, whether you are talking about convolution neural networks, whether you are talking about recurrent neural networks, RNNs, okay.
PAUL: And finally comes the transformers family. Okay, so on top of which, the LLMs are built, okay? So, the fundamental thing of any type of LLM is that it is basically a deep learning model. It's basically a combination
PAUL: of weights and biases in some printouts, okay? So, you have to always remember this, because deep learning started from 2012.
PAUL: Okay, now, this course is not about deep learning, but the fundamentals
PAUL: of LLM always comes from that.
PAUL: Now, very specifically for large language models, there is something, a concept that comes transformers, the architecture.
PAUL: How many of you know about transformers? Because this part is important.
PAUL: Because this course… I won't be teaching you Transformers, but this is fundamental. It started back from 2017.
PAUL: Okay, whoever doesn't know about this one.
PAUL: please go, okay, and learn about transformers, okay?
PAUL: Okay, probably I will ask the team also to attach the videos in the dashboard, okay, as a prerequisite. Okay, so there is a paper called as Attention is All You Need. Okay, very, very important research paper. I'll be adding those links in the Notion. Later on, you guys can check it out.
PAUL: Okay, so any type of LLM is always based on a transformer's architecture.
PAUL: So you have to remember that.
PAUL: Now, what are transformers? So, simply, deep learning models. Okay, and whenever we are talking about models, LLMs.
PAUL: Okay, now we'll be talking about
PAUL: the LLMs, very specifically, like, what are the major problems?
PAUL: Okay, because if I'm talking about LLMs.
PAUL: you are working with any type of NLP models, okay, because there are so many, but few common ones, if you've heard about, like BERT architecture.
PAUL: Okay, probability T5… okay.
PAUL: or BART part.
PAUL: These are different types of models. Okay, now, when I'll be talking with respect to the research paper, okay, now these things will come into the picture.
PAUL: So, all these things, like BERT, T5, Pegasus, okay, the list is locked. So, these are based on the transformer's architecture. Now, transformers follow a very specific architecture referred to as
PAUL: The encoder-decoder architecture.
PAUL: Okay? The encoder-decoder.
PAUL: architecture.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Now, when you will learn about transformers, you will come to know about this particular architecture, which is very specifically mentioned in the attention is all you need paper.
PAUL: Okay? If somebody doesn't know, please go through these things. Then I will finally come to the main topic, because these are some prerequisites, because when I start reading papers, okay, tell you, most of you will say that, okay.
PAUL: Most of the terminologies are unknown to me, okay? That should not be the case. That's why I'm giving you… these are the major things, okay, your underlying, I can say foundational knowledge, okay, whenever you are learning about LLM Central.
PAUL: Now, you know that one of the most famous models, if I'm talking about GPT.
PAUL: Okay, so GPT comes from which organization, guys?
PAUL: Okay, the OpenAI. Okay, so when I'm talking with respect to OpenAI, okay, now GPT follows a very specific type of architecture, referred to as the decoder.
PAUL: Similarly, there is, like, BERT, if I'm talking about.
PAUL: Okay, so… it follows.
PAUL: An encoder-based architecture.
PAUL: So, birth, this comes from Google. Okay, so this comes from the Google research team.
PAUL: Now, based on this, I'll be showing you a long list of models in Hugging Face.
PAUL: Also, you'll be… you will know that there are a lot of open source models which are available, and right now, the things that I'm talking, it's completely open source. It means that anyone can download those models, and you can perform any type of NLP task.
PAUL: Now, in NLP, whenever we are working with, I can say LLM, okay, or, basically, the models where you, like, for GPT or both.
PAUL: There is something called… there is a concept called as upstream and downstream.
PAUL: Okay, the other one is downstream.
PAUL: How many of you know about this?
PAUL: Please let me know. Because this is nothing with respect to RAG, but…
PAUL: This is, like, the NLP concepts. So, many people know about NLP.
PAUL: There is something called as upstream task and downstream task.
PAUL: Upstream is the sources, okay?
PAUL: And, what is downstream?
PAUL: Downstream is target application. Alright, downstream is destination. It's not destination, really what type of task you want to, okay? Now, let me just give you the idea, because RAG is actually based on this downstream task, okay? So, anything that you do with respect to pre-training.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Before training, whatever the things that you try to do.
PAUL: Okay, so, for example, if you want to perform any type of language modeling task, okay, for that, you have to perform a masked token operation.
PAUL: Okay, and based on that, you can do a net sentence prediction. Okay, one… anything that you do, like, pre-train. Okay.
PAUL: Anything before the training that comes, it's referred to as an upstream task, okay? And anything that you will be doing for downstream, it means that for, like, after training, I can say, okay, like, post-training.
PAUL: Okay, so the common term that is used, you people might have heard, which is referred to as fine-tuning.
PAUL: I think everybody has heard fine kidney.
PAUL: Generally, like, with your custom data that you train a particular model is referred to as a fine-tuning task, okay?
PAUL: Yes, Laura, no, Sengal, you were wrong, like, LoRa is quantization, very specific.
PAUL: Okay, so right now, you have to understand these fine-tuning tasks. So, what type of tasks are referred to as downstream tasks? So, one of the most common examples that I can give you… okay, so here, masking, I am telling.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And here, what are the different types of downstream term? One is something like text classification.
PAUL: Okay, then comes your summarization.
PAUL: Okay, then comes your POS… Okay, then you can think about NER,
PAUL: These are all classic NLP tasks that we do. Okay, then comes your question-answering, Q&A, Okay.
PAUL: at any point of time, or you can think about empty also, like machine translation. So, these are common tasks which are being done.
PAUL: At any point of time.
PAUL: Okay? Now, these are the major tasks for which you actually look for an LLM. Can I say that an LLM can actually do summarization?
PAUL: Can an LLM do text classification?
PAUL: Okay, now, or question answering, if you ask a question, it can answer. So, these are basically the problems. Okay, which LLM is solving?
PAUL: You have to understand. So, these type of tasks are referred to as downstream. Now, going forward, if I say, okay, this is downstream, so you guys have to analyze, I'm talking about a fine-tuning task.
PAUL: The task can be text classification, or summarization, or POS, or NER, okay? Simply, you have to understand that. Whenever I use the term, towns do.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Suha Sharma is asking, what is masking? Masking is done very specifically used in BERT, okay, where you mask some tokens.
PAUL: Okay, so probably there are multiple tokens you can think about. So, when you convert them into embeddings, like, with certain numbers, okay, you can put 0, 0, okay, by replacing those numbers, where you actually try to hide something. So, that is referred to as masking.
PAUL: So, in this particular course, okay, in the RAG course, it's all about the downstream task. It's not about the upstream task. You have to understand.
PAUL: Okay, for RAD, it's all about the downstream, because most of the major LLMs that we'll be using with RAD, it will be doing the downstream type of task.
PAUL: Okay? So, please summarize upstream and downstream. Upstream, anything that you do before training. Okay? Downstream, anything that you do post-training, like fine-tuning, one of the simple examples.
PAUL: Is this packed here?
PAUL: Raul Paradas asking, what are… what is POS?
PAUL: Okay, those are referred to as posh tags, NERS referred to as name, entity recognition, QA is referred to as question and answer.
PAUL: See, these are fundamentals around. If you really don't know, okay, you can build an application, but really, you cannot follow research. So, everyone, I want you guys to focus on these things. At least spend one day, 3 to 4 hours, just going through the basics at any point of time.
PAUL: Alright, so is this part clear for everyone? Can I move to the next stage?
PAUL: Okay, somebody's asking, can you have a flow diagram? There is no flow diagram. These are simple two concepts. There is no flow here, that I put.
PAUL: Okay, and it doesn't fit into that.
PAUL: You have to understand, these are the fundamentals of NLP that people have been learning from 2016, 17, 18, RAC came later in 20. Okay?
PAUL: So, there is no relation.
PAUL: Elmo, yes, Elmo, basically, embedding-based models, that was done. Alright.
PAUL: Let's move to the next part.
PAUL: Okay, so now, downstream, whenever I say, you guys will…
PAUL: Basically, so whenever I say downstream, you have to understand it can be any type of task which are mentioned.
PAUL: Waiting for.
PAUL: Now, let's move to the next part of LLMs, and what are the major problems with LLMs that we do face. Because whenever we are working with, LLMs.
PAUL: there has some… there has been one of the major problems, okay? So, let's focus on those. LLM?
PAUL: Okay, problems that I will say here.
PAUL: Now, whenever I'm talking about LLMs, I can use different terms, okay? So, one of the terms is, it can be a base model, I can say.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Or I can use the term foundational model.
PAUL: Okay? So, whenever I use the term base model or foundational model, it means that I'm talking about the original, large language model, or it can be a small language model also, in simple terms.
PAUL: Okay? So, the idea is that it's a language model. So, on top of this model and foundational model, okay, when you try to add some of your custom data.
PAUL: Okay, and you?
PAUL: Build your own SLM or LLM, okay? That task is referred to as a fine-tuning task.
PAUL: So few people were asking the question, like, what is fine-tuning?
PAUL: Whenever you have a base model, it means that, okay, like, somebody has trained some SLM or some LLM, okay, and he has made it open. Now, you thought about, okay, I have my custom data, and I want to build
PAUL: on top of that. Then what you will do, you will pick up that, okay, very specifically, that particular SLM or LLM, okay, and then you will bring your
PAUL: custom data, and then you will train a complete new model from the base model. Now, that is referred to as a fine-tuning task. It means that you are fine-tuning it on top of your custom data.
PAUL: Is this part clear for everyone?
PAUL: Please let me know in the chat.
PAUL: Okay? What is SLM? See, guys, SLM and LLM, the… it is referred to as small language model.
PAUL: Okay, so if anybody is confused with SLMs, it is referred to as small language.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Somebody's asking what is the difference between SLM and LLM? So, any model that has more than 1 billion parameters, okay, they are referred to as LLMs. Anyone below that, probably in millions, like, 50 million, okay, 10 million, those are referred to as SLMs.
PAUL: It totally depends upon the parameters. Both SLM and LLM follow the transformer's architecture at the end of the day.
PAUL: Okay? Because that's why, when I see that, like, the idea is that when you start earning racks, you should have a very good hold on energy. If you really…
PAUL: Because to teach NLG takes 3 to 4 months.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why I cannot teach you transformers. To teach transformers, it will take me 3 classes.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why…
PAUL: These things I won't be discussing, but I'll be sharing the links and probably some videos which will help you to gain those concepts. Okay? So don't ask me to teach Transformers.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: Now, when I'm talking about this fine-tuning task, okay, now this custom data that I am talking about, okay? Now the question comes about, okay, now this data.
PAUL: I have trained the model, and there was some type of data. Now, what will happen after 6 months?
PAUL: If I ask anything, resend to the LLM, can it respond, yes or no?
PAUL: please let me know. For sure, it will not. Okay, so that particular concept is known as
PAUL: knowledge cutoff. This is one of the major problems with any type of Okay, or,
PAUL: any type of SLMs or LLMs. So, I use both of these terms. See, guys? SLMs and LLMs, when I'm talking about, at the end of the day, I'm referring to some type of language model. Always remember that.
PAUL: Now, why this knowledge cutoff? Because there is a cut-off training date.
PAUL: Okay? So, whenever a new model is released, okay?
PAUL: With that model.
PAUL: the team, for example, OpenAir or Anthropic, they always say that, okay, this model has this cut-off running date at any point of time.
PAUL: They will always release the date.
PAUL: Because dates are very, very important when you are working.
PAUL: Okay? Now…
PAUL: this knowledge cut-up is one of the major problems, so that's why we might bring RAG into the picture. Okay, now this is where, or this is how RAG thinks.
PAUL: Then the other problem, okay, now I will move to the next part.
PAUL: Okay, and because of this, there is one major problem. How many of you know about hallucinations? Please let me know.
PAUL: So, for example, I have asked an LLM, okay, tell me what are the latest features in iPhone 17 Pro.
PAUL: Okay, to an LLM, okay, which was trained in 2022.
PAUL: Okay? So, simply, if I ask that, I know that it will throw me some wrong answers at the end of the day, or false information. Yes, correct. Okay? So, simply, I can say, because of this, okay, it will provide me some type of wrong answer.
PAUL: Because I know that, yes, it doesn't have the latest information, so if I ask some type of latest question, how it
PAUL: Okay, so because of this, yes, hallucination is a problem, always.
PAUL: Okay, it's not only about rack, guys. In LLM solves.
PAUL: Don't think about RAGC, guys. Many people are writing RAG also hallucinate. Okay, yes, LLMs also hallucinate. Don't get confused. Anyone.
PAUL: Okay, I'm… until now, I've not told you anything about RAC, so I have told nothing about RAC or vector databases.
PAUL: Okay? So always remember this.
PAUL: I am talking right now with respect to language models only.
PAUL: when I start the paper discussions and others, then I will finally come to RAC. So right now, no RAC. These things are very specific to language models.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: Now, the second main, the second problem is, lack… Oh, input.
PAUL: Okay? So, lack of information, okay, and very specifically, like, in domain-specific tasks.
PAUL: Okay? So, lack of information in domain-specific tasks, okay? Now, the language model which was built, okay, for that, somebody have used some type of data.
PAUL: Okay, now, probably, you want to use that LLM, and if you want to ask me, like, domain-intensive questions, for example, with respect to genetic engineering.
PAUL: Okay, well, probably with respect to, some type of science, I can say, healthcare, pharma, drug discovery, anything like that. Okay, now, if…
PAUL: The language model was not trained on that data, it can never respond.
PAUL: So, right now, like, after 2023, very specifically, people have been building dumil-specific. It means that, okay, now this LLM is only for medical purpose.
PAUL: this LLM is only for, like, I can say healthcare, or this one is only for law, this one is only for mathematics. Okay, this one is only for physics, in that way. They have tried to differentiate.
PAUL: So, this is a very common problem, because when we started back in 2017 and 18, okay, the…
PAUL: data that we have used, it was always small. With respect to time, the size of the data has increased. But again, always, responding correctly for a domain-specific portion, it will not have the knowledge. This is one of the other major problems.
PAUL: Now, because of this major problem, I can say that the rat came into the picture.
PAUL: at any point of time, okay, I feel that, okay, the data that I'm working with, it has no idea.
PAUL: So, the idea of racking.
PAUL: Alright, now let's move to the second one. Okay, so then comes…
PAUL: Lack of proprietary data.
PAUL: Okay, rather than proprietary, let me just keep private here.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: At any point of time, if you want to bring your own organizational data, then what to do?
PAUL: Because before 2021, it was all about training, on training a language model on top of your custom data.
PAUL: Okay, and to train, it's a very resource-intensive task. Okay, I'll be coming to that particular point, but for now, like, there was no way of how to introduce my, private data, or my organization data.
PAUL: Okay? Now, this has been one of the major problems. Okay, now comes another one, like, how many of you know about citations? Please let me know. Citations.
PAUL: This is one of the best things about, right? Okay, so previously in language models, this was not there, which refers to the source. It means that, I told you, okay, now, this is the news. Now, it will tell me, okay, now, from which news channel, or from which news organization, that particular news came.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, any type of models, if I am referring language models, typically cannot cite their sources related to a specific response. Now, this has been always the problem, but with RAG, even we do solve that particular problem.
PAUL: Okay? Now, these are all… there are so many other problems. Okay, so… Then finally comes output generation.
PAUL: Okay, so…
PAUL: Probabilistic output generation.
PAUL: Because of this, also, hallucination comes into the picture. Okay, the output generation in any type of language model is always probabilistic, you have to understand.
PAUL: Okay, so when I'm talking with respect to the probabilistic part, it means that you can change the probability.
PAUL: from 0 to 1. And based on that, the output will change. How many of you know about there is a certain concept about temperature in elegance?
PAUL: If you have worked with LandChain and others, you people might have Howard about that temperature?
PAUL: Based on the changes, okay, you know temperature, alright. So, based on those temperature, you can… if you change that, there will be
PAUL: certain part of the output that will be changed. I cannot say the entire output will be changed, but yes, certain part of the output that will be changed.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So because of that, it's not always a static output you have purchased.
PAUL: So that's why we refer to as the probabilistic output generation. At any point of time, it can change this.
PAUL: Okay, so, recently, like, after 2023, we have been using the term creativity.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, if you change the probability factor, okay, it changes the creativity of the language model. We'll be talking about temperature and others, don't worry, in our upcoming lectures, but for now.
PAUL: I hope you get the core idea that what are the major problems that we do have within this.
PAUL: Yes, everybody got it. Can we move to the next part?
PAUL: loses trusted sources. Okay, I'll be taking all the doubts at the end, don't worry, because today's class is all about the history that I'll be talking about.
PAUL: Yes, context limitations, like, I can make this point more than 50 points, okay, but the idea is not to go, I hope you get the major one. Context limitation is also there for sure.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: No?
PAUL: the question comes about… okay, now, because of these problems, we have introduced rank.
PAUL: Okay, so let's try to understand at least the basics of RAC, okay, and how things will come into the picture.
PAUL: So… The major problem that I face, okay, if I say rack versus LN,
PAUL: Okay? It's a major problem that we do have, okay? It's the trading.
PAUL: Okay? Which is computationally very, very expensive task.
PAUL: To build an LLM, it takes millions of dollars.
PAUL: Okay? So, millions of dollars if you want to build a good LLM from scratch. Okay, so for that, you need a lot of GPUs.
PAUL: when I'm talking about a lot of GPUs, really, the stack is very long. You can think about there is a stack of 100, 200 GPUs, okay, which has been
PAUL: And GPUs are very, very costly.
PAUL: Now, to train this, now the idea is that, okay, how to introduce this? Because not everybody can build their own elements.
PAUL: Okay, if you are sitting in your home, you have a laptop, you cannot bid.
PAUL: Okay, only big organizations
PAUL: can do that, or research labs can do that. Now, this was the main problem, because we have been doing fine-tuning.
PAUL: But really, that task, probably, like, back in 2020 and 2021, I have been training GPT models and BERT models on custom data a lot. But that training used to take time. Probably, I can say, 4 days, 5 days, sometimes 15 days, it depends upon the amount of data.
PAUL: Okay? Because you have the architecture. Once you have any type of deep learning model architecture, you can bring your own data and you can train the model.
PAUL: But to train the model, you need GPUs, which was something costly at the end of the day. And because of these GPUs, like, a lot of other things that comes into the picture. You can think about environmental problems, cooling systems, because these type of systems release a lot of heat and other things.
PAUL: Okay, so then data centers, very specifically for GPU-based data centers, guys.
PAUL: Okay, which are really, very less in the world. The normal data centers running CPU-based instances, they are pretty much found. But GPU-based data centers are very, very less.
PAUL: Vicki?
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: Now, because of this problem, RAC came into the picture, because you can build a rack without the GPUs, that is one of the best things.
PAUL: And every organization is building that.
PAUL: In starting from 2023, that's why every organization is building that. Because you really don't need GPU. If you have a good CPU, then also.
PAUL: But, you have to understand, there are certain, process or parts and rag, okay, which might take time. If you have a GPU, it can be faster, but relatively, it won't be, like, 1 month, or 2 months, or 3 months. Okay, it can be done within a few hours. Okay, at least not in minutes, but at least it can be.
PAUL: done in few hours that you have to understand. So, this rat becomes famous, okay? And LLMs becomes much more limited at any point of time.
PAUL: Okay, so this is a very limited technology that I feel. Not everybody can build their own LLMs, because it costs really millions. Okay, at least to build a good SLM, you have to spend close to, I can say, more than $15,000.
PAUL: To build a small language model.
PAUL: Okay, and that's what people have been doing starting from, like, the 2024 end, I have seen. People are actually not building LLMs, but rather than they are building SLMs on top of the domain-specific data. That has been our common standards now.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Wow.
PAUL: Alright, so, like, see, the camera's this side, okay, and I have, 3 screens, so that's why. Okay, I can change the camera if you want that particular view.
PAUL: Okay, so just wait.
PAUL: All right, let me just switch this one. Okay, now I will come to the RAG architecture. Little bit about the RAG architecture I want to discuss, because once I start, discussing the research paper, okay, you will feel that,
PAUL: a lot of new things that comes. But before that, what is basic RAC? Let's try to understand. Because before jumping into papers, okay, I feel that at least the basics of RAG is important.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Alright, let me just switch on.
PAUL: Alright, so let's start with the basics of track.
PAUL: Okay? So, first of all, what is a full form of rack? Okay, so this is referred to as
PAUL: Retrieval.
PAUL: augmented?
PAUL: Generation.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: As simple as that. Now, what is the concept of, or what is the meaning in English in retrieval? The idea is that it will try to fetch something from somewhere. The idea is simple to fetch. Okay, from somewhere, that somewhere we'll be talking about later on. But, in simple terms, it's fetch. What is the meaning of augmented?
PAUL: Quickly, please let me know. Anybody had heard about augmentation?
PAUL: Data augmentation.
PAUL: Somebody is telling filtered, end reach, improve… okay, alright. Augmented means some type of, like, on top of the original data.
PAUL: Okay? You will do some type of modification.
PAUL: Always remember, this is the actual meaning of augmentation. So, there is a certain concept which is referred to as data augmentation.
PAUL: So, generally, like, data augmentation task is done in computer vision, as well as in natural language processing also. So, for example, a simple example, if I try to give you with respect to data augmentation, okay? So, there is an image.
PAUL: Okay, so, respect to… with an image, okay, so if this is…
PAUL: 9 is written, okay? Now, I will be just doing some type of task, okay, and I will try to just flip this image a little bit.
PAUL: Okay, so, and this will become something like this.
PAUL: Like, now I can say that this was original.
PAUL: Okay? And this is augmented version.
PAUL: Similarly, if I say, like, my name is Paul.
PAUL: And the same thing, Paul is my name.
PAUL: See, I can say the context is same.
PAUL: at any point of time, with respect to the text, an image, actually, you have to do augmentation, okay, by looking into the data, because what happens if I do a 6, and later on, if I try to do a vertical flip, it can become a 9.
PAUL: Okay, now it becomes actually a destructive operation. Okay, but with respect to text, generally it doesn't happen. So this is also an augmented task, but the idea is that the context will be same.
PAUL: So, I can say that more than 99% of the context will be same. On top of that, what you are doing, some type of modification.
PAUL: Is this part clear, with respect to, like, when the term augmented comes? What should be in your mind?
PAUL: Why we need this augmentation? Augmentation actually helps you always to get better output. Okay, the idea is to making the data much more diverse at any point of time.
PAUL: more diverse is your data, better the results. Because in actual scenario, we never know what will happen.
PAUL: We know that, with your original context, there will be some type of noise that can be induced.
PAUL: Okay, so because of that, augmentation is done. Because in the real-world scenarios, it's always about, you know, that my training data cannot be the exact one which is the end user might ask. Okay, so that's why we try to diverse the data, whether it's text data, whether it's vision data, that's the purpose of augmentation.
PAUL: Okay, so similarly, in RAG, okay, like, some type of modified text. So, in RAG, what happens in simple terms, you will get the sources, okay, so…
PAUL: There will be some type of data.
PAUL: I can say that data is stored in VectorDB. I'll be talking about all this concept step by step, but for now, how augmentation comes into the picture, that I will say.
PAUL: Okay, so data vector TV. Okay, now, from that vector TV, I'll be getting the sources.
PAUL: Okay, now those sources will be sent to some type of LLM, okay, and then I will be getting the answer.
PAUL: Okay? Now, these sources are original one.
PAUL: And when it actually goes to the LLM, it will be modified, you have to understand. I cannot say it will be the exact line. There has to be at least 1% modification.
PAUL: Everybody agrees or not.
PAUL: Any time when we send our source data to the LLM, LLM will at least do 1% modification.
PAUL: Okay, so whenever I'm talking, now the modification can be more also, guys, like 20%, 30%, okay, totally depends upon the query that we do ask. Okay, so you have to understand, so that's always some type of modified data, but what is the most important thing? Context.
PAUL: is always retained.
PAUL: Okay, so provami, like I say, some type of rephrasing with respect to English words, but at the end of the day, the context is preserved.
PAUL: Okay, so the actual meaning that we're looking for, the actual output we get.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why this augmented term comes. I hope everybody understands augmented, really. I've never gone in depth just for augmented, okay?
PAUL: I hope everybody gets that.
PAUL: Alright, now somebody's asking, how do we get the context as written? Based on the answer, you can actually verify the answer from the alert. Based on that, you can actually do. We can always check our sources, this part you can always check, and this part also you can check.
PAUL: Okay, so based on that, you can decide whether the context is retained. If the context is not retained, I can say that the output has hallucinated, in simple terms.
PAUL: Okay, I hope you get it.
PAUL: Alright guys, so now, rag part and generation, I hope everybody understands the meaning of generation. I don't need to explain that part, okay?
PAUL: Please let me know. Because, generation is also a downstream task, that's why. Okay, if I take… okay, so generation comes here. Text generation.
PAUL: Okay, so, text generation is also referred to as a downstream task.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is to generate text. In simple terms, the idea is to generate text.
PAUL: Alright, so here also, the main part, the idea is to fetch some data.
PAUL: After fetching the data, that data will be modified, and finally, based on that modified data, the final response that you will be getting from the LLM, it will be generated. So, who is doing the generation? LLM.
PAUL: Okay, generation is always being done by the LLM, very, very important.
PAUL: Okay, LLM is actually responsible to do the task.
PAUL: Perfect.
PAUL: Now, I will come to the, now, core RAG parts, guys, okay? So, RAD…
PAUL: Simple architecture, I will say, for now. Because going forward, the architecture will change in a lot of ways.
PAUL: Okay, rag, simple architecture.
PAUL: No sir, we do need to build.
PAUL: What is the difference between embedding and encoding?
PAUL: Embedding is basically on top of your text, data that you do. It can be images also. Encoding is basically, if you think about encoding, embedding is one type of encoding.
PAUL: Okay, but, like, we cannot see the opposite.
PAUL: Alright, guys, I will not look into the questions, let's focus on the architecture, and then I will take, because if I start taking questions, totally will be going out, okay? So…
PAUL: So, let's start with the simple architecture. Everybody, please don't write in the chat, because I won't be looking. So right now, just focus, on the core part that we are discussing.
PAUL: So, in simple terms, what we can say? So, like, RAG is a technique, okay, so using which we can bring our external data, okay, to get better accuracy at any point of time.
PAUL: Okay? Because LLMs, we know that it cannot connect to external data.
PAUL: But, if we use RAG very specifically, we can bring our external data, okay, and based on that, we can get the
PAUL: Okay, so the first step that comes is bringing your data. What is referred? That is referred to as data ingestion.
PAUL: This is the first part, at any point of time, data ingestion.
PAUL: Okay? To bring your own data, you can think about external knowledge sources.
PAUL: Okay? Now, here you can think about any type of file format, okay? PDFs, HTML.
PAUL: JSON, CSV.
PAUL: Okay? Then comes your, Xls… Okay, then come docs… PPTX…
PAUL: Any type of file format that you can think about. External knowledge sources.
PAUL: Okay, that is the core idea. Now, during the data integration process, what happens? Like, any type of company, if I take the example, okay, so, like any type of proprietary company.
PAUL: Okay, now see guys, I have told about these are all tech sources, okay? So, yes, I can actually differentiate these things much more than I can bring into, image.
PAUL: Okay, for images, you can think about, Gifs. Okay, JPG.
PAUL: Okay, I hope everybody understands the list goes long and long, really. Okay, then TIF.
PAUL: Okay. Then comes audio. This also… Is your source.
PAUL: Okay, probably HTT formats.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, so similarly, like, for videos also.
PAUL: The list is long, it can be any type of data source.mpv4.mov.
PAUL: Okay, so all these type, so any type of file format that you can think of.
PAUL: Okay, so these are the major ones. I have taken all the multimodal things also. So, text, okay, and these are all multimodals. Okay, so this term is referred to as the multimodal
PAUL: Multimodal sources, okay? And these are very specifically tech sources.
PAUL: No,
PAUL: So, during dataization, what happens? The idea is that some type of organization will bring their own custom data, or proprietary data of their organization, and they will load it, okay?
PAUL: Now the question comes, they will load that, external sources. Now the question comes, where they will load.
PAUL: Yes?
PAUL: Where they will load, That is the second part, which is about the vector databases.
PAUL: Okay? Now, before understanding vector databases, let's try to understand what is a vector.
PAUL: Yes, so simply, you can tell me what is a vector in simple terms.
PAUL: Multimodal source means images, audio, those type of things.
PAUL: And text also, like, mixed with images and everything.
PAUL: Okay, it's some type of 2D data, all right, directional data in simple terms.
PAUL: Okay? All right. So in physics, that is the actual meaning of vectors, okay. But here, vector databases is basically, in a simple representation, this will be some type of numbers.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: The most important thing.
PAUL: Okay, so it is a number representation.
PAUL: Okay, so if I say that my Name… Is… Fold.
PAUL: Now, the idea is that I will change mine to 0.1, I can change name to 0.8, okay, 0.9, okay, and this becomes 0.75.
PAUL: Okay? Now, when you try to create an array of this, so 0.1,
PAUL: Comma 0.8, comma 0.9, okay, 0.75.
PAUL: Okay, now this is a numeric representation. Okay, now what I have done, I have converted my text data into some type of numerical representation.
PAUL: Okay, so it's not necessary binary numbers, it can mean floating numbers also.
PAUL: Okay, numeric representation of data. Now, you can think about if you have some type of algorithm to do this, okay? I can say that, yes, it can be. Okay, now, if you have an algorithm, because right now, this is random that I've written, but when you do it using some type of algorithms.
PAUL: Okay, then it is referred to as an embedding.
PAUL: The concept of embedding started back in 2014. Okay, and these are, like, the pure NLP concepts, okay? So, can you tell me some of the older embedding techniques? Anybody who has learned NLP? I will write a few of them here.
PAUL: Backup words, how many of you have heard about these type of concepts?
PAUL: TFIDF?
PAUL: Concurrency matrix.
PAUL: what to wake?
PAUL: Okay, sentence to wake, yeah, para to wake, all those.
PAUL: Seabao, somebody told, so under what to wake only, I can say that, okay, Seabao, and Skip Gram comes into the picture.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Positional encodings, great.
PAUL: Lemmatization and stemming, no. Nagapan, does not.
PAUL: Okay, now positional encoding…
PAUL: Okay, now this is actually not an embedding algorithm, but it is much more, okay, that's why we'll put a star here, because this is not an…
PAUL: embedding algorithm, you have to understand. Okay, it's much more of an encoding algorithm, which is used.
PAUL: Yes, Murthaza. Correct. The most famous one nobody told about, okay, one hot encoding.
PAUL: This is the one which people have been using for decades.
PAUL: Okay? Now, people who don't know about these things, please…
PAUL: After the class, try to go through this.
PAUL: Okay, LMO is also one type of embedding, correct?
PAUL: Okay, the list is, guys, really long. Okay, so I don't want to jump into this one. Ngrams, correct?
PAUL: Okay, so the list is really long, but these are a few of the common ones which have been used quite a lot and classically.
PAUL: Okay? Now, the idea is that we will be creating similar embeddings, but for you, you really do need to know, okay, there will be some type of embedding model, that's the best thing. Okay, so, in your case, what will happen? You need to…
PAUL: Convert the text data, whatever the text data.
PAUL: Okay, or slash, I will write here, multimodal data.
PAUL: Means images, audio, those things. That needs to be converted into some type of numbers.
PAUL: And those numbers I'll be referring as embeddings.
PAUL: Always remember this.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Now, these embeddings, for this particular embeddings, you will be choosing a model.
PAUL: Okay, and I'll be showing you, like, what are the top best models that are available. Okay, it is available under the MTV leaderboard in Hugging Face.
PAUL: From here, we take the decision, that, okay, out of the top 10 models, right now, we can select one. So, for example, any embedding model that you guys know, for example, there is Gemini embedding model from Google.
PAUL: Okay, Gemini embedding models, then, you have?
PAUL: From OpenAI, Text3 small.
PAUL: Okay? Hugging phase, all mini LM6, correct?
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Oh, yes, OpenAI, okay?
PAUL: text, ADA models, that is deprecated right now, Raul Gumasin, but yes, Nomik. I love Nomic a lot. This is open source completely, okay?
PAUL: Now, we have two things. See, the list is really long. I can show you more than 200 embedding models, guys, but you have to understand that, okay, now, these are a few of the major models.
PAUL: From Amazon, there is something called as Titan Embeddings that also comes into the picture. Okay, the list is long, but you have to understand that few embedding algorithms are open source, and few are paid.
PAUL: Okay, so when you actually go for embeddings, one is the open source one.
PAUL: Okay, and the second one is speed.
PAUL: So, in the open source section, like,
PAUL: you have… majorly, all of them are available in Hugging Face.
PAUL: Okay, so directly in the Hugging Face model section, you'll be getting all the open source, but in the paid ones, like Gemini, that comes from Google, OpenAI, okay, they have really not open sourced the algorithm, you have to understand. They have kept it as a proprietary embedding model.
PAUL: Okay, so some things are paid, and some things are open source, okay? So you really need to decide when you are actually going for… do you want to use
PAUL: A paid algorithm, or an open source algorithm.
PAUL: Okay? Then you have OLAM. Olama embedding models, yes, using… in Olama, we use Nomic models major. Okay? So, this decision is totally up to you, and you have to always check, like, what is the best right now in the market? Select something out of top 10, I will say.
PAUL: Because in top 10, you will have open source as well as paid, both.
PAUL: What is the difference between embedding algorithms? I see, embedding algorithms are basically… what is the meaning of embedding algorithm?
PAUL: The algorithm which will convert your text
PAUL: Okay, or images, something like that, you can think about into that numeric representation.
PAUL: Okay? Now, few of them have open-sourced the algorithm, and few of them have not open-sourced. They have kept it as a proprietary, and they take money.
PAUL: Okay? That is simply referred to as the algorithm, the embedding actual algorithm.
PAUL: I'll be coming to embedding algorithms when we will go deep dive into embeddings, but this class is about the RAT
PAUL: basic components.
PAUL: Okay? So, don't worry about that, because for embeddings, there is a… will be a dedicated class.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: Now, I hope everybody understood, okay, what is the simple idea of embeddings? Okay, what are the types of embeddings, okay, from where you will get. Now, these embeddings are saved inside a vector data.
PAUL: Okay, now this is where your vector TV comes into the picture.
PAUL: Okay, so inside your vector TV, what you save? The embedings.
PAUL: Is this part clear? Okay, now for vector TVs also, you have, again, the same stuff. Okay, open source vector TVs are there.
PAUL: Okay, and again, paid versions are also there.
PAUL: Okay, now this is just like a database. Now, database needs to be hosted when you are in production. How many of you agree?
PAUL: Whenever you are building an application for production, it needs to be hosted somewhere.
PAUL: Okay, similarly, VectorDB also, it needs to be hosted somewhere.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: So that's why, like, one of… we will start with Fires, okay, and open source from Facebook, then you have Chroma.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And the list is really long. If I show you, okay, I will show you more than 200 vector databases. Pinecone is there, correct. Vivate is there. My favorite is QuadTrend.
PAUL: Okay? PostgreSQL, no. PostgreSQL, not. It is called as TGVector.
PAUL: Okay? So, whoever is talking about Suraj, I think. Yes, Redis has a vector database, Momo has a vector database, IBM vector database, everybody. The list is very long, guys. So, really, you have to understand there are different type of vector databases, as simple as that. Open search, serverless.
PAUL: Okay? Neo4j is a graph database.
PAUL: Amiltas, okay? So, don't write so much thing wrong. Alright. Now, this was a poor idea. It means that, first, you will be getting the data from different type of external sources, okay? So, for data ingestion.
PAUL: Once you have the data, you will convert that data into some type of numeric representation, which is referred to as the embedding. Once you have that particular embedding, that embedding needs to be saved in some type of vector database.
PAUL: Is this part clear for everyone?
PAUL: Create Victor databases.
PAUL: Please ask these questions later on, okay? Don't worry, there are so many paid.
PAUL: And, I will be using most of the time paid stuff in class, so don't worry.
PAUL: Alright, let's go for a 15-minute break. Even I forget, guys, okay, you guys can, always…
PAUL: what's the time now? It's 10-12. I think we can go ahead for more 20 minutes, and then… yes, from 10.30 we can do the break. Or you need a break, please let me know.
PAUL: Okay, most of them are telling, let's do the break from 10.30, because it's just been one hour. I know it's theoretical, that's why, a little bit boring stuff, but two classes you have to appear before starting the actual practice.
PAUL: Alright, so 10.30, we will go for a break. Okay, so in the open source tab, in the page tab, let me write, quadrant.
PAUL: Quartrend has an open source version also, we create… Then, Zillis, my favorite.
PAUL: for, large-scale, data, I use it.
PAUL: Okay, so…
PAUL: the list is long, and really, it keeps on going. Now, you understood that, okay, now from here, there is a database where your text data, image data, or any type of data is saved into numeric representation.
PAUL: Now, the next part. Okay, so I can say…
PAUL: The second part was vector databases. Within that vector databases comes your embeddings, so let me just write your third.
PAUL: Okay, then comes a retrieval. The concept of retrieval now comes into the picture.
PAUL: Okay? Now, to understand dread travel.
PAUL: How many of you know the concept of DPR?
PAUL: There's passage retrieval.
PAUL: Now, you will understand what is the need of that MBT. Okay, don't worry.
PAUL: Okay, step by step, things will become clear, because so many concepts
PAUL: are there. Okay, so, don't worry.
PAUL: Alright, anybody has heard about DPR? Please let me know, because this is a big concept that comes in NLP.
PAUL: With respect to the retrieval, Alright, looks like…
PAUL: Alright, so before, DPR, let me…
PAUL: How many of you know about… by encoders.
PAUL: Anybody has heard the term biencoders? Two encoders say buy means two, in simple terms.
PAUL: Yes, DPR uses, so now DPR uses two encoders, you have to remember this.
PAUL: Okay. Now, before RAG,
PAUL: before RAG came into the picture, okay? Generally, when we are working with language models, there was this particular concept of DPR. Okay, so based on DPR only, the RAG came into the picture.
PAUL: why I'm talking about this concept, because
PAUL: Many of you might not have known, but if you actually look into the research paper, you will see DPR term will be used a lot.
PAUL: Okay? Because this is the actual fundamental from where the retrieval came into the picture. Okay? In simple terms, let me just try to tell, like, how you can think about, like, how the architecture looks like, okay? So, just think about, you have two encoders, okay? So, the first encoder that you have
PAUL: Okay, so two encoder blocks that I am drawing right now. Okay, so one of the encoders is just, like, a cushion encoder that you can think about.
PAUL: Okay. So, question… encoder.
PAUL: Okay, and the other one is a passage, or basically the response-based encoder that you can think about.
PAUL: In the actual research paper, these terms are used, potion and passage, for DPM.
PAUL: Okay. Now, what happens? Now, this encoder, first, what it will do? It will convert it into
PAUL: Let's take the… into some type of embedding, okay? So, let's take, queue for now. Q embedding.
PAUL: Okay? And this will do a P-embedding.
PAUL: Okay? Now, two encoders are there, both of the encoders are performing an embedding operation, okay? Now, the idea is that you will be performing a comparison, okay? Or basically, if you want to find any type of similarity between that.
PAUL: Okay, so for example, if somebody is asking a question, now, based on that question, like, if I say, what is my name? Okay. Now, what is my name? That will be, again, converted into some type of embedding, and it will try to look
PAUL: Through the passage encoder, because, again, the passage encoder, whatever the data is there, okay, it will be converted into embeddings. It means that anything that goes through this, and anything that goes through this, because
PAUL: Okay, everything is in the form of embedding. Now, the idea is you will be comparing both of them.
PAUL: Just to check.
PAUL: Okay, so one of the simplest mathematical terms that you might have used, which is similarity, okay?
PAUL: Cosine similarity.
PAUL: Okay, cosine similarity, you can think about, dot similarity.
PAUL: The idea is to compare, okay, how close they each are.
PAUL: Okay? In simple terms, or how they are correlated
PAUL: Poor relation, actually, you cannot directly calculate the poor relation, Shivaji, but you have to understand.
PAUL: Okay, so how close they are?
PAUL: Simple terms, with respect to their numeric representations.
PAUL: Now, this particular concept that you have, it is referred to as a DPR.
PAUL: Okay, so at any point of time, whenever we say… okay, because the term, this DPR is also called as neural retriever, I don't know.
PAUL: Okay, but similar terms, the meaning is same always.
PAUL: Because in the research paper, when we will go through, you might see these terms. The idea is that you should be familiar. Okay, the idea here is to find semantic similarity. This is the most important thing, because at the end of the day, we want to find the semantic similarity.
PAUL: Semantic similarity.
PAUL: I can say, if something is more similar, okay, then yes, those two things are much more related, Derek.
PAUL: So, that's Euclidean distance also correct. You can use Euclidean distance
PAUL: Manhattan distance, Jacquardian Index, okay, the list is really long if you want to really find out the similarity. Okay, I'm not talking about all those things, but you have to understand the most famous ones I'm talking about.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: Now, the next part, okay, so as the retrieval concept, you guys have understand, in simple terms, okay? Now,
PAUL: For this, now the question comes, if you want to do… there are DPR-based models in Hugging Face.
PAUL: Okay? So, those DPR-based models, actually, you can explore. Okay, so with respect to some practical implementation, do you want to really see how DPR works, or something like that, you can let me know.
PAUL: DPR is… already I told you, DPR is a retrieval technique, where you have two different types of encoders. Both of the encoders will perform an encoding… embedding operation. Now, you will try to compare those embeddings, okay?
PAUL: What if the use case is not a use case, you can think about simple, I can take two sentences and I can compare.
PAUL: Really, that is the core idea. Okay, so for example, okay, so I have to actually look into the Hugging Face model. I will stop sharing the screen. Okay, a little bit, let's try to understand that how exactly we get numbers at the end of the day.
PAUL: Because entire thing that we have, it's all about numbers. Deep learning is all about numbers, that's why.
PAUL: Now I will start sharing my screen. I think this is desktop 3.
PAUL: Alright, I do have a course template with me. Let me just open collab… Wooden?
PAUL: New notebook.
PAUL: Just wait, because I'll be executing a piece of code
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Now, really, this piece of code is not related to RAC, but if you really want to go depth in retrieval, because the research in retrieval is really, like, more than 2 years, so a lot of good retrieval papers are there.
PAUL: Alright, now I'll be showing you some examples with respect to Hugging Face. Let me just copy a piece of code that I already have, okay?
PAUL: Alright, yes.
PAUL: So…
PAUL: The idea is, see, you need two different type of encoders, okay, so that's why, very specifically, there are some type of DPR models, okay? And this DPR model, why I'm taking Hugging Face, because the research come from Hugging Face, guys. So that's why DPR question encoder, single NQ base, this is a model.
PAUL: Okay? And then you have this, DPSTX encoder single in Q case, as you can see.
PAUL: Okay? So, two different type of encoding models that I have. Yes, you can use any encoding models, but I'm going just based on the research which was done by Facebook here. Okay?
PAUL: Now, here, you can see, like, once we have defined the model that we are doing… Now, how many of you have used transformers? Because this is pure NLP. That's why, really, I want to understand that, are you comfortable with this syntax and code?
PAUL: Please let me know, because… And if you cannot understand the code only, then it becomes very problem.
PAUL: No, sir.
PAUL: not comfortable.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: In high level, I'll be telling you the code, okay? See, from transformers, import the potion encoder, and the potion encoder tokenizer. So, what happens whenever you are working with transformers, or in Hugging Face? Every model has its own tokenizer.
PAUL: Please try to understand. Now, don't ask me what is tokenizer.
PAUL: Because, really, those are NLP basics. Anybody who doesn't know tokenizer, or tokenization.
PAUL: Okay. Most of you know about tokenization, then good.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: So, now this is a very specific model that I'm just importing. Okay, and this is also a very specific model. So, for that particular model, I have a tokenizer.
PAUL: Similarly. Okay, so if I use a part model, for that part, I have a tokenizer. If I go with distalbot, another distal part tokenizer. If I go with Robata, the list of models is really long, so…
PAUL: Again, face, model, okay.
PAUL: there are more than one lap models. So, really, I cannot teach you these things, because the idea is that you should, at least have the basics, okay? So, please explore this part.
PAUL: Okay, now as you can see, so these are a lot of LLMs that you can see. Now, let's pick up a task, okay, like, text generation.
PAUL: Now in text generation…
PAUL: Again, a lot of, as you can see, so these are different type of open source models that are available.
PAUL: Now, OpenAI GPT OSS, really a very good model. I use the 20 billion one. Okay, Google, Gemma. So, these are all different type of models that you have. So, when you are actually training a model, for that model architecture, you will always have a tokenizer operation.
PAUL: Alright, then comes the cosine similarity, okay, which will actually compare the two embeddings and give you a certain score. Now, this I am taking from PyTorch.
PAUL: Okay? So, this is a simple implementation of DPR. The idea is first to load the models and the tokenizer. So, this is the part from where, from the Facebook repo, I'm downloading the model, and then I'm just performing a tokenizing operation.
PAUL: Similarly, for the context encoder also. So, the quotient encoder and the context encoder.
PAUL: Okay, so these are totally open-source models that I am using. Now, you can use some other importer models also, like BERT-based models.
PAUL: Now, see, here, this is a question. Okay, so the idea is to encode the question, okay, and here, see, this is a simple example, like, who wrote Hamlet?
PAUL: A simple example that we have taken. And then, based on that, we are performing our tokenizer operation, so we are actually calling this tokenizer here.
PAUL: Okay? And here, very specifically, here we are passing the question, and the return type is PT. What is PT?
PAUL: PyTorch.
PAUL: How many of you know, like, the tensor type written will be PyTorch type? Okay, so this is how… this is simple NLP, guys. If you are, you can simply skip this part, but if anybody's interested, you can focus this part.
PAUL: Similarly, like, encoding the passage. It means that some type of embedding that you will create. So this is… that's why Q underscore EMP and P underscore EMP.
PAUL: Okay? So this is the actual embedding.
PAUL: And finally, you try to compare the scores through cosine similarity, like, as you can say, print scores.
PAUL: Okay, you will be getting the final cosine similarity score, so let me just print it out. It will be a tensor, and this is the similarity score that cosine
PAUL: is throwing, okay, between the two embeddings. So I can say that, yes, this is some type of semantic similarity score that the algorithm is throwing.
PAUL: Okay, so this is how you compare Oliver's two embeddings.
PAUL: I hope you get it. Okay, because I have taken a pure NLP model.
PAUL: Okay, and I have shown you, like, this is how you try to compare the embeddings. Yes, I'll be sharing this, don't worry.
PAUL: Okay, but, this is a poor idea. If you are not comfortable with this, simply escape, because really, for RAG,
PAUL: You don't need to know the retrieval research so much.
PAUL: Okay, but retrieval research is based on purely language models.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, the idea was to show you how to compare to embeddings, and based on that, I'll be getting some score. Okay? Now, higher the score, better the result, always remember.
PAUL: Higher the score, better the result.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Now, based on this, okay, so I think I can go back to my notes now.
PAUL: Because I have two embeddings gradual, as simple as that.
PAUL: Alright, so… advanced, let me just get back to the…
PAUL: Because I will, complete the… architecture part.
PAUL: Alright. So, with respect to the retrieval, because… The retrieval part is…
PAUL: The idea is to fetch out some type of score, okay?
PAUL: So, in the retrieval part, in simple terms, what will happen? So, any type of relevant data based on the similarity score. Okay, we will try to fetch that. Fetch…
PAUL: relevant.
PAUL: data, From where?
PAUL: from the vector DB.
PAUL: Because in VectorDB, you have embeddings.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: So, because of that, you can do a comparison. Okay, now how the comparison will be done? So, let's try to understand.
PAUL: Okay, so for the retrieval, to do any type of retrieval task, you need a question.
PAUL: Just think about the question slash query.
PAUL: Okay, that query, like, if I ask, like, what is my name? That will be converted into MBT.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And already in your vector databases, you have embeddings.
PAUL: Okay? Now, the idea is to compare this one with this one. How relevant they are. Okay, so for that one… the same algorithm, cosine similarity, has been used a lot.
PAUL: Okay, now this algorithm that can be used.
PAUL: So that's why the concept of DPR came into the picture. That's why I told you a little bit about DPR. Because you have already existing embeddings in your vector database. Now, when some query is asked to the system, that query will be converted into embedding, and that embedding will be actually compared with your vector DB list of embeddings.
PAUL: And based on that, you'll be getting some type of… semantic.
PAUL: Similarity.
PAUL: Okay, reserved.
PAUL: Okay, now, probably it can be a list of embeddings, or only embeddings. Okay, so when you try to compare, yeah, it will simply say that, okay, now, if I take this as E1,
PAUL: Okay? And this is as V, okay? Because vector database, that's why. Now, E1…
PAUL: context can be there, improbably, like, I can say V11
PAUL: V12V13. Okay, now these are different type of… data sources.
PAUL: Well, you can think about, probably, in the vector databases, there you have uploaded 100 documents. Out of those 100 documents, like, one document is V11, the other document is V32, then the other document is V13.
PAUL: Okay, in simple terms. Okay, so different type of data sources. So, based on this, for everyone, you'll be getting a similarity score. It means that, okay, this one, I can say that the score was 0.4. For this one, I can say it's 0.6. Or for this one, it was 0.8.
PAUL: Okay, so that is basically the similarities for that email.
PAUL: I hope this part is clear, like, how we try to fetch something, the retrieval part.
PAUL: Please let me know with a yes or no.
PAUL: Both sides similarities, similar, both are same.
PAUL: Huh.
PAUL: Semantic similarity, the algorithm is little bit different.
PAUL: All right, guys, so I hope this part is done. Okay, so after the retrieval, what happens now comes the stage of augmentation, okay?
PAUL: So, this is the fourth stage.
PAUL: The augmentation stage.
PAUL: So, in the stage of augmentation, very specifically, what is the thing? It means that some type of modification that will happen. Now, here, you know that, okay, so when we did, okay, it tried to fetch some type of sources from the vector DB, okay, or some type of documents, if I say, in separate terms.
PAUL: Now, somebody's asking why V11 and not V1? It can be any number. It can be P0, B0, C0. The idea was it was some type of sign, okay? So don't get confused.
PAUL: Are embeddings built in Vector TV? No.
PAUL: Vector DB is different, embeddings are different.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Is the retrieval done by LLM? No. Right now, there is no LLM only. Till now, I have taught all the components. Till now, LLM doesn't come into the picture.
PAUL: Alright, we will be taking a break, just wait, I think 10.34. Alright, we can take a break of 10 minutes, okay? And let me just take a few questions in that 10 minutes. I feel that people are asking very simple questions, and we can take that, okay? So, just wait. I will just start the clock.
PAUL: I think I have the clock.
PAUL: Just wait. And in the meantime, people who have some doubts, they can just raise their hand. For 10 minutes, I'll be taking questions.
PAUL: Okay, it's a parade, guys, whoever wants a parade.
PAUL: Mmm… clock, yeah.
PAUL: Alright, so… let me just start taking some questions. I will switch off the video.
PAUL: Alright, anybody who has questions, they can quickly raise their hand. Okay, no screen sharing, only just short questions, that is the idea. And in the chat also, you can write, okay, let's start with Swatika, okay? Then, Asar, Prathamish, Athare.
PAUL: Pratamehatri, okay.
PAUL: Guys, please quickly.
Prathmesh Atre: Hello, sir, hi.
PAUL: Yes.
Prathmesh Atre: Actually, I have a question, in that, when we say embedding techniques, we have… we've seen a lot of embedding techniques in ALP, like BOW and TF-IDF.
Prathmesh Atre: So, when we have the actually embedding model, right, does internally it is using that specific technique, or it is already trained on some data, like, this is the text, and this is…
PAUL: You were correct. See, whenever we are… I'm talking about a model, model is always about weights and biases. So, yes, the mod… it has been trained on some type of data, and in that model, you have the weights.
PAUL: Okay, so yes, it has been triggered.
Prathmesh Atre: Okay, so it means it is not internally using any technique, but already on the pre-trained data, it is giving the embedded.
PAUL: On top of an algorithm, it has always… it has been trained, in simple terms.
Prathmesh Atre: Right, right. But later on, it is not using that.
PAUL: Yes, yes. Like,
PAUL: For RAG embedding models, it is done. But simple, like, for one-hot importing, really, you don't need to train. It's pretty much simple, that you have to understand.
Prathmesh Atre: And most of the time, like, do you know, like, on which algorithm or technique it is built upon?
PAUL: what I told, some things are open source, and some things are proprietary. Okay, so, like, if I'm talking about proprietary, we really don't, but they are.
PAUL: If I'm talking about open source based, then there are a lot of models which are from the DubSik family, okay, from Momic family. Okay, they have their research paper, and there is a mathematical formula that they will… they use a lot.
Prathmesh Atre: also…
PAUL: Every… every embedding model has a different mathematical form.
Prathmesh Atre: Right.
PAUL: Okay, so if you ask me, like, exactly what is the formula, if you ask about a specific model, you have to go to the research paper of that particular model, and you have to check what is the underlying mathematics.
Prathmesh Atre: Right, so also, like, when you say we have augmentation, but why, after retrieving any kind of data from the vector database, you know, through any kind of similarity search techniques, we got some top K chunks, right? Then why don't we directly pass it to LLM, and why there is in-between augmentation part, in between retrieval and generation?
PAUL: Okay, now augmentation is the actual… in augmentation, what happens? The retrieve data… okay.
PAUL: and the user query, because both the things comes into the picture. Your user query embedding, and the retro data embedding, okay? So, both will be combined with the prompt.
PAUL: And that particular prompt, like, it can be anything, like how we want the LLM to respond for that particular… it'll be using some type of prompt. Okay, and that particular… these three information goes to the LLM.
PAUL: the user query, the retriek data, okay? Now, whenever you are actually passing these three information, okay, then the augmentation step happens. It means that whatever the original data that was fetched from the vector TV, that will be modified based on the user query.
PAUL: Okay, and even the prompt that you are passing.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why that particular modification happens, because of that augmentation term came into the picture.
Prathmesh Atre: Then, who is actually responsible? Like, what's the internal thing that is doing this augmentation?
PAUL: It will be the LLM, no?
PAUL: If your prompt changes, the response will change, so it's dialed…
Prathmesh Atre: Okay.
Prathmesh Atre: Okay, so…
PAUL: Rotted or written?
Prathmesh Atre: Let's move to the next one.
PAUL: Quickly.
Swagatika: Hello, sir?
PAUL: Yes.
Swagatika: So, what is vector data? Is it, like, some kind of SQL database, or what is vector data?
PAUL: It's… you can think about it's like a database, but it saved numbers only.
PAUL: I told you numeric representation.
PAUL: It saved only numeric representation.
Swagatika: We can store data here, or where it gets data.
PAUL: Not only I told, you can save numerical representation data.
PAUL: Not text data.
PAUL: you ask, can I save SQL data now?
PAUL: Can I say Mongo data? Okay, or NoSQL data? I hope you get it.
Swagatika: Okay, thanks.
PAUL: Okay, okay, so…
PAUL: Krishna is asking where exactly temperature comes into the picture, so when you actually, define the LLM, then you have to define the temperature of the LLM.
PAUL: Till now, we have not come to that point, and practicals will be seeing that.
PAUL: Okay, anybody else want to ask a question, please let me know in the chat.
PAUL: So… I have a question about TPR Lagunar… Lagunar… Yes.
Lagna Ray: Oh, yeah.
Lagna Ray: Good morning. So, like, I just wanted to know about the DPR. So, in the traditional retrieval augmented generation, that architecture, we have one, like, phase called document ingestion phase, and another one is the query processing phase. So, how DPR, like, is it the same thing? Because in the
Lagna Ray: document ingestion phase, we have to divide the data into chunking, then you have to do the embedding, then query processes, we have to query the embedding, then we have to do all this re-ranking, all these things, similar research by using those.
PAUL: Yes, yes.
Lagna Ray: chair.
PAUL: Okay, so in there.
Lagna Ray: Is it doing both those pages?
PAUL: In DPR, it's pretty much simple. You have two things, like question and answer.
PAUL: Okay. Generally, it's a passage, okay? Based on that, you'll be getting, so you have a question that is converted into an embedding. Okay, now on the other encoder, you have your list of passages, or list of answers.
PAUL: That it will try to fetch out. All those answers are converted into embeddings. Now, the idea is to compare both the embeddings through cosine similarity. Okay, the same thing happens in RAG also. In RAG, what happens? You have all the embeddings in a vector database.
PAUL: And that user query becomes that question. Okay, now you try to compare the segment. So, it's actually the same thing.
Lagna Ray: Okay.
PAUL: RAT, it's actually the DPR.
PAUL: Okay, which is responsible for the reclaimer part.
Lagna Ray: So, can we consider the DPR is the, like, it's kind of the originate of the, like, from the DPR, we can orientate the rack, or…
PAUL: It is the backbone of Prague.
Lagna Ray: Okay, okay. And, like, LLM would be the solely responsible for doing all this activity?
PAUL: LLM is… LLM is only responsible for the generation part. In RAD, you have that G, generation is responsible, okay? Because to generate, you need context. Now, to find better context, you use DPR, so that you get better context from vector team, okay?
Lagna Ray: Okay, okay, okay. I think we, after going this research paper only, this all, this idea will be much.
PAUL: Yes, like, let me see whether I can do it, or in the next class, I will be doing it.
Lagna Ray: Okay, yeah, thank you so much for your answer.
PAUL: Alright, next, there is, we want to ask a question, Rithpesh Maheshwari, when we are importing, is it done on cloud? It can be done in local, Rithvish, okay?
PAUL: Yes, Priya is asking, I want to ask a question, sir. Priya.
PAUL: Really, many people have raised hands, guys, so every question I cannot take, but… Yeah, I cannot see.
PAUL: Alright, let's move to the next participant.
PAUL: Semantic layer, right now, we are not talking about that, okay, so don't worry.
PAUL: Because for semantic, a lot of things others.
PAUL: Fikari Musa.
PAUL: Fikrim Musa is asking, can we understand DPR better? This is NLP concept, so really.
PAUL: That you need to dive into the classical NLP.
PAUL: Because to understand DPR, okay, the original research paper, it might take two lectures only for…
PAUL: Okay, so that's why I don't want to go on a depth. I was to compare the retrieval, but what is the actual research that is going on? That's what I have to do.
PAUL: Manasa, may you want to ask a question? Yes, Manasa, I will unmute.
PAUL: Yeah, I will share the collab link, don't worry.
PAUL: good understanding of basic will work. Basic will work, gradual, but at the end.
Manasa Madabhushi: Hello, sir, am I out?
PAUL: You need to have a good understanding if you want to crack a good technical interview.
PAUL: Yes, please go ahead, Manas, with your question.
Manasa Madabhushi: I have two questions. First one is, you have listed the… some of the reasons, what are the drawbacks of LLMs, in that you mentioned probabilistic output generation. I would like to understand how it is a problem.
PAUL: How it is a problem. The problem is basically, the answer is not always static, it becomes dynamic. For example, when we'll be doing the practicals, you'll be coming.
PAUL: do a certain parameter called as temperature. If you change the temperature, the output changes. I can say the context is retained, but somehow there will be some type of changes with respect to the output.
PAUL: Then, when you'll be doing the practical, you will be getting that.
Manasa Madabhushi: Okay, it is similar to hallucination, right?
PAUL: No, no, no, it's not similar to a hallucination. It's referred to as the creativity of the model, that temperature. You can simply look about what is temperature in an LLM, you will understand the concept.
PAUL: Okay?
Manasa Madabhushi: Okay, sir, and another thing is, like, we have some… for vector database, we have open source and paid, right? In that we have, ChromaDB and all, why can't we store them in normal SQL? Why are we moving into different things?
PAUL: Because SQL is completely tabular-based, and this is vector-based.
PAUL: They are totally different. It means that Like…
PAUL: See, the architectures are totally different. That's why, in simple terms, if I say.
PAUL: In SQL, simply, you can save numbers, but here, the list of numbers are very, very long. It can be, like.
PAUL: high dimensional, very high dimensional, if I'm talking about SQL cannot do that. SQL has a lot of limitations.
PAUL: It's, like, nobody uses SQL for, like, deep learning tasks, very specifically. Or your generic type of task for your normal software development, it's fine.
PAUL: But really, when you are working with high dimension numbers, like 1 billion parameters, 8 billion parameters, okay, really, that is not a solution.
Manasa Madabhushi: Okay, all these questions are…
PAUL: Like, deep learning questions, not really, architectural questions.
PAUL: Okay, could you share the fundamentals, like, tokenization? I will be sharing this, because these are NLP fundamentals.
PAUL: R is asking, can you please answer? I have a question? How deep we need to learn about these concepts? It's totally up to you. If you want to crack a technical interview, you need to know about depth.
PAUL: You don't want to crack a technical interview if you're looking for some type of business rules, you really don't need to go in-depth.
Manasa Madabhushi: Sir, another one, the Red Tribal, you have explained, right? So, it belongs to pure, natural language processing, so where can we learn them? Like, could you please help us to suggest some resources, like books or something?
PAUL: books or no, I will add some additional materials in Notion. Later on, everybody, I'll be adding a few basic NLP topics, okay? From there, you can actually relate those things, okay? So, at the end, after the class, I'll be adding that.
Manasa Madabhushi: Okay, sir, thank you.
PAUL: Yeah. Michael last, and then I will start the task again.
Michael Sampath: Two questions. One is, if I understand it right, E and V. E is the question that is embedded, and V is a data source that is embedded in the vector database. Is that the right understanding?
PAUL: Yes, yes.
Michael Sampath: Okay, perfect. Second question is regarding deep learning and RAG. So, can I substitute or do anything deep learning can do using RAG?
Michael Sampath: Or is it…
PAUL: learning can do extract, so LLM, if I'm talking about it, so LLM is a deep learning model, no?
Michael Sampath: Yeah, yeah.
PAUL: You always keep dealing with racks.
Michael Sampath: Certain things can be done only with deep learning, and most of the things can be done with RAG.
Michael Sampath: My question is… Can we…
PAUL: No, no, no, so your question is, somehow, I feel, you are telling certain things can be done with deep learning?
Michael Sampath: Only.
PAUL: So, let's take the example, building a language model, okay? Now, your second part question is, certain things can be done with RAM, and which cannot be done with deep learning.
Michael Sampath: Correct.
PAUL: No, you are totally wrong. So, whenever you were working with RAT, you were working with an LN. So, underline, it's a deep learning model at that.
Michael Sampath: Okay.
Michael Sampath: So my… so let's say I have a million, X-ray images.
PAUL: If…
Michael Sampath: And I want to see the anomaly in the images. Can I use RAG, or do I have to go through a one step up in deep learning?
PAUL: Then, really, if you want to find the aluminals, okay, now, in that case, you really don't need a rag.
PAUL: Because for… to finding the anomalies, very specific, you need some type of computer vision model there.
PAUL: But it will be a deep learning model at the end of the day.
Michael Sampath: Okay, okay, perfect, yeah. That's, that's all…
PAUL: Otherwise, see, like, if we want to use a RAM, very specifically, then you need to have a data source, where you have an image, and it will say in that image that, okay, in this image, there is no animal. Then, again, in this image. In that way, you have to train an animal.
PAUL: And then you can bring your customer.
PAUL: Got it. That is another way also. I hope you get my point, okay?
Michael Sampath: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Michael Sampath: Thanks, thanks, boy.
PAUL: Okay, alright. So now, guys, let's get back to our class.
PAUL: Alright, let me start sharing my screen.
PAUL: Here at the phones, typing iPad via cable here.
PAUL: All right. Now, for the augmentation, okay, there are 3 things that need to be taken care. Okay, so let me switch something.
PAUL: Yeah. So, the first part that you have is your user query, okay?
PAUL: Then you have your retripped Docs.
PAUL: And with that.
PAUL: some type of prompt, okay, it's 3. Okay, so some type of prompt that comes into the picture. Okay, like, how you want your response, what is the structure of the response that you are looking for. So, all those things that comes. Okay, now this is basically the augmentation phase.
PAUL: Okay, now these three things will be sent to do the generation task, because after this, finally, at step 5, that you have your generation.
PAUL: Okay, now for generation, you use a large language model, and LLM will come into the picture. You can use open source LLMs or paid LLMs, as simple as that. Okay? Now, this is where you're…
PAUL: Tech generation is done.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Now, how the… so, to do the text generation, three things are required. One is the user query, one is the recturing docs, and finally, you have the prompt.
PAUL: Okay? So, now the question comes, LLM get context from where? From those three things. The context is broken into
PAUL: those three.
PAUL: I can say parts for now.
PAUL: Okay? The query, the retrieve docs, and the prompt, QRP, in simple terms, that you can remember, going forward.
PAUL: Alright, now let's try to build a simple, step-by-step workflow so that you guys can remember, because right now, this is,
PAUL: I can say a lot of steps that we have discussed, but let's try to draw a simple flow at how everything will work, okay? So, two things. There are two parallel things that I can break it. One is the ingestion. Ingestion fees is totally separate, okay?
PAUL: So, the data ingestion phase that I feel I… my data ingestion is totally separate phase. For example, if I want to keep it in production. So, you can think about my data ingestion service is going
PAUL: Like, total, as a microservice, as a different microservice.
PAUL: Okay, so generally, how you can do ingestion? By taking some documents, okay, so, like, one docs…
PAUL: Then come crawl.
PAUL: These are the normal ways of performing an ingestion operation, okay? Now, once you have the documents.
PAUL: Okay, you convert them into chunks.
PAUL: Okay, now chunking, a detailed lecture will be there. For now, you can think about, there is a simple document.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, and in that document, you try to break it into multiple chunks.
PAUL: As simple as that.
PAUL: Okay, now you can, decide the chunk size, the chunk overlap here. Two important parameters during practical we'll be talking about, but for now, chunks is simply a part of a document, as simple as that.
PAUL: Okay? Now, these chunks are sent to a embedding model.
PAUL: Okay? Now, from embedding model, this is sent to vector team.
PAUL: Okay? Now, this is a data ingestion phase, which I always… if I'm doing it in production, I keep it as a separate microservice, because this is really not related. Okay.
PAUL: To my main retrieval pipeline that I have, okay? Now comes your retrieval pipeline that I'll be talking about. What is crawl? Somebody's asking. Crawl means crapping in simple terms. I hope everybody understood the meaning of crawl.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, what is QRP? Q is query, okay? R is the retrieve text, and P is basically the prompt, okay? Whoever is asking about this one.
PAUL: to QRP in shortcut, I write, okay, sometimes, but because these things I've already mentioned in the augmentation piece.
PAUL: Alright. Now, data ingestion phase is done. This is phase one, at any point of time.
PAUL: Now comes our stage 2, which is basically the retrieval part.
PAUL: So, let's talk about Phase 2.
PAUL: Okay, sorry.
PAUL: Okay? To do the retrieval process, first you need a query. User query, you can think about. So I will just write query for now.
PAUL: It means the question that we'll be asking.
PAUL: Okay? Now, once you have this, now this will go to the embedding model.
PAUL: Okay? The embedding model will generate the embeddings, okay. Now, it will try to fetch where? In vector D.
PAUL: Okay, so… really, if I… okay, now, in VectorDB, what we store? Dense vector.
PAUL: Okay? Or it can be sparse vectors also.
PAUL: I'll be talking about these things later on, but for now, just in high level, I'm talking about. Okay? The idea is to, once the embedding is generated, it will try to fetch in the vector div, and from there, it will try to get you the
PAUL: Retrieved documents.
PAUL: Okay, one, the retrib documents are done, then some other concepts comes, like, you can actually perform a re-ranking operation, just to see which one is better. Okay, now what is re-ranking? For re-ranking, you have models.
PAUL: Okay, so this part, later on, I'll be talking about in-depth regarding re-ranking, but it means that, okay, you have fetched 50 documents. Out of that 50, I will say that, okay, I will just only take the top
PAUL: 20 only. Rest, 30 I will discard. Okay, that is totally possible.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why I feel that,
PAUL: you can use re-ranking, okay, and otherwise, I will just break it from here.
PAUL: So, I… can I say this? Retrieve docs as context, please? Let me know.
PAUL: Can I say this as context?
PAUL: That I got from VectorDB.
PAUL: And the query that was asked here.
PAUL: Very specifically, this one.
PAUL: Okay, now, this query that you have.
PAUL: Okay? And what will be added here?
PAUL: One important thing, that prompt, if you remember, three things that I have told. Okay, these three things are passed to the LL.
PAUL: Okay? And finally, LLM will provide you the response that you are looking for.
PAUL: Okay, so…
PAUL: step by step, is this part clear for everyone? What would be this query example? So, for example,
PAUL: In a vector DB, you have a lot of, documents related to RAG, okay? Now, your query can be, explain me RAG, what is RAG? Okay, so tell me, like, what is the RAG architecture? That can be your query.
PAUL: I hope you get it.
PAUL: What is prompt? Prompt is basically a setup instruction that you sync.
PAUL: Guys?
PAUL: How many of you don't know about prompts? What is prompt?
PAUL: Beauty.
PAUL: Prompt is a setup instruction.
PAUL: Okay, so for example, in the prompt, I can say that, provide me the response in Markdown format. Okay, this is just an example random that I have taken. Okay, so in the prompt, you can say that, or if you want a certain structure in your output, so for example, I want a structure something like this, introduction.
PAUL: Okay, then application… Okay, then comes, use cases.
PAUL: Okay, real-world study.
PAUL: Okay, and then finally, conclusion.
PAUL: Now, this is a set of instructions that I am telling, okay, my output or my response have to follow this particular, instructions.
PAUL: Okay, so the generation of the output is dependent on the setup instructions that is provided on the prompt.
PAUL: Is this part clear?
PAUL: Who creates this additional prompt? We create, we create prompt.
PAUL: Not created by RAG or any model, we have to give the…
PAUL: Okay? Now, what is ranking? Ranking is basically when you try to fetch the documents, on top of the fetch documents, you try to use a re-ranking model, just to find out which retrieved documents are much more better.
PAUL: Okay, so for re-ranking, I will take separate class. Don't worry, each of these components have separate classes.
PAUL: So, really, don't worry. This is just the idea, is you understand the high-level architecture of that. So, don't think about it.
PAUL: Somebody is telling initial query is the prompt, no. Initial query is not the prompt. Initial query is just the question that you will be asking to the rank system.
PAUL: Yes, I'll be teaching you what is dense vector, what is sparse vector, I will be showing you past estimation, don't worry, Sumash. All those things will come. This is first class, guys, but really, don't try to go in-depth, because even I'm not going in-depth. This is pretty much high-level stuff.
PAUL: Okay? Alright.
PAUL: Now, this is the actual flow, and based on that, you get the output. So, the flow is clear for everyone. So, there are two phases, the data ingestion phase, and the other one is the retrieval phase. Okay, so this one I will say as phase one.
PAUL: That, later on, you can use it.
PAUL: Okay, and this is for us.
PAUL: Chunk 1, 2, 3, 4.
PAUL: Who generates the context? Nobody generates the context. The context is returned from the vector team.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Okay? Now, everybody is comfortable with the flow.
PAUL: Okay, or do you need an example of this flow? Okay, so, for example, in the data ingestion, just think about, I have taken 10 different PDFs about RAM, okay? So, what I have done…
PAUL: Simply those, documents that I have, those 10 PDFs, I will convert those… each document into chunks, and all those, chunks, I'll be converting them into embeddings, and I'll be saving them in a vector table.
PAUL: Okay, so my VectorTV has a good amount of information about RAC.
PAUL: Now, in Phase 2 for the retrieval, I asked a question, okay, so, like, what is RAC, in simple terms? Now, this particular query, what is RAC, will be, converted
PAUL: embedding. And the idea is to use the… see, generally, the idea is to use the same embedding model always, guys. Okay, so if you are using a Gemini model here, here also I will try to use a Gemini model. If you change the embedding model, we have seen that we get bad responses, because the…
PAUL: mathematical, I can say, calculations for each embedding model is different. It's not fixed. Okay, so if the algorithm changes, there is
PAUL: Issue with the output. Okay, so the idea is always use, the embedding model same during Phase 1 and during Phase 2.
PAUL: Now, when you ask this question, what is… now that what is rack will be converted, okay, now, that embedding will be compared with all the embeddings which are available in VectorTV. Now, using, similarity, cosine similarity, we'll be getting the retrieved tops.
PAUL: Now, once we have those retrieved dogs, out of 100 docs, okay, we can look for only 30 docs. For that, we can do re-ranking. Again, re-ranking is totally optional, it's not like… it's a compulsion step, so that's why I kept it as a start.
PAUL: Once you have those retrieve docs, so retrieve Docs is basically the context
PAUL: Now, that context with the user query plus from these three things are combined and sent to the LLM, and finally you get your response.
PAUL: Okay? This is a simple architecture, guys, understand. Because there will be more complex architecture, but this is the most simple architecture.
PAUL: I hope you… okay, and in the response, what you will be getting? The final output from the element. So, probably, you might have used 10 retrie documents.
PAUL: For all those 10 written documents that you have as context, it will be fed to the LLM, and then LLM will completely recreate or generate your final results.
PAUL: Okay, I think exactly this part should be clear for everyone. What is Phase 11? There is no Phase 11, there is only Phase 1 and Phase 2.
PAUL: VectorDB will have dense vector, then why you have mentioned sparse vector. VectorDB can have dense vector as well as sparse vector.
PAUL: Okay, don't think about vector TV can keep only tense vector. VectorDV can keep both the vectors, tense as well as parts.
PAUL: Context is also a vector. Yes, you can think about, because at the end of the day, context is basically some type of embedding.
PAUL: Okay, so yes, embedding is a vector.
PAUL: At the end of the day.
PAUL: Alright guys, so the high-level part is done, please let me know in the chat.
PAUL: Okay, then I will proceed ahead with the research paper. So, let's start with the research paper.
PAUL: Query is extracted. Query is totally… how it is extracted from the… this is query, which is asked by an user.
PAUL: And prompt is totally different. Prompt, I'm telling you, it's a set of instructions.
PAUL: Now, you can ask me, okay, this is provided by the user, yes, I can say.
PAUL: Okay, but, like, this can be a system prompt, it means that I've kept the prompt fixed. Okay, this can be changing, but this cannot be. It is only a static setup instruction that I'm passing.
PAUL: So, both the things are different.
PAUL: Now, can we say the prompt driving the output is an example of augmentation? We can say the prompt is driving the output in a set of structure that has been defined.
PAUL: Okay, in the prompt.
PAUL: So, if you allow a setup instruction, that setup instructions need to be followed by that.
PAUL: Prompt is JSON format. There are multiple formats of prompt. We are not talking about prompt in detail. For now, prompt is just a setup instruction, and don't think anything more than that.
PAUL: Okay, Rahul Parir, your question, not relevant now, it will be after one month. I'm not talking about decomposition, okay, query translation, totally, not up to…
PAUL: Okay, Akash, any use case, please?
PAUL: So, with respect to use case, I've already given you an example.
PAUL: In Phase 1, just think about, you have any type of domain-specific questions. For example, with respect to healthcare, those documents are saved in VectorTV. In the interview phase, you can ask any questions.
PAUL: with respect to the healthcare part, like, what is the medicine for this particular disease, okay, or what is that? In that way, it totally depends upon your retrieved context, okay, that you have fed during data ingestion. If it will have the context, it will give you the results.
PAUL: If you ask something out of this, simply, hallucination is one of the problems that it can.
PAUL: Okay, Satya, that we'll be talking about in VectorDB classes, when to choose pass vector or, dense vector, okay?
PAUL: Not related now. Guys, we'll have a… when you ask a very specific question, just be sure. This is the first introduction class, so I don't want to go in-depth. Okay, it's high. So, let's stop now, here, and let's start our paper.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: Most of the questions people are asking just advanced, right?
PAUL: Okay, so don't worry, we will go into advance, we have a lot of time.
PAUL: So, this is subscribed 3, okay, and I think I have…
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: Palabre is asking, can you show one hands-on example?
PAUL: I don't want to jump practical, because, right now.
PAUL: I showed one practical, most of you are not familiar with code, so I don't feel that I should show you practical today. I'll be showing you all the practicals, on Saturday.
PAUL: Okay? Because, little bit of Lang Chen and other stuff, okay, so when I show you the code, you might not be familiar with today, so I don't want to discuss. So let's try to understand rank.
PAUL: Okay? So, everybody please open the research paper. We will be going through the abstract part first of all.
PAUL: Okay, everybody please open the paper.
PAUL: Don't ask me for the link, always look into Notion.
PAUL: See, guys, what is the purpose of sharing Notion, if you guys don't use Notion?
PAUL: 9th November Introduction to RAC, and simply you'll be getting. This is the first paper that I'll be discussing today.
PAUL: If you can't navigate nothing, I can do, Bala.
PAUL: Because I think you have to be smart, man.
PAUL: I cannot do entire spoon feeding.
PAUL: Everybody can access it. In Notion, please let me know. The first paper that I'll be discussing, 11401.
PAUL: Okay, I'll be taking questions, don't worry at the end.
PAUL: Alright, so let's start with the paper now.
PAUL: Okay, so as you can see, so this is the 2021 paper from Facebook AI research team.
PAUL: And with, UCLNY.
PAUL: So, let's just try to understand, because the entire paper, I cannot read it, okay? The idea is basically to go through the, part very specifically. So, here, if you look into the Retriever DPR part, a lot of things that will come into the picture. In high level, I'll be letting
PAUL: So, here, large, pre-trained language models have been shown to store factual knowledge in their parameters and achieve state-of-the-art reserves when fine-tuned on downstream NLP tasks.
PAUL: Okay? This is the first line.
PAUL: I hope everybody can understand this particular line, and there should not be any problem.
PAUL: Because, fine-tune, I have told. Downstream, I have told.
PAUL: Okay, parameters. What are parameters?
PAUL: Yes, what are parameters?
PAUL: WNB, correct, Agreeing Gupta. Okay? Always remember that.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: So, first of all, so, when you have this.
PAUL: So, the first line is pretty much clear, and I don't think there should be any problem. However, their ability to access and precisely manipulate knowledge is still limited.
PAUL: Hence, knowledge-inclusive tasks, their performance lags behind task-specific architectures. Okay, now, this part is important. Okay, now, what type of task you want the large language model to do?
PAUL: Okay, because previously, there were separate models. Okay, so for example, using a single model, I cannot do everything.
PAUL: Like, for text summarization, I have a separate command.
PAUL: For NER, I have a separate model. For PoshTag, I have a separate model. For Q&A, I have a separate model.
PAUL: Okay, so generally for text summarization, what is the model architecture which people use as an NLP? Anyone can let me know.
PAUL: For text summarization, what is the most famous Architecture which is used.
PAUL: Don't say but, I am talking about the architecture.
PAUL: Encoder, somebody, transformer, no, no, no.
PAUL: Guys… See, everybody see… The most common one is sequence-to-sequence models.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Sequence-to-sequence models, so simply like an encoder-decoder-based architecture that we do follow.
PAUL: People are telling what to make, totally out of the context. See, guys, please cover the fundamentals of NLP, really. Like, if I'm an interviewer, if I ask these questions you cannot answer, I will never hire.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, simple things, these are. Okay? So, previously, what people have been doing, very specific to research, okay, for specific type of downstream task, okay, they have built very specific
PAUL: I can say architectures, and based on that, only you will be getting your own. So, it's telling that their ability to access and precisely manipulate knowledge is still limited.
PAUL: Okay, and hence, on knowledge internship tasks, their performance lags behind task-specific architectures.
PAUL: Okay, so somehow I can say that task-specific architectures are better, but again, if you change the task, then it cannot do any other task. It has to be that very specific task only, like summarization, or like eventing. Okay, if you try to build something generic.
PAUL: Okay, it will really not work. And at the end of the day, knowledge intensive. Knowledge intensive, it means that when I'm feeding a lot of data, it will have the knowledge, but that knowledge will always be limited.
PAUL: Because it totally depends upon the data that I am feeding.
PAUL: If I ask it something new again, it cannot respond.
PAUL: Additionally, providing provenance for their decisions and updating their world knowledge remain open search problems. Can you see this? This is the most, like, important line with respect to RAG, if you think about it.
PAUL: Okay, back in, 2021, this was an open research problem.
PAUL: Actually. Okay, now how to increase the data?
PAUL: Because training LLMs every day with new data, that is not a solution. Because training is a very expensive task, and it cannot be done by everyone.
PAUL: Pre-trained models with differentiable access mechanism to explicit non-parametric memory
PAUL: have, far been only investigated for extractive downstream tasks. How many of you know extractive and abstractive? What is the difference between extractive and abstractive? Again, NLP concept.
PAUL: Please let me know in the chat.
PAUL: Transformer is also a correct answer.
PAUL: Ea summit, in that case, S2S is based on encoder-decoder, and transformers uses encoderT. Okay. Please let me know what is the meaning of extracted.
PAUL: Not sure, not sure. Just guess, guys, because I know there are smart people here, at least. Abstract is creativity, yes or shit correct.
PAUL: Okay, now see, whenever there is a term called as abstractive, it means that it will try to fetch the exact data. And when it's an abstractive task, it means that it will fetch that data, but it will try to do a rephrasing operation.
PAUL: Okay? It means that it will try to recreate something. That is the difference between extractive and abstracted.
PAUL: Okay, create a new summary, yes, super deploy, correct.
PAUL: Okay? Assumption, predictions, like, no, no, no, no, it's totally, okay. So, in simple terms, extractive means the exact information on which the data was, trained, okay, or the model was trained on.
PAUL: Abstractive means, okay, it will get the original information, but that information will be rephrased, okay, with some type of creativity that you can think about.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Extract is retrieval, abstract is manipulative.
PAUL: Alright, but abstractive… in abstractive also, the context is always written.
PAUL: Okay, so directly, cannot say it's manipulative, but you have to understand, the context is the same at the end of the day. So that's why I don't know how many of you know, there are two types of text summarization. One is extractive text summarization, the other one is abstract text summarization.
PAUL: Alright, okay, few people have heard about that, alright.
PAUL: ESE domain-specific LLMs are there, efficiently.
PAUL: All right, now, let's very specifically, jump into this part, okay? So, query trained models with a differentiable access mechanism to explicit non-parametric memory.
PAUL: Now,
PAUL: In simple terms, how many of you can understand, like, what is non-parametric memory and what is parametric memory?
PAUL: Because that's why reading papers…
PAUL: I know it will be hard in day one, but by the third month of this course, you guys will be really good. So, don't worry.
PAUL: Parametric is model's internal paper. Okay, alright. So, let's get back and let's try to understand these concepts.
PAUL: That's why I… Feel the problem.
PAUL: Just a bit, I will just take the notepad, okay?
PAUL: explain you these concepts. These concepts should be clear in your mind.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, first of all, this, extractive concept at CAMS.
PAUL: from… Crypto.
PAUL: Okay, so these two, I've made it clear.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, one simple… I think everybody knows the meaning of rephrasing. Like, my name is Paul, and Paul is my name. That is the rephrased version. Okay, so I know the context is there. I am not losing any type of context. Okay, so that's why.
PAUL: this. Okay, now coming to… parametric memory.
PAUL: And non-parametric memory.
PAUL: So, first of all, with respect to, a parametric memory, what I'm talking about, okay, so you can think about a pre-trained sequence-to-sequence model, okay?
PAUL: Any example of a sequence-to-sequence model that you can give me, guys?
PAUL: Anyone that you have used, Like, DeFi, BART, anything like that.
PAUL: RNN is not.
PAUL: No.
PAUL: Okay, so just think about a, pre-trained?
PAUL: SEC to sec.
PAUL: model, okay? A pre-trained sequence-to-sequence model. So, this paper comes from, Facebook, okay? And Facebook has its own model, which is called as BART.
PAUL: The name of the model is basically BART. So Bart comes from the Facebook AI research team. So that's why in this paper, you'll be seeing this. So, I don't want to take the example of T5 or others, okay, because those are Google models. So, right now, I will stick to the Facebook models only.
PAUL: Okay, that stores…
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Now the model is storing some type of information in simple terms, okay?
PAUL: In, sorry, rather than not its depth, just wait.
PAUL: in… weights.
PAUL: Okay, rather than this one.
PAUL: It means that there is a model. In that model, your exact… the data that you have trained on, that data information is saved within the model. That is called as parametric mint.
PAUL: Is this part clear for everyone?
PAUL: So, if I'm talking about this bot model, I think the bot model is a big one, like, close to, I think, 400 million parameters.
PAUL: Okay, now inside is 4 million parameters, 400 million parameters. You have that training data knowledge that has been saved.
PAUL: It's like convolution neural parameters.
PAUL: Parameters are common, whether it's CNN, whether it's RNN, whether it's LSTN, whether it's transformers, the concept of parameters never changes.
PAUL: So, this is basically used while training. Yes, exactly correct. When you have trained the sequence-to-sequence model, okay, and very specifically here, the part architecture that I have taken, okay, it was trained on some type of data. Now, that data
PAUL: Okay, is, which is stored inside the model, that is referred to as the parametric memory.
PAUL: Is this part here? What is parametric memory? The actual information on which the model was trained on, and that information is saved within the model. Okay, that is referred to as parametric memory. Please let me know.
PAUL: Because going forward, if you are confused on these type of things, it becomes very hard.
PAUL: Rahul Pariar is asking, what kind of category of parameters
PAUL: Parameters are weights and biases. There is no category of parameters.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Is this part clear? Now, what is parametric telling me? Then I will move to non-parametric.
PAUL: If sheet. Simple. You have some training data, Training data.
PAUL: Okay, now that… using that data, you trained a sequence-to-sequence model. In this example, I am taking part.
PAUL: After the model that is trained, the final model that you have.
PAUL: This model, let's take the example, it has 400 million parameters.
PAUL: Parameters are weights and biases. Now, when you have this model, now, using this model, what you can do, so let's take the final model.
PAUL: Okay, and you want to do any type of NLP task.
PAUL: Can I say that inside this final model, you have this training data information? Yes or no?
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Now, this information that you have, that is referred to as parametric memory.
PAUL: Because the information is saved in the form of weights and biases.
PAUL: Okay? Is this part clear for parametric memory? What is this? Can I move to the next part of par…
PAUL: Okay? Alright, now let's come to non-parametric memory.
PAUL: Because these are NLP concepts, and really.
PAUL: If I… I thought many of you will know this.
PAUL: Alright, non-parametric memory.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Non-parametric memory, it means that the model that has not been trained on. Okay, a simple example, like vector TB that you have. Okay, so I can say, dense…
PAUL: vector… Okay, any type of information that you have. Okay, a dense vector of…
PAUL: It can be any type of data sources, okay? Like, any type of external data sources.
PAUL: Okay? A dense vector. It means that, very specifically, this is an external memory that you have.
PAUL: Okay, so for example, you know, there are different types of data sets, so if I take the example of Wikipedia.
PAUL: Wikipedia dataset is there.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, similarly, anything that the model has not been trained on.
PAUL: As simple as that. Okay, that's why we're referring them as external, because the model has not been trained on this data.
PAUL: If something the model has never seen, it is referred to as non-parametric. If the model has seen during the training, it is referred to as parametric.
PAUL: It's this part here?
PAUL: Okay, and this parametric memory, how it can be accessed.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is that, okay, you have this dense vector.
PAUL: Probably, I can say, index for now.
PAUL: Okay, so later on, you will be seeing few words like collection, indexes, okay, with respect to vector TV, but for now, this is a dense vector. Okay, and now how this dense vector can be accessed at any point of time? It's through a neural retriever.
PAUL: Okay, or in simple terms, DPR.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, to access a non-parametric memory, you need a DPR, in simple terms. It means the information which has never been seen by the model.
PAUL: But the parametric memory can directly accessed. You don't need a retriever for that.
PAUL: Is this part clear?
PAUL: Parametric, non-parametric, All right.
PAUL: Alright, fine, guys.
PAUL: So, I will stop sharing. The… okay, let's get back to the abstract, at least. Let's try to cover the abstract part today.
PAUL: Desktop 3… okay, hold on.
PAUL: Cheer.
PAUL: So, here, so pre-trained models with a differentiable access mechanism to explicit non-parametric memory have been so far only investigated for extractive downstream tasks. Okay, so extracted downstream tasks, you can think about a task like text summarization for now.
PAUL: We explore a general-purpose fine-tuning recipe for RAG, very specifically, RAG, I'm directly calling it. Okay, and directly they have called it models.
PAUL: which combine pre-trained parametric and non-parametric memory. So, right now, I hope you understand, combining a pre-trained parameter. Pre-trained parameter, it means some data on which the LLM is already trained. Okay, it means that LLM already have that particular information.
PAUL: And non-parametric data, it is basically your external data that you have.
PAUL: Okay, and now these two will be combined to give your final answer, which is basically the language generation task, which is done by the LM. So, it's basically a combination of two types of members. The parametric, which is… which comes from the LLM,
PAUL: And then comes your non-parametric, which comes from your external, knowledge bases, or any type of documents, okay? And it can be accessed only through a DPR, okay? Through a retriever, in simple terms, if I talk about it.
PAUL: And based on that, you'll be getting your final generated answer.
PAUL: So, here they are talking about, we introduced RAG models, where the parametric memory is a pre-trained sequence-to-sequence model, and the non-parametric memory is a dense vector intense. Okay, here they have taken the Wikipedia dataset. So, what they have taken, their external data source is basically the Wikipedia
PAUL: Dataset. So, they have converted the entire Wikipedia dataset into embeddings, and they might have saved it into some vector database one. That was the idea.
PAUL: Okay, so, Wikipedia, accessed with a pre-trained, you can see, neural retriever. So, here, very specifically, now, how to access this, access the non-parametric, data through a neural, retriever.
PAUL: We compare two RAG formula, okay, two RAG formulations. One, which conditions on the same retripped passages across the whole generated sequence. Okay, it means that there's, see, same retripped passages.
PAUL: Okay, so what is the meaning of same retripped passages?
PAUL: It means that in your vector TV, there is some amount of information. Okay, you can think about pretty much the same information that is being repeated. Okay, because the same information might have similar type of cosine similarity schools.
PAUL: And another which use different passages per tool.
PAUL: Okay, now, this task I will explain, okay, because,
PAUL: this is two things. One is, this is a rack sequence, and this is a token sequence. Okay, two different variants that were picked. So, let's try to explain these two things. So, two formulas are there, okay? So, let's try to break down into simple things.
PAUL: Let me just get back to my iPad.
PAUL: These concepts are important, okay, but…
PAUL: Yes, really, nobody teaches these things, okay? So, right now, they have two rag recipes in simple terms, okay? Two rag recipes that they have.
PAUL: Okay, the first recipe that they talk about, which was the, rag sequence.
PAUL: Where the same sequence or passages was used.
PAUL: And the other one is basically the RAG token-based approach.
PAUL: So, in drag sequence, what happens? In, simply I can say that it uses the same retreat documents for the entire output sequence, okay?
PAUL: uses the… theme?
PAUL: Retrieved.
PAUL: Okay, passage I can write, or document I can write, so you can understand passages just like a document, in simple terms.
PAUL: Okay, so don't get confused in that.
PAUL: documents.
PAUL: To generate the entire output sequence.
PAUL: I did.
PAUL: And this is the most used one, guys. Okay, rag sequence. This is actually that we do use now also.
PAUL: RAP token,
PAUL: So, this also, like, we use a combination of both of these formulas, which is the best one. Now, the concept of token, you have to understand. Token means, rather than using the same retrip passage, we'll be taking different passages. The idea is that different documents comes into the picture.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: So… V?
PAUL: Can… views… Different?
PAUL: Documents.
PAUL: To generate the final output sequence.
PAUL: Okay? So, in simple terms, in rack sequence, what happens? It uses the same passage, or the same document. Passage is a document.
PAUL: Okay? The same document which is being used. But in Wrap token, what happens? EV uses different type of documents.
PAUL: Okay, so that is the… because when they were building the formula, okay, for the rag in their recipes, these two things were tested out.
PAUL: And finally, like, we know that, in… right now in 2025, we use both of these formulas of the recipes combined together.
PAUL: Why we use a rack token? Because I cannot say that if I ask a question, I really cannot say that it will be only in that document. It can be some other document also.
PAUL: with better context, or lesser context, it can happen. We really don't know. When we ask a query, it can be in a document, or it can be more than 10 documents.
PAUL: So, we really don't know how my final output sequence will look like.
PAUL: So for that, we need to take both of these approaches.
PAUL: Okay, so both of these, recipes, that needs to be combined.
PAUL: Okay? All right.
PAUL: So right now, let's get back to the paper.
PAUL: I'm not going to teach you how to implement these recipes. Okay.
PAUL: It will take more than 1 year or 2 years to complete this course.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Now, you can do this type of, experiments, but really, like, with Wikipedia dataset, a lot of resources that is required. I can't teach them.
PAUL: Okay, rather than, you can directly use the information from the paper.
PAUL: Okay, so here, very specifically, okay, so those two formulations. One, which conditions on the same retrieve passages across the generated sequence, and the other, which can use different passages per ticket.
PAUL: We fine-tune and evaluate our models on a wide range of knowledge-intensive NLP tasks.
PAUL: and set the state of the art on three open domain keyword tasks outperforming parametric sequence-to-sequence models.
PAUL: and task-specific retrieve and extract architecture, okay? Now, based on this paper, they are used on 3 different types of tasks. Open domain Q&A,
PAUL: Okay, so this is the major thing. So, for example, whenever we are working, we are asking any question in ChatGPT. Okay, that is open domain Q&A all.
PAUL: Then comes, the second task is parametric sequence-to-sequence model, because for sure, it will outperform parametric, because at the end of the day, in this paper, they have introduced a non-parametric memory.
PAUL: So I know they have introduced some external knowledge. So, for sure, it will be better, because at the end of the day, this paper uses both the memory, parametric as well as non-parametric.
PAUL: Okay, and task-specific retrieve and extract architectures, okay. Now, task-specific retrieve and extract architectures are also limited to parametric memory only. So, because of that, for sure, this paper will perform better as compared to others.
PAUL: Now, for language generation tasks, we find that RAG models generate more specific, diverse, and factual language than a state-of-the-art parametric-only sequence-to-sequence baseline model in simple terms.
PAUL: Okay, so for sure, because any type of sequence-to-SQL model will be restricted to parametric memory only. The idea is to bring non-parametric memory through this paper, so that's why this paper gets very good results.
PAUL: Now, tell me how many of you understood the abstract.
PAUL: Because really, I've tried to break down the abstract as much, I think.
PAUL: To understand, to a certain level.
PAUL: Okay, because his papers are…
PAUL: little bit complicated, okay? That's why most of the times I will discuss the abstract.
PAUL: Because now, if I really try to go in-depth, what are the things, okay, it will become, like, even hard for me to explain.
PAUL: And, like, it might take a lot of time.
PAUL: Okay, now, the idea is that you go. So, for example, guys, see, when you don't understand a paper, take this paper. Take a screenshot, okay, or ask ChatGPT, okay, what is exactly mentioned?
PAUL: Why research papers are important? First of all, better decision-taking.
PAUL: Whenever you are building something, we always use research papers.
PAUL: If you want to crack an interview, you can… Do a very good debate.
PAUL: In Indian market, really, there are very less people who actually read papers. So when you say something, okay, this is my point, and this is referred to this paper, okay, then it becomes heavy. Okay, somebody will say that, okay, you can actually refer to that directly.
PAUL: So that's why papers are important if you are looking for a good package at any point of time, if you want to crack good. I feel that this should be there.
PAUL: Okay? So that's why, at least the abstract part will help you, okay? Like, how RAC came into the picture. RAC never came like this, okay? I will add a PDF, I will add an embedder, I will add this one, okay? The idea was to bring non-parametric memory.
PAUL: Okay, with the combination of parametric memory, which was pre-existing.
PAUL: Okay, that was the only new thing that happened.
PAUL: Okay, so here they have given an example of a sequence-to-sequence model in this particular image. Okay, there is a retriever, there is a generator, okay, and they have taken an example of a Q&A task, a question-answering task, in simple terms.
PAUL: Okay, now, let's go into the methods.
PAUL: Okay, so this is a RAC sequence model, so for that, very specifically, the mathematical formula that they have given. And right now, you can see this will be returning what? Some type of top K documents at the end of the day. And this is… will be also returning top K documents.
PAUL: So, that's why you can see always here a top K that will come into the picture.
PAUL: And really, you don't need to learn the formula, nobody asks this formula. It's just for your own understanding.
PAUL: Then comes your retriever DPR. Okay, so this DPR, the retrieval component is based on DPR, you can see 26, which is another research paper, basically.
PAUL: And which is a bi-encoder architecture. I already told you two encoders are there, that's why it's referred to as bi-encoder.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And here it is basically a dense representation. It means that I'm embedding in simple terms, okay, of a document produced by a broad-based encoder, okay?
PAUL: And, this particular implementation I showed you in this particular notebook.
PAUL: Okay, so this was the core ID of using two different encoders.
PAUL: With respect to the practicality. Okay, then you have the generator, because for the generation, a sequence-to-sequence model, which is being used right here, which is the BART model. Okay, now this BART model comes from the Facebook family.
PAUL: Just as having close to 400 million parameters.
PAUL: Okay, so to combine the import X with the retrieved content Z when generating from BART, can you see?
PAUL: you are actually combining both the memory. One memory that you already have, okay? And then, so X is your parametric memorial sample time. Z is the retrieve content, the information that you are fetching from the non-parametric memorial sample time.
PAUL: Okay, and finally, the generation will take place. Okay, we simply concatenate them. Can you see here? It's simply telling… we concatenate both the results from both those memories, the parametric memory and the non-parametric memory.
PAUL: Alright, so bot was pre-trained using a denoising OK. Now, this is all about the training of bot, which is not required.
PAUL: It has obtained the state-of-the-art results on a diverse set of generation tasks and output
PAUL: performs comparatively sized T5 models. So, T5 models come from the Google family. So, based on their, I can say experiments, simply, they found out that, Bart is performing much better as compared to T5.
PAUL: pre-trained data plus live data. Don't say live data, just say external data. Live data is mean exactly that you are getting in real data. Okay?
PAUL: So that is a wrong intuition.
PAUL: Okay, then you have the training, how they have, built that particular corpus and other things, because right now, we will never deal with the training.
PAUL: Okay, training, like, LLMs or SLMs is not a part of this course, so I can skip that.
PAUL: Then comes, with respect to the decoding part, is basically, decoding means fetching context, okay? And there are two types of context fetching. One, the same document, one, the other document. So that rack token and rack sequence, which has been very specifically mentioned here.
PAUL: Now, these are the different type of experiments that they have done on different type of tasks, and here, can you see FIAS, the vector database that has been used in this particular experiment. FIAS comes from Facebook, so they have very specifically used their own vector database.
PAUL: So, open domain question answering, abstract, tip question answering, okay.
PAUL: Now, different types of data sets they have tested with, like, MS Marco, okay, SearchQ&A, so finally, if you look into some type of results, okay?
PAUL: Now, this part, with respect to results.
PAUL: Can anybody, like, decode exactly, like, what is the… Because, like, B1, QB1,
PAUL: RLB1, anybody knows about these are NLP metrics. If you don't know about this, we can skip this part.
PAUL: Because, like, anybody has heard about, blue score, blue?
PAUL: Because I think few people might have heard
PAUL: Okay. Alright, fine. Fine, fine, fine, fine, no issues.
PAUL: If you have heard about blue score, rogue score, Blue 1, Blue 2, Blue 3, Rogue 1, Rogue 2, Rogue 3, okay, these are language translation metrics. Yes, Prakash, correct.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why. So here, if I'm talking about NQ, okay, so NQ is a dataset. Okay, NQ stands for, like, your natural questions. That is one type of dataset, and again, like, different models, like, T5 is a,
PAUL: I can say sequence-to-sequence model. Okay, and with 11 billion parameters. So, they have tested, so these are all dataset names. NQ, natural questions. TQA is, trivial. Okay, the trivia, QA dataset.
PAUL: Then you have WQ, again, web questions. Then you have CT, curated track, another dataset. See, guys, these are all datasets, so don't get confused here.
PAUL: Okay? And always remember, higher the score, it is always better. So right now, if you look, this is the closed book, open book. Okay, and here, if you look into rack token and rack sequence, so you will see that the results are very close.
PAUL: Okay, it means that there is not a lot of difference. It's 44.1 in this dataset, and this is 44.5. Again, in the other dataset, you can see that, okay, RAT sequence recipe is working better.
PAUL: Now, in the other one, in this dataset, again, you can see RAT token is working better.
PAUL: So, we finally came to know that, okay, we have to use a combination of both of these recipes.
PAUL: Okay, and finally here also, in CT, I can say the rack sequence formula is working better.
PAUL: Okay, and now these are the actual metrics, I can say, the evaluation metrics on top of different data set. Geopardy, different data set. MS Marco, different data set. FPR, okay, and FPR, so 3 and 2, the fewer data sets that we have.
PAUL: Okay? So these are fever data sets, fever two-way classification, fever three-way classification. Okay, and here also, if you look into
PAUL: RAT token, okay, so based on the scores, if you try to compare with original path, only having parametric memory, I can say that, yes, RAT token is working better, close to 17.3.
PAUL: track sequence 14.7.
PAUL: So, on Jeopardy! datasets, the blue scores, so this is B1, so these scores are Blue 1 score.
PAUL: Okay, B1 stands for blue one, which is a metric. If you don't know, okay, I will be attaching one link for different type of metrics in NLP, you can go through that. Then you have QB1, so this is also QBlue1. Okay, then you have,
PAUL: RL, this stands for Rogue. Rugel.
PAUL: Okay, Rogue, rogue S, different type of rogue metrics are there. Then again, you have B1, and with respect to, like, the most common metric, blue and rogue. If you don't know about this, okay, please learn.
PAUL: And then, finally, labeled accuracy.
PAUL: Because at the end of the day, what matters to us is level accuracy, where you can do classification, or some type of data set. And this is where I can say the results
PAUL: are really good with respect to SUTA, 81, 89. I can say the results are really good. Anything above 75 is referred to as a good metric.
PAUL: Okay, so furthermore, RAD can generate correct answers even when the correct answer is not in any retrieved document.
PAUL: Can you think about this statement, correct? Yes or no time?
PAUL: Yes or no? Because this statement I really want you guys to analyze.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Somebody's telling yes, somebody's telling no. Okay, now, let me just tell the answer, see?
PAUL: Simply, they are talking about, furthermore, RAC can generate correct answers even when the correct answer is not in any retrieved document. So, retrieved document means non-parametric memory. It means the correct answer was available in the parametric
PAUL: Okay, that's why this statement is there, and, like, whenever I discuss this, okay, so many people get confused, so we have to understand, if something is missing in the non-parametric memory, and even if it is giving correct answer, it means that it is available in the parametric.
PAUL: All right, now, these are on different questions and others that has been mentioned here.
PAUL: So, with respect to… now, these are some common metrics. Later on, I'll be talking about RAG metrics, and very specifically, like, factualities, okay, and specificity. You can say RAG better in most of the cases. So, with respect to getting factual answers, RAG is really good, according to the research that is being shown here.
PAUL: Okay? Then comes some type of… like, BM25. BM25 is a sparse vector algorithm, it's not a dense vector. Okay, so using BM25, you can actually create sparse vectors.
PAUL: And, here also, if we look into, based on the sequence, okay, so 2458, this is a classification task which is done on the FIVER dataset. So I can say that, yes, RAG is performing good.
PAUL: Okay, so really, the answers, when you look into the experiment, the results of the experiment, this is really good.
PAUL: All right, so, majorly lounge, guys, go spend some time, spend one day, if you have at least spent one hour on this paper, that is a bare minimum requirement, because when you are speaking in the interview, I want you guys to speak from this particular perspective little bit.
PAUL: Because rarely, I have seen students talking about parametric and non-parametric memory, which is the fundamental of RAG.
PAUL: How many of you knew about this thing, that you feel that you have learned something new today?
PAUL: Because, really, that… when you start learning RAT, this is the most fundamental stuff.
PAUL: And really, when I ask questions in interviews, you see, I also take interviews, okay?
PAUL: rarely in India, okay, not even less than 2-3% know about this stuff. Because they know RAC, but they really have not gone. Why RAC came? What was the need? Okay, why non-parametric memory is important? Now you will have an overall idea.
PAUL: Knowing the RAG architecture is different, but actually why that architecture was developed by the Facebook AI research team. You have to focus on these things or not.
PAUL: Okay? So, see, today I'll be talking about, I have another paper that I was planning, okay, and this paper I'll be talking about, because this paper is a little bit advanced paper.
PAUL: This is a Chinese paper. Okay, so first we jump into US, now in next class, little bit towards the Chinese. Okay, so you guys, if you have time, you can go through this paper also, but I'll be discussing this paper,
PAUL: in-depth next time, because in this paper, I'll be talking about different RAG architecture.
PAUL: Okay, like, starting from 2020 GPT, okay, what are the things that happened? So this is much more, like, the entire development of RAG that has happened.
PAUL: Okay, this is a RAG architecture. Then what are the different types of RAG? What is NAVE RAG, Advanced RAG, Modular RAG? Okay, so this will be, like, in next one, because I want to give you an overall idea. Then we'll start with the practicals, because the code is already available, it's not a big thing. Okay, and can you see, these are so many rag papers.
PAUL: Okay, out of this, we'll be discussing few, not all, because, guys, the list is really long. If I start discussing, it will take…
PAUL: Many, many months for me to discuss everything only with respect.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why, out of this few we'll be discussing.
PAUL: And finally, I feel that a few important papers are there, that are not mentioned also, like RAFT, SAG, okay, those things we'll be talking about much more.
PAUL: All right, guys, I hope you have enjoyed the lecture, okay?
PAUL: Because, going into depth is a little bit hard, I know, for many of you. There will be a lot of questions you can ask me. We have time, like, more than 90 minutes, so if we try to ask any question.
PAUL: Okay, before that, I have one task, okay? So let's complete the task first of all. Okay, so I will just raise the pulse also.
PAUL: Okay, just wait.
PAUL: Krishnak Academy, okay, let me launch the post, and in the meantime, the product that we are working on, okay, I'll be providing you the access. You know the product that we are currently working, Xenodox, which was being shown to you, okay?
PAUL: So, let me… everybody, please, I have raised the poll. Okay, it is important for me to know your feedback, because I'll be taking a lot of cases.
PAUL: Okay, and really, like, this research, really, if you are interested in, okay, or you can leave some type of feedback.
PAUL: I know for many of you, a lot of things are new. I'll be adding all the content from fresh YouTube channel, or some paid courses, okay? So, you can let me know that, Paul, okay? Probably I need this content. I don't have clarity on this one. Okay, I will try to incorporate those videos, at least.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is that, for… if, if it is required, probably one Udemy course, if somebody, okay, if you are very much…
PAUL: Because I know 30-40% students have NLP knowledge, okay? Then the rest, 30% have… little bit low.
PAUL: And I feel that 20% is there, somehow, they are zeroed. Exactly. Because I don't want you to be that in that zero field. Okay, the idea is that in the coming one week or two weeks, please spend two to three hours, okay, every day.
PAUL: Okay, at least, because this is important.
PAUL: If you're looking for a good job, if you're looking for a good package, really you have to move the research. Because research is fine, because practical is fine, but really.
PAUL: In the first step, everybody asks you questions, okay? Then, you're practical, what is the project, another story.
PAUL: And these are the core bases. Alright, I hope you guys can see my screen. Let me just start sharing. This is my desktop 3. Okay, so everybody, please try to sign up in Xenodox.
PAUL: Okay, because today you guys need to do the rating and product time.
PAUL: Because this is a task which has been told by Krish to me, so that everybody can just try to sign up. Probably you might be in the waitlist, it's fine, because after this class, I will ask the dev team to give the access from DB.
PAUL: Everybody, please do, give the post, guys, everyone.
PAUL: Okay, everybody.
PAUL: Alright, everybody, I'm sharing the link of Xenodocs.
PAUL: Everybody, please do sign up going forward, even I will be using this in live class, okay, and even you will be getting access. A limited access, but at least you will be getting the beta access of this one. So, it has a lot of things, we'll be talking about this in detail, probably when the beta launch is there, I will ask
PAUL: Ekman or Prish will be coming.
PAUL: Like, for this, I have worked on the… this product is also having a rack, so I have worked on that particular backend rack.
PAUL: And, right now, I'm working on the catching part, very specifically, user profiling catcher.
PAUL: Okay, so everybody, please do sign up, okay? And in the meantime, just do an upbooting in Product Hunt. How many of you know about Product Hunt?
PAUL: You have to create your account, so this is an activity. In the meantime, I can target.
PAUL: Here you can search about VINU.
PAUL: Dope.
PAUL: The idea is to make things… okay, so here…
PAUL: Okay, so, like, few people have just given. Okay, so you can add due… the reviews.
PAUL: Okay, so we'll just try to give the rating, that is the main thing that we are looking for.
PAUL: Everyone, just take your time. In the meantime, I will start taking questions one by one. Okay, because from here, directly, I can see, like, how many. Just try to follow, okay, and review.
PAUL: If Chris doesn't see again, he will come then next week, for sure, right?
PAUL: Alright guys, so let me start taking questions now.
PAUL: I think everybody, if you don't have an account in Product Hunt, you can simply create it, okay, and you have to just do an upload.
PAUL: I… do I have an account? Let me check, okay, yeah, I do have an account.
PAUL: Okay, so something like… You can give a star, I use…
PAUL: this. Okay, I mean, you can just do an upbooting.
PAUL: Alright guys, please do provide, reviews, and by evening, you will be getting access to Xenods, okay?
PAUL: From here, you can get majorly the documentation, and next week, I'll be telling you a lot of details with respect to the product. In the meantime, I feel you guys are smart. Here, it's a simple, like, you can think about. RAG is there behind the scenes in this product, where we try to fetch different type of context related to
PAUL: different type of documentations and others. Then we send that context to LLM, so that you always get
PAUL: Up-to-date code at any point in time.
PAUL: Just logging, okay, it might be there. There can be some issues, I know, but it is running in an ECS target, I think, so…
PAUL: It can auto-scale.
PAUL: All right, fine, let me start taking questions. The idea is you guys should have clear concepts. This we can do next week also, but any
PAUL: But I flee.
PAUL: Bank is sick today, I feel.
PAUL: I just, try to follow.
PAUL: And then pass it. Otherwise, next week would be fine.
PAUL: It says server error. Alright, fine. Just try to later on also, you can create your account. Review once you try to access the product, then next, like, next Saturday also, you can do it.
PAUL: Yeah, but if somebody's interested, they can do it now.
PAUL: Alright, so let me start taking questions. So, let me know in the chat. Okay, move on, because many people have raised their hands, really.
PAUL: Every question is hard for me. I think more than… okay, it's lesser of me. So let's start with Rajat Karna, first of all. Then I will go to Fikri Musa, because I think Fikri was asking a lot of questions in the chat with respect to NLP Basics.
PAUL: So let's start. Rajat, I think you can start?
Rajat Khanna: Am I ordering?
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, Rajat, you are automated.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, so my, basic question is related to the NLP, so it means I have, done a basic, video that to understand the NLP and how it works, and also the practical implementations.
Rajat Khanna: But, some of the points that you have mentioned, mentioned as in, the answers that we get in NLP, like, if we have created a good NLP,
Rajat Khanna: processing for the document or not. It goes from the 0 to 1 rating. Like, it starts from 0.06, might be in an average, and 0.08 will be a good
Rajat Khanna: document that we have created means good NLP processing that we have done. But I am not…
PAUL: When you're talking about these numbers with respect to retrieval of those documents, I refer to the cosine similarity score. Higher it is, better it is.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, okay. And, just for the suggestion part, as you have given a rating window, so before my… in the next lecture, what you will be teaching, so the basic that you need to have understanding of, so we will have a 5 days
Rajat Khanna: In between, so we can read about that, so that we will know…
PAUL: Share the paper, you can go through the paper. Next, and… because next Sunday, I'm planning for the practical, so Saturday I will start, but once I discuss the paper, then I will start with the practical. So, the second paper that I showed today, that will be the next class agent.
PAUL: I hope you're okay.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, okay, that's it. Thank you.
PAUL: Got it.
PAUL: Next, Vikri.
Fikri Musa: Yes, hi. I was looking at the links that you just sent right now. I did have plenty of questions, but I seem to not be able to remember them all right now. But those current links, can you just go over those a little bit, so that way I know what we got those links for, for the last ones?
PAUL: The research paper links, are you referring?
Fikri Musa: Yeah, the last one's correct, the last two? Right.
PAUL: Look, this paper link, yeah.
Fikri Musa: Not the papers link, the one that you just sent to everybody's,
PAUL: This one, Xenodos.
Fikri Musa: Yes, you know.
PAUL: This is a product that, currently we are building.
PAUL: So, the idea was to provide access to everyone, that's…
Fikri Musa: Oh, okay. And what does it help us with?
PAUL: It helps you to, like, getting better context, like, getting up-to-date code from any NLL.
Fikri Musa: Get up-to-date code from where?
PAUL: Yes, from any type of LLMs, just think about if something is launched, okay? There is a cut-off training date. Okay, so that's why. Anybody has used Contact Center?
PAUL: Nobody has seen it. Okay, fine. Like, if somebody has… the idea is, whenever you ask something to the LLM, whether it's chat, Jupyter or anything, with respect to a particular framework, there is no guarantee it will provide you the latest version of the code which has been lost.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: But in our case, we try to provide the state of the art, whichever the version that has been launched. Okay, that particular piece of code.
PAUL: So it becomes easier to code for any developer at any point.
PAUL: I hope you get my point.
Fikri Musa: Right.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Now, any questions? Other questions, please let me know.
Fikri Musa: like, how intensive is the coding gonna be? I do have a little bit of practical experience with Python, but I'm actually a little bit, you know what I mean?
PAUL: When I start coding, then you can ask me, like, how intensive it is.
Fikri Musa: Okay.
PAUL: Yeah, because right now, I will try to use Jupyter Notebooks initially 1 month, or probably 2 months, but after 3 months, when you start working on the project, it will be modular vertical.
PAUL: So, yes, at least in intermediate level. Like, I cannot say basic, if you are not comfortable with object-oriented programming.
PAUL: And just go through. It's not a rocket science. Just spend 1 hour, you will get the underlying concepts.
Fikri Musa: Okay.
PAUL: Okay? No.
PAUL: Alright, fine. Let's move to our next partisan.
PAUL: Hi everyone.
PAUL: Ashok, Salman, then comes Platformation Shop 3.
PAUL: Okay, then comes Kaushiksar. Okay, few people have one ready. Guys, quickly, quick.
Prathmesh Atre: Oh, hi.
Raghavendra V: Heaven.
PAUL: Yeah.
Raghavendra V: So, the fact…
Raghavendra V: So, so the question I was having previously was how we are connecting our Phase 1 to Phase 2.
Raghavendra V: of.
PAUL: No, you are, okay, let's get back to that. Okay, I saw this in the chat. Somebody asked. Just wait. Okay, so I… just wait, let me connect my iPad once.
PAUL: Okay, yes. So, right now, this is a phase one, okay? So, I told you, Phase 1 is a totally separate task. It means that there is no connection with Phase 1 and Phase 2.
PAUL: The job is, in phase one, you'll be just saving the embeddings to vector database, that is the only thing. So that's why I'm telling Phase 1 is a separate microservice.
PAUL: Okay? Now, the vector DB embeddings that you have saved, that will be only used in Phase 2, during the retrieval part.
PAUL: So you can think about, if there is a bridge, that bridges this vector TB to vector T.
PAUL: Okay, it means that the same vector DB is used for the returnable part. Okay, here you just created the vector DB, later on you are using that vector DB for this rate.
PAUL: That is the only connection. Other than that, there is no connection.
PAUL: Totally separate things, okay?
Raghavendra V: Got it. One more question I have, related to, like, can you please share,
Raghavendra V: any NLP, like, things which we should go through in and out, such a way that it would be helpful throughout the course, because, basically, from my side, I'm not that good with NLP, like, I did not go through that till date, so it would be helpful.
PAUL: Like, it depends upon, no, like, how much time you have. If I'm the guy saying, really, like, for everybody I'm just telling, yeah, my favorite book that I have is, I don't know how many of you know, Stanford?
PAUL: It's an open source book, Joravski.
PAUL: Okay, so this is my favorite book, okay, that I have been using a lot.
PAUL: But there are other authors also, so you can see August 24, 2025, this is the… every year they update this. Okay, so this is one of the best ones by Dan Jorovsky. Like, I've been reading this book back from 2000, I think, 16 or 17, the same book. So here you have a major information.
PAUL: Okay, and everything is available. Like, you will get, majorly all the information.
PAUL: Okay, so if you want, you can explore this. This is the best place with respect to research.
PAUL: Okay, but, from… if you don't want to go inside the book, just take the topics and try to do a Google or ChatGPT. That's the at least thing, because this book covers majorly all the topics.
PAUL: That I feel which are important.
PAUL: Okay, I've sent a link to the book, everyone, so please don't… Ask me the name.
PAUL: Thanks, and one more thing, can we… You have done.
Raghavendra V: Yeah, can we chat with papers in general doocs, by any chance?
PAUL: No, not with… no, no, this is much more developer-focused, only good part.
PAUL: For, research papers directly, upload the PDF to ChatGPT and start asking questions. That's the best thing that you can do.
Raghavendra V: Yeah, yeah, yeah, thanks, have a good day.
PAUL: Okay, alright.
Prathmesh Atre: Isa?
PAUL: Yeah, go on.
Prathmesh Atre: actually, I got to learn a lot, and, the few parameters, like parametric memory, non-parametric memory, so I just have some few requests, like, just, this kind of terms, one to two terms, if you kept on, telling us in every lecture, every, you know, then it would be really great that, it will enhance our knowledge.
PAUL: Related to, you know… These terms are much more used by research teams, like, say.
Prathmesh Atre: Vape.
PAUL: Okay, when the author changes, the terms will change, that's all. The meaning will be same at the end of that.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why, like, different authors uses different names or different terminologies, but sometimes it might relate to the same thing. It always happens in the research community.
Prathmesh Atre: But, like, you know, when…
Prathmesh Atre: this is the kind of JNI particular course, so even if we keep on going for some NLP tasks, you know, like 5 to 10 minutes in every lecture, then at the end, it will be…
PAUL: I'll be talking about it in the next one month. So, you guys will be comfortable. I know, this is daily.
PAUL: After 2 months, if you really give 30 minutes, at least, every day. Like, my idea is at least in a week to discuss one thing.
PAUL: Okay, so if you become a habit, I know that after 2 months, you will be in a really good
PAUL: place. Initially, it's hard, I know. For me, also, it was hard when I started. I thought, who read papers? Okay, but later on, at a certain point, you will feel that, okay, that AI really helps me, whether I'm working, whether I'm doing research, okay, whether I'm leading a team, somehow it helps that.
Prathmesh Atre: like, I was into some previous batches also, but due to the heavy workload, I was not able to, you know, join, and actually even tried to complete them as a recorded session. So, this time, this time is actually comfortable for me, 9 to 12.
Prathmesh Atre: Hoping to join every live lecture.
PAUL: Alright, time is something like that's from your end, that you have to get. Because from my end, what I can do, because sometimes I feel like, probably after 3 or 4 months, I might feel that I'm lagging behind the course, because really, this is the first time I'm dealing with much more into research that I have planned for this particular batch. No other batch we have taught in this.
PAUL: I'll plan for this very specifically, so I know that probably after 3 months, I might need to take some extra classes also. I don't know, because a lot of things I've committed, but I will try to deliver. I know it is possible, because I know that stuff, only to express those things to you so that you can get it and implement.
Prathmesh Atre: God.
PAUL: You will be beneficial that's why.
Prathmesh Atre: But you take…
PAUL: Take the PDF, don't worry.
Prathmesh Atre: You…
PAUL: 3 months or 4 months, don't they.
Prathmesh Atre: You keep on…
PAUL: Yeah, at least.
Prathmesh Atre: Right, right. Getting some extra classes also, because in turn, it will help us only to get some extra knowledge, if we are getting.
PAUL: I'm sharing the PDF, just wait, and just wait, I'm sharing the PDF.
PAUL: MediaP will get it there also, so just let me update in the, drive.
PAUL: Okay, not this way, let me use the question.
PAUL: Yeah, next, anybody want to go, they can go ahead. Okay.
PAUL: Anyone?
Salman: So, Paul, with RAG, will it be right to say that it supersedes the fine-tuning? And now fine-tuning is not
Salman: so relevant.
Salman: Is that the right understanding?
PAUL: It supersets the fine-tuning, but in 2024, a paper came where they have combined fine-tuning with, like, the paper is wrapped. Okay, so that's why.
PAUL: And so fine-tuning is…
Salman: irrelevant.
PAUL: Fine-tuning is relevant, but again,
PAUL: that computationally expensive. It means that you need a lot of infrastructure.
PAUL: That's why they don't prefer finding. That's the main thing.
Salman: Okay, my next question, in the beginning, while you were just giving some idea of vector DBN embedding, you gave an example, like, my name is Paul, and then you did assign a number for each word, like, that is… that is 4D vector, that my name is Paul.
Salman: But we can introduce more dimensions to Ascend.
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, for sure. This is deep learning. 1 lakh dimension, 10 lakh, 15 lakh, this is nothing.
Salman: No, it need not to be just the four-dimension, or one word.
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, it's not happening.
Salman: but for me.
PAUL: So, any dimension. Like, when I'll be creating sparse vectors, very specifically for algorithms like BM25, in future classes I'll be talking about, where we take a dimension starting from 30,000 to 50,000.
PAUL: Those are sparse vectors, and generally for dense vector, we don't take such a big dimension, we take somewhere starting from 386 to 3072. That is the law for now.
Salman: Okay, so is there any link that you can provide, you know, on this channel or any other channel, where one can understand all these embeddings? I know how.
PAUL: certain.
Salman: what to…
PAUL: Okay, embeddings?
PAUL: different type of embeddings you will get, and this is a common topic, okay? But, those sparse vector and these vector embeddings, I'll be teaching you in class, because that is related to that.
Salman: Okay, you'll be.
PAUL: party too.
PAUL: I'm… I will be only teaching then since past, but the other, that long list that I have shared, few researches from 2013-14 Stanford, those things I'll be… directly, you can search, like, what is concurrency matrix, give you an example in ChatGPT, and you can directly… because these are very small concepts. So, is sparse vector, or…
Salman: Okay, sparse vector and dense vector are just the embedding technique, or a general concept? I know in sparse vector has so many of the rules.
PAUL: Generally, for RAG, we use only test vectors.
Salman: density.
PAUL: Because sometimes we feel that we need to build a hybrid search system.
PAUL: Okay, because sparse vectors are much more text-based algorithms.
PAUL: Okay, whereas dense vectors are much more deep learning-based encore.
PAUL: Okay, so the idea is to combine both the techniques, which is referred to as hybrid search.
PAUL: Okay, now the pusher comes, it comes with the price, that's why.
PAUL: Okay, when you are creating vectors, so if you're using any boosted good data mix for production, okay, then if the number of vector increases, or the dimensions of the vector increases, your cost will increase.
PAUL: So, when you are doing the entire cost optimization, then you need to take care of that. So, I'll be talking about this when I'll be discussing in the embeddings lecture.
Salman: Okay, so there will be an algorithm which generates a dense vector. There will be an.
PAUL: Yes, yes.
Salman: is not an algorithm, right? It is just an output, basically.
PAUL: ESJS vector is an output. Actually, the embedding is an output.
Salman: Okay, that admitting, we are calling it as a vector.
Salman: And which algorithm you would be teaching, you know, while doing this, or…
PAUL: I'll be talking about BM25 for sparse vector, majorly, because other algorithms for embedding are providing a sample one, but the original formula, if I show you more, it's just, like, half research paper.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why it's mathematics, that it's not really needed for anyone. Nobody cares about that. You have to understand that, okay, these are the models. I'll be telling you how to select the best embedding models, based on the benchmark that we have in.
Salman: Yeah, that is better, right. At least one should have some comparison point which would.
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
Salman: Okay, thanks, Paul.
PAUL: All right, Salman. Yes, next.
KaushikSaha: Hey, Paul.
PAUL: I won't. Yeah, yeah, gotcha.
KaushikSaha: hub.
KaushikSaha: Well,
KaushikSaha: as a part of the architecture explanation, you have explained the chunking, embedding model, and all. I believe, in later on stage, we'll be, also understanding more on the embedding, because you have mentioned a couple of.
PAUL: I mean, I don't have those knowledge.
PAUL: Yeah. I have just told you the components, I've not gone depth in any component.
KaushikSaha: Okay, yeah, that is. I'll be going in depth. It will be probably just take about after 3 weeks or 4 weeks.
PAUL: Once we start with simple, that's why in the PDF, I have written simple first.
PAUL: It's simple, Raga.
KaushikSaha: Sure.
PAUL: Hey, Louis.
KaushikSaha: Understood.
PAUL: the conference.
KaushikSaha: Okay, the point is, I don't have much knowledge on the NLP, the point, the topic, like, transformation encoder or tokenization, which way you were explaining, right? So, probably it may need on this process also. So, would you suggest some topics…
PAUL: Let me see, let me just talk with Kresh. I don't… if we have that RAG,
PAUL: That NLP course. Okay, then probably for your best, to everyone, I will ask to create the course.
PAUL: Okay, if not this month, then probably next month. In the meantime, let me see. Because I know in its YouTube channel, everything is available. It's just, I have to ask my intern, and I will, in Notion, I will add those links. Transformers is very, very important. It's really, like, in every interview, this is the first question.
PAUL: IP. That's right.
PAUL: Okay? Sure.
KaushikSaha: I think,
KaushikSaha: Oh, sorry, one more thing that maybe, if we… if you share also the link, it may be… we may not get enough time to deep dive while we are doing the RAG course as well, right?
PAUL: Okay.
KaushikSaha: So maybe the major things which we can at least understand after, getting those topics, understanding the topic, so that I… we can understand what you are saying or what you are explaining. So that I was thinking that.
PAUL: If you are having less time, always use AI to do the summarization part, and just… Yeah, so the topic, that is what…
PAUL: That's why I told you, now, next week, already the research paper that I'll be discussing.
KaushikSaha: Okay, okay.
PAUL: Okay, that is the main paper, and it will take time, because it has a lot of digraphs, and we will explain those things step by step.
KaushikSaha: Okay, okay. Sure, sure, sure. Thank you.
PAUL: Alright. I'm sharing the PDM link, okay, I am attaching it in Notion.
PAUL: Yes, in the meantime, next, please go ahead.
Ashok: Hey, Paul. I know you started the whole conversation with saying that the LLMs, they don't have access to the private data, right? That's one of the selling points for RAG, right?
Ashok: But I have a question, or more a confusion, to do with the security and compliance, right? Say, the data is private for a reason, isn't it?
Ashok: And when you start using the embeddings, right, you are, in fact, you are submitting your data
Ashok: to companies like, I don't know, Cloud or, you know, OpenAI and all these things. So practically.
Ashok: if you look at any enterprise, or any major enterprise, with security and compliance being the, the huge issue these days, I don't know how practically this thing is possible.
Ashok: Right? The only thing I can think of is hosting the LLMs on-prem or locally, right? Which is not cheap, right? I know Microsoft is, I know in the US, at least, these days, Microsoft is selling their Azure OpenAI service.
Ashok: where they are saying, hey, this is more reliable, secured, and all those things, right? So, leaving those things aside, just for other corporations, let's say mid-size or small caps or whatnot, I don't know how this thing is practically feasible, because you're exposing a lot of security data outside.
Ashok: And that is a… that's why I said there's a very good reason why the data is private.
PAUL: At the end of the day, you need to host it in your own frame.
PAUL: Indian banks who are using RAM, if I'm talking about Indian banks, they are pretty much everything is on-prem. At that point of time, they will be building a server.
PAUL: Okay, and for that server, you need GPUs. It's not like you need a lot of GPUs, just at least.
Ashok: God.
PAUL: H100 will do the job for RAM. Then again, it depends upon the traffic. If you feel you fill up a lot of traffic, then probably you might increase the number of chicks.
PAUL: But at the end of the day, that is the best solution for security, because nobody loves to expose their data to OpenAI. They have different type of data sharing agreements, okay, they try to do HIPAA compliance and other things, but really, I don't trust.
PAUL: banks don't trust AWS, neither of those. So they always use on-prem-based solutions. They host everything on-prem.
PAUL: That's the only thing. Otherwise, there is nothing that weakened.
PAUL: If somebody is a small-scale organization, most of them are medium-scale, they always stick to cloud.
PAUL: That is… The thing that you are worried about, it's a genuine concern.
PAUL: Because at the end of the day, for AI,
PAUL: And the cyber laws that has been defined. There is only one continent which has defined it, it's only the European Union.
PAUL: Nobody in India, do you think there are laws specific to AI? Was very specific, like, what things should be done. Nobody else defined, neither in he was.
PAUL: It's only the European Union that they have defined, okay.
PAUL: Out of those, nobody follows anything.
PAUL: Okay, I don't know, probably, it might take the next 20 or 25 years, one decade more, to define, like, every country will have their own AI.
PAUL: Okay, things will be…
Ashok: From a prospective…
Ashok: Sorry to interrupt. So the financial institutions and all those people, they are hosting locally. LLMs, Orchestrator, VectorDBs, and everything, right? That's a trend we are seeing?
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, you are exactly correct. That's what's the tool. For example, let's take an example of Quadrant.
PAUL: Quadrant has their own hosted vector DB selection. Okay, where they use this? AWS or others.
PAUL: Now, they have an enterprise solution, where they come, they provide their product, they will ask you which cloud you use. It can be any cloud, or it can be a bare metal. They will ask you, take a bare metal server and do the whole setup.
PAUL: Everybody's providing that. It means that they will bring their solution, but yeah, there will be a long-term contract for that. That's the only thing.
Ashok: Okay.
PAUL: I'm clear now, yeah.
Ashok: Yeah.
Ashok: Alright, got it. Thank you.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Okay, I've shared the Drive link, you can see here, the Ultimate Drag document hub. Okay, so here in the notes file, I have added the Google Drive link. So simply, you can click this link, and this will be the main database of all the notes that I'll be sharing, going forward.
PAUL: Alright, let's move to our next, let's go with Surajitas, Viraja's there, Madhasaraki, Sait Eja, Rohan, okay, multiple people I have unmuted, so yes, one of my running guys can vote.
Suraj D S: Apple. I guess Apple.
PAUL: Yes, yes, you are audit.
Suraj D S: Yeah, yeah, thanks for the… all the information, but I do have a few queries, like, I have worked.
PAUL: Yeah, boy.
Suraj D S: data, but, how do we actually work on the images, video, and audio, like, building RAG applications, like, in terms of the.
PAUL: Like, they will be having different embedding models, that's the one.
PAUL: Okay, generally for… see, for video, there is no video embedding model. You convert the videos into images, and then for those images, you'll be using an embedding model like Clip. There are so many multimodal embedding models.
PAUL: Because the embedding strategy will change.
Suraj D S: You know, like, what would be the vector stores for these, multi-.
PAUL: collector stall.
PAUL: When I do multimodal, it means that the same thing, at the end of the day, it's a numeric representation.
Suraj D S: Okay.
PAUL: There is no change in that.
Suraj D S: Okay, yeah, got it. And, you will…
PAUL: only… see, there will be only two changes. One, the embedding model, which has to be a multimodal support.
PAUL: And if you want, the LLM, which should have a multimodal support. Only two things that needs to be modified. Rest, everything is pretty much the same stuff.
Suraj D S: Okay. And also, the similarity search will also follow the same, right?
Suraj D S: Yeah, okay.
PAUL: There, the search algorithm can be changed. You can move to something like focal loss and others. Other loss functions are there very specifically. It depends upon the task exact.
Suraj D S: Okay, yeah. And also, you mentioned that you will be covering up, how do we actually choose the embedding model, or,
PAUL: Thanks for listening.
Suraj D S: Fuck yeah.
PAUL: These things, practically whenever we start at least the practicals, we'll be talking about that.
Suraj D S: Yep, okay, I'm good, thanks.
PAUL: Alright, Suraj. Next, Viraj?
VRAJ PATEL: Hi, Seth.
PAUL: That's game.
VRAJ PATEL: So, thank you so much, sir, for today's session, and I'll also be part of the Agent TK 1.0 batch, so I know that you shared a lot of new things to the entire batch and everything, so…
PAUL: the batch got launched late. I thought it would be launched in September, okay, but it got launched.
VRAJ PATEL: Yeah. So, my first question is that in the REG application, we are using the embedding models, right? So, whatever the embedding models that we use for data ingestion, the same embedding model we are using for data retrieval.
PAUL: Correct.
VRAJ PATEL: So, if the… any embedding model will be deprecated, or any new embedding model will come. So, do we need to use the… or do we need to do the data in JSON with the new model?
PAUL: So, we generally keep the model fixed, because I don't want to change the entire solution.
PAUL: So, generally, what happens if.
VRAJ PATEL: Absolutely.
PAUL: OpenAir and others, okay? So, when you have an enterprise-based, like, account, okay, the deprecated models are also available.
PAUL: In that case. Okay, but for general accounts, deprecated models you cannot access. So sometimes, I will show you that open source models perform better than paid models.
PAUL: I prefer always, like, for production, if I go with… okay, I will select open source models, because when I will show you the MTV leaderboard, you will see that open source models are performing better than paid ones.
PAUL: So most of the times, people move ahead with that.
PAUL: And there are certain vector DB solutions, okay, like Pinecone and others, where they have their own model hosted. So, if you are using VectorDB as Pinecone, okay, then there is a specific model which is always hosted.
VRAJ PATEL: Okay, and you can always use that model.
PAUL: They will charge for that, for sure, but that model is fixed. Okay, they never removed that particular model. So these many vector TV solution guys are hosting the open source models in their own hands.
VRAJ PATEL: Yeah, yeah. And the second thing is that, I'm very much interested to know about the… how's the LLM model will be trained and everything. So, recently, in a few days, I just go through the one book.
VRAJ PATEL: Oh, from the main publication, building the LLM from the scratch.
PAUL: That is by, Salaksha Rashma.
VRAJ PATEL: Yeah, yeah. So, it'll be good on…
PAUL: Rashka's a nice guy. I have met him. That's why. Krisha's also met him. Rashka is really good. Even, he's working currently in Lightning AI. We met the Lightning AI CEO also.
PAUL: That's why. Oh, great guys. They have good products. That's why I always promote Lightning. Lightning is really… if somebody's system is not working, you can do everything in the cloud. The book is really good for starters, and you can always look into Antraj Kaparti YouTube videos.
PAUL: Those are, like, The best content that you can get.
VRAJ PATEL: Yes, yes, sir. Thank you, thank you so much, sir.
PAUL: Okay. All right, because I remember in your batch, I've shared major authors, okay, even cheap women. Chipwin books are also really great.
VRAJ PATEL: Alright.
VRAJ PATEL: Sir, which YouTube channel you record?
PAUL: Andrish Kaparti. Andrish Kaparti is the guy who has designed Tesla. Like, I learned from Andrish Kaparti from Stanford Lectures back in 2016. He used to take the computer vision lectures there. Then he went to Tesla, even he has contributed in OpenAI, so…
PAUL: Very good researchers.
VRAJ PATEL: And Chris, thank you so much.
PAUL: Yeah.
PAUL: Alright, next, Madhasar.
Mudassar Hakim: Hey, Paul. Nice session overall today. I've been in places trying to, you know, bring everything in context.
Mudassar Hakim: Also, I think, so the way the queries are getting resolved is slightly different over here.
Mudassar Hakim: I think, I probably need to document them and, you know, kind of while talking to the end of the class. So I've not been able to recall all the routes I had.
Mudassar Hakim: But, I think I know this part, but I just want to confirm that in one of the sections where you were explaining the…
Mudassar Hakim: the RAG-based approach. You said, the context plus the query plus the prompt.
Mudassar Hakim: So… so, context, I get it.
PAUL: What is the augmentation phase.
Mudassar Hakim: Right. When text, I get it, where it is coming from. The query and the prompt. The prompt is something where I, as a customer or a user, will ask the question.
Mudassar Hakim: Oh, sorry, that's a quid.
PAUL: That is… that is the query.
Mudassar Hakim: That is the query. And prompt is what exactly? And I wanted an example is…
PAUL: I'll be showing you during the practicals. It's a set of instructions. So, for example, how structured, like, do you know about structured output?
PAUL: inline chain, or in other places. If you don't know, I will show in the next practical class. You will see, like, how you want the LLM to generate the response in what structure.
Mudassar Hakim: So, let me then call out, and then you can tell me if I'm going the right direction or not. So, let's say that I have created a model or a program that basically tells me if my resume is as per the job description or not.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, that's the entire area of work. So…
PAUL: Thank you.
Mudassar Hakim: the prompt would be where I would write the prompt, where I say…
PAUL: It'll be something like this, yeah.
Mudassar Hakim: Correct, right?
PAUL: Do I resume it?
PAUL: I've been export, okay.
Mudassar Hakim: The user, the role, the action kind of thing. That's the prompt you're referring to, right? Yes, yes. And the query… the query would be the input coming in, in terms of the… Yes, yes. Right? That's what the difference is, correct? I mean…
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, exactly. That's why I told you it's a setup instructions, that's why.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, okay, yeah, that is something I wanted to clear. With respect to NLP, the interesting thing is that I've gone through this course once before, not exactly with Krishnak, with respect to NLP, but the problem is that
Mudassar Hakim: I've heard these models, tech tools are what to work, but obviously I don't recall everything right now. I'll definitely go and brush up, but my point is that no matter how many times I go back and read it, I might not be able to…
Mudassar Hakim: Re-collect everything to the teeth.
Mudassar Hakim: I might have some idea, but I'll try my best to, you know, maybe.
PAUL: You know, it happens, like, we keep on teaching, so we remember these things, but for sequences, sequence, the best content that you will be getting is JR Lama.
PAUL: Okay, Alama, sequence to sequence, that guy has created awesome animation, which will actually help you.
Mudassar Hakim: Oh, from Google Class.
PAUL: this one, and the Illustrator transform on this one. Anybody wants to go through this.
Mudassar Hakim: This guy has great blog sites. Yeah.
PAUL: The whole world is using his content.
PAUL: Okay, so these type of links, I'll be adding it in the Notion also, I know. Many of you will, remember.
Mudassar Hakim: Hello, this is Ronald.
PAUL: Yep.
Mudassar Hakim: Yeah, but that's what I was saying, during the session, by the way, apologies for the background noise, my kid is running around me.
PAUL: Okay, good.
Mudassar Hakim: And, so that's the reason why, you know, there's gonna be times where you might be definitely asking me some very fundamental questions, and probably, at least I might be a noob in that area, or might not be able to recollect. So just wanted to call that piece out. Okay, fine.
PAUL: The idea is, if you don't know something after the lecture, go and check.
Mudassar Hakim: What? Exactly.
PAUL: 5 minutes on that. That is my only bare minimum request.
Mudassar Hakim: Absolutely, absolutely. I mean, I understand at the end of the day, you're going to set the foundations. For example, I'm pretty glad we took this paper today. It really haunts me to…
Mudassar Hakim: take up the task of reading the entire paper, but at least when I know the context, the pieces which matter, it helps me to get into it, at least. I might not say I might be able to.
PAUL: That's the same thing even I'll be doing in classes. I cannot go through the entire paper. Exactly. That's why I will always go through the abstract and the core part of the paper. That's what matters to me.
PAUL: And, sometimes I might relate it just, like, about Saturday I've read a paper.
PAUL: On Sunday, the idea is to compare Sunday's people with Saturday's people, so that you understand the pros and cons.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, okay. So, I'm just gonna have… take another few more minutes, where I'll just confirm what my understanding is.
Mudassar Hakim: And, you know, making sure that I'm heading the right direction or not. The key areas which you went into was the abstract, which is fine. It gave a sense of things, in which you mentioned one is the, RAG, which, you know, we introduced the RAG models with the parametric memories pre-page sequencing models, and non-parametric memories, and then swept off Wikipedia.
Mudassar Hakim: So basically, my parametric is the weights which my SQL model has been trained on, and and non-parametric is the dense vectors coming from the Wikipedia, right? That's… that's the deal.
PAUL: Yes, yes, Wikipedia data was the external data source that they have used.
Mudassar Hakim: Yeah, so here I get… here I get the deal that without the RAG, it relies only on what it memorized, right? And it cannot update the facts, and it cannot explain things better. But with RAG, it concerns the return external knowledge, you know, gets updated data, and gives more… better justification.
Mudassar Hakim: What my question is here…
Mudassar Hakim: In this process, does it update its existing weights that are there in its parametric level? For example.
PAUL: No, no, no, no, no, no, it's frozen.
Mudassar Hakim: rules of weight.
PAUL: always frozen.
Mudassar Hakim: Exactly, exactly. So, let's say, for example, I… as per my, parametric memory, it knows that, I'm just going to take a very vague example, that Kolkata… Kolkata was Kolkata, right? So, it takes that, okay, it is Kolkata.
Mudassar Hakim: But now, as per my non-parametric memory, I get to know that it was Kolkata before, not Skolkata.
Mudassar Hakim: So…
Mudassar Hakim: at the end of the day, there is a bit of a churn here, right? That will always happen, even though I know that my parametric memory has this information that this
Mudassar Hakim: this is…
PAUL: You lost your voice, or what?
Mudassar Hakim: Hello? I'm audible?
Mudassar Hakim: A module?
Mudassar Hakim: I'm audible?
PAUL: Just wait.
PAUL: Are you calling?
Mudassar Hakim: You're calling on.
PAUL: Okay, yeah, yeah, yeah, my microphone changed. Just wait one minute, one minute, one minute.
PAUL: Their batteries down.
Mudassar Hakim: Mobile, slow down swing today.
PAUL: Come on… Yes.
PAUL: Okay, yeah, now we go ahead. I think I'll be good.
PAUL: I'm audible now? Yes, yes, yes, yes, you were audible, it was my…
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, excellent.
PAUL: That battery down as well.
Mudassar Hakim: No worries, no worries, man, no worries. So, what I was trying to say is that, I gave the example of Kolkata and Kolkata, right? So, my parametric memory has Kolkata, okay? But as I used my non-parametric memory, externally, I came to know that, you know, it's no longer called as Kolkata, it's Kolkata.
Mudassar Hakim: So, with the RAG approach, this basically means that I will always have that churn unless and until I update my paramedic memory.
Mudassar Hakim: That chirp will always exist.
PAUL: Okay. Now, your understanding, I will change it a little bit toward the embedding level. Okay, so when, you are actually creating the embeddings for Calcutta and Kolkata, very specifically, okay? Now, in that high-dimensional vector, those two things will be very, very close.
PAUL: Okay, so…
Mudassar Hakim: Got it.
PAUL: The network knows, so actually, with respect to the embedding dimension representation, the values that they will have, the mathematical values, they will be very, very close to one another. So, visual perspective, if I'm talking about, if you think about a 300 dimension, those two things will always be close, just like king and queen. That is the underlying fundamental concept of embedding.
Mudassar Hakim: From a proximity perspective, cosine similarity perspective, they both will be close. But from an outcome perspective, where it has to give a certain outcome, a final outcome.
PAUL: It will have to, at the end of the day, choose either one, either the Kolkata or the Khalas.
PAUL: Yes. Right? That, it will choose…
Mudassar Hakim: choose, and I also get this part using RAT, it will definitely go and choose Kolkata, because it has the updated information, correct?
PAUL: Yes, see, the more time it says Kolkata, it will use. More Kolkata.
Mudassar Hakim: The idea is the appearance of the same word, more time.
PAUL: Yes. In your documents or corpus.
Mudassar Hakim: Oh, okay.
PAUL: that will, that will be the… what? The idea is that if it appears more.
Mudassar Hakim: losing your job.
PAUL: Vivid Apple.
Mudassar Hakim: That's missing.
PAUL: you'll be shown this.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, okay, the.
PAUL: You have to drink, you're.
Mudassar Hakim: the TDF TD IDF thing, is it?
PAUL: Yes, you can relate to that concept. The same thing happens here also. At the end of the day, it's an embedding-level thing.
PAUL: Because LLMs can easily understand this particular context. For that, you really don't have to worry. Whatever the stuff which is occurring more at any point of time, that will be reflected in your
PAUL: Final output.
Mudassar Hakim: quarter.
Mudassar Hakim: Got it. So basically, it's a one-time thing, it's not a recurring churn that will happen, it's a one-time change, or that building of that memory that will happen. That, okay, it's called karta, it's not Kalkata.
PAUL: Yes, because the same thing, because so many things are updated with their names, so it always happens.
Mudassar Hakim: Right. And then you mentioned about the RAT sequence and the RAT toker, right? So, the rack sequence is, if I have to just correlate to a naive example, is like, pick one passage and generate the whole answer from it. That's what RAT sequence is all about. But if I talk about.
PAUL: about the one document, the same…
PAUL: passage, that's why it's the same document that I have been referring.
Mudassar Hakim: Correct. And if I talk about RAT token, it's like, at every word I generate, I may switch which passage I'm using. It will keep on,
PAUL: It gives different chunks from different documents.
Mudassar Hakim: Got it.
Mudassar Hakim: Correct.
Mudassar Hakim: Sorry, can you repeat that?
PAUL: Different chunks from different documents.
Mudassar Hakim: Different chunks of different documents, as compared to a single document.
PAUL: Yes, they're at different chunks, but from the same document.
PAUL: That is a rack sequence.
Mudassar Hakim: Excellent.
PAUL: The sequence. Sequence Y? One chunk, another chunk, another chunk. That sequence is my thing. But for 2Ks.
Mudassar Hakim: It can be…
PAUL: Different chams from different documents.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay. Got it.
Mudassar Hakim: Got it, got it, got it, got it.
Mudassar Hakim: And, the numbers, right? If you could just quickly open that paper, if it's possible. I just wanted to verify the numbers and their meaning. For example, the human evaluation
Mudassar Hakim: Question generator. Factuality, specificity.
Mudassar Hakim: Bar, drag.
Mudassar Hakim: Yeah, yeah. So, here, what is the difference between, first of all, factuality and specificity? Because fact is a fact. But when we say if specificity is more.
PAUL: To do these type of evaluations, you have to create separate evaluation data sets. Okay, now based on that evaluation dataset that they have created, these numbers are coming.
Mudassar Hakim: I'm asking a little more fundamental question here. What does… how does factuality and specificity differ here, is what I'm trying to understand. I mean, if you can use small example, a basic naive example, what it means, it is more factual, and what is more specific?
PAUL: Based on the metric that they have defined here. Okay, so factuality means that the exact fact which will be available in either type of your memory.
PAUL: As simple as that.
Mudassar Hakim: I think.
PAUL: It can be parametric, it can be non-parametric. Okay. Now, specificity specifically defines whether it is available in the memory or not.
PAUL: One is an exact match.
Mudassar Hakim: one is…
PAUL: the availability?
Mudassar Hakim: What is that exact match, and the other.
PAUL: One is the availability. Like, it is not sure that every time that particular information will be available within a certain memory.
PAUL: Specificity, what is the meaning of specificity in machine learning?
PAUL: Can you relate?
Mudassar Hakim: Specificity… no, not right now, at least.
PAUL: Okay. Okay, because that's why, like, precision, there is an exact match that happens.
Mudassar Hakim: I know, I know precision, Recall, and F1. I know those…
PAUL: ICP also comes there also, no?
Mudassar Hakim: Yeah, I think I missed… I don't want to recall the specificity part of it.
PAUL: Okay. And so, generally for any type of classification problem, if I'm doing, or any type of fact check, okay, then we actually check it, like, I don't remember the formula, I think it's something like true negative divided by.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, now I remember. Okay, okay.
PAUL: So.
Mudassar Hakim: For some reason, I was assuming this to be, like, a grammatical difference. That's the reason why I went through that. But now I remember, there is a formula for… because translation also works that way.
PAUL: A number of events positive.
Mudassar Hakim: negative divided by the number of events, kind of a formula that gets created. Okay, so it's a formula-driven area by which these numbers are getting generated, factuality and specificity.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, and it has basically taken different models at a time. Both individually, RAG individually, then both?
Mudassar Hakim: And, So, in this case, I guess they're both being good and poor. No majority means?
PAUL: No majority means neither of them are performing.
PAUL: It means that not getting responses in simple terms.
Mudassar Hakim: I thought that would be both poor.
PAUL: No, no, no, that is not cool. If you are getting at least some level of responses, then that is referred to us.
PAUL: Ultimately, we're not getting any type of responses.
Mudassar Hakim: Gotcha. Both core means you're getting at least something, rather than…
PAUL: But the quality of responses are, like, you have only 10% information, whereas 90% of information is not factual. It's totally out of the context.
Mudassar Hakim: Got it. So no majority means it's not there at all. That's what it means.
Mudassar Hakim: And, MS Marco and Jeopardy QGen. This is, like, a different.
PAUL: dataset.
Mudassar Hakim: dataset, okay. And I get the BART and the rag. What is gold here?
PAUL: Okay, this is, another model.
PAUL: Okay, as another mod list. Yes.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, okay, okay, okay. Just for a comparison perspective, they gave this.
PAUL: Hey, spend time on this. Like, if you have to spend time.
Mudassar Hakim: Right. Because this is something, like, see.
PAUL: If you spend just 5 to 10 minutes, you will understand that what they are trying to say, because these are all models. BERT is a model, track token is a model, rack sequence is a model. So forage and Gold will also be a model.
Mudassar Hakim: Correct, correct. Just wanted to confirm that.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay.
Mudassar Hakim: So, in this case, the table 6, basically, what we are getting to know is, there is birth, sorry, BM25, frozen retriever, and fully learned retriever, right? These three things we are comparing.
PAUL: Yes, and we are getting the best result in the dense one.
Mudassar Hakim: Correct. The Dense Learn Retrieval works better than Frozen Retriever, and that Frozen Retriever works better than BM35 Retrieval.
PAUL: BAM25 is the worst you can think about. When I'll be teaching you hybrid such, then I'll be talking, so this is a sparse vector. Okay, so this is the dense one, the last… these two are the dense, these two are the sparse.
PAUL: Sparse vector is, like, if there's an exact match, then only it performs.
PAUL: Okay, it means that water by what, everything has to be matched then.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: All right, I was coming to the other candidate, I know he's taking time, but fine. But these are some things that you guys should also know.
Mudassar Hakim: Correct, correct. Okay, cool, cool, Paul. Thanks. I'll take a pause then here. Thanks.
PAUL: Okay, okay, alright, yeah, next.
saiteja: Well, that's happening?
PAUL: Thank you. Yes, I could just go ahead.
saiteja: Hello, sir, thank you for your teaching, sir. I really liked how you explained each and every
saiteja: Point. Sir, sir, my question is…
saiteja: Sir, I don't know NPL that much, so are there any NLG.
saiteja: Spend some time.
PAUL: I'll be adding some resources, and probably let me see if I can get the coupon for that Udemy course of which. That will help you to… okay, let me check, this week, and probably by Saturday, I will let you know. In the meantime, I'll be providing few videos that you can at least go through.
saiteja: Okay, sir. Thank you, sir.
PAUL: Okay, next, Sunil… Okay, Sunil, you have not raised hand. Okay, alright. Anybody else? Rohan?
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, I'm here, can you hear me?
Rohan: Yeah, thank you for the opportunity. I wanted to ask a question regarding the,
Rohan: DPR passage code that you're showing. And I saw that there were two different encoding models for the question and the context. Yes.
Rohan: So, if you have two different encoding models, how can we calculate the similarity, and how does that work?
PAUL: You have two different encoders, you have to think in that way.
PAUL: Okay, so if…
Rohan: So, if I'm encoding one text with a different encoder, and the other one with a different encoder, and we try to get the similarity.
PAUL: Encoder, say, encoder, after that you do a tokenization.
PAUL: And after that, you create it. Okay, so right now, generally, generally in RAG, what you do, you try to use the same embedding model everywhere.
PAUL: But generally, in the DPR research, okay, it is not necessary that you use the same one. You can have a different embedding.
PAUL: Okay, but the idea is that you use similar encoders. In the practical use case I have shown, both the embeddings were from Facebook.
PAUL: Okay, so I know the embedding model of that encoder is having a very similar parameter.
PAUL: So, when they have shown it in the research, their underlying embedding algorithms are actually the same for both the encoders.
PAUL: Your point is at this point. Nobody says that, but it's there.
Rohan: Okay, so, so underlying, it's still using a similar, end…
PAUL: Embedding algorithm is the same in both the encoders.
Rohan: Okay.
Rohan: Yeah, that's what my confusion was, like… How are we doing.
PAUL: Actually, what happens now, if you change the embedding algorithms in RAG also, just think about during
PAUL: and your data ingestion phase, you have used an OpenAI, okay? Later on, during the retrieval phase, if you try to use a Gemini model, we have seen it will give the response.
PAUL: But if you use the same embedding model, you get better responses. That's the only thing. The idea, we feel that using similar embedding models always give a better context. Let's come back to using different embedding models.
PAUL: It's not like that, it will not work. It will, but the quality of the context somehow will feel that it gets reduced.
Rohan: Okay, yeah, yeah, thanks for the explanation. And one, note as I mentioned, so if you could have shared the research paper a bit earlier, we could have… I would have at least, or everybody else would have got a chance to go through it to…
PAUL: Go through it now also, okay, see, in class, when I teach the iPads beforehand, see, like, I know which day I will teach, that's why for next Saturday, I've already provided. Okay, now, again…
PAUL: what will be after that, little bit after thing. Sometimes it depends upon an algorithm, or a type of rack. Okay, so I will plan that, and I will attach it there. You'll always get it at least before the class.
PAUL: Because sometimes I am also late in preparing the quantitative to understand, okay, I take a decision probably one night before.
PAUL: So, it happens with me, but sometimes I will tell you, because I knew at least 2 weeks plans from now.
PAUL: Okay.
Rohan: Okay, yeah, yeah, thank you so much.
PAUL: All right. So, Rohan, next iPhone.
PAUL: Yeah.
iPhone: Can you hear me?
PAUL: Yes. Yeah.
iPhone: Okay. Oh.
iPhone: Paul, just, first of all, thanks for the session, and I have a couple of questions. So, when it comes to the embedding part, right, and we are storing this embeddings in the vector database, and
iPhone: these embeddings I have generated with a couple of my PDF files, right? And what happens? Suddenly, there is a change coming to that PDF, and one additional page gets added to it, into that whole drive.
iPhone: So now… when we create the… when we try to create the embedding ETMs.
iPhone: Do we remove the older embeddings from the vector database and load the whole PDFs again, or we just…
iPhone: Upload the delta part.
PAUL: You can do the upload… you can upload the delta part also. No worries in that.
PAUL: You have to maintain a version control for the files, basically.
PAUL: So what happens, generally?
PAUL: when you are creating the metadata for the… actually, this, again, advanced topic, so I hope you know, because you have worked on that. So, in the metadata, for example, for every file, you'll be keeping the URL or something, the path.
iPhone: Okay, slash, that's fine.
PAUL: Okay, so when you know that a certain file has changed, and there is a delta amount of content which has been added, you need to look into the file. And from the last chunk of that file which was created, now you need to pick up, and again, you can add it in a certain index, very specifically for that file, or anywhere.
iPhone: So, while in your upcoming sessions, you're going to take care of… you're going to show…
PAUL: Those are production-level things. You can't ask me to show everything related to production.
PAUL: Really, like, these are production-level issues.
PAUL: Okay, because, you need to… if I'm working with GitHub, I need to take care of the commits.
PAUL: Okay, I need to track the commands. In simple terms, I am telling you. It's a simple level implementation, it's not rocket science, I've told you. Okay, you just need to keep a version control of all your files, what are being changed. I track it through GitHub, it depends upon the file format also.
PAUL: Okay, so…
PAUL: You can do that. It's not, because it's simple, like, what are the recent changes, and, based on your chunking mechanism, what is available in your metadata? The more diverse metadata you have.
PAUL: Most of these things, I do the filtering in metadata.
PAUL: the file path, okay, probably for a file, a specific chunk, okay, so all those parameters that I can define, the chunk ID, okay, based on a certain algorithm, I can define it.
PAUL: No, yes, it is possible.
PAUL: That's not collected.
iPhone: Okay, got it. And…
iPhone: Other part is, in this whole system of a RAG, right, are we also going to take care of the scaling, of the things in…
PAUL: Just learned, directly scaling team, day one, you were asking me to scale.
PAUL: No, no, no, I'm not asking, I'm asking… You can ask me this question after 3 months, at least.
iPhone: Okay.
PAUL: See, do you think scaling is done by AI engineers?
PAUL: No. Who does the scale?
PAUL: Infrastructure, who takes? It's the ops guys.
iPhone: Yes.
PAUL: Then…
PAUL: At the end of the day, I can do… I can put it in an autoscale. Simply, EKS cluster, I will put it. I can put it in Farget and other stuff.
PAUL: Okay, so infrastructure can take care of that, really, for a RAG. At the end of the day, I feel that the infrastructure does the job more. Few things from the RAG perspective, that needs to be taken care of.
iPhone: Okay, perfect. Thanks, Paul.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Yes, next. Many people I have unmuted. Please go one by one.
Saranya Sathanandam: Hi, do you hear me and Lisa?
PAUL: Saran, you go first.
Saranya Sathanandam: Yeah, sir, this is my first time getting into learning this, all these AI concepts, so, please, bear with me if I'm asking some very silly question or something. So, so I understood the concept of this, RAG, which uses this non-parametric memory.
Saranya Sathanandam: So my question is that in my organization, if I have to use my RDBMS as one of the ingestion source.
Saranya Sathanandam: Is that possible? Because we store a lot of data in the databases, and if I have to, my use case needs to…
Saranya Sathanandam: take the data from the database instead of just from the file system.
PAUL: Your data source will change. Basically, for any type of SQL-based or NoSQL MongoDB, at any point of time, if you want to read certain tables and other things, you can bring that into the picture. That is being done, the common standard in RAM.
PAUL: Because, sometimes we always try to, identify the relationship between tables, between keys, and that.
PAUL: Okay, and it's not only about that, sometimes we add additional knowledge bases, very specifically certain documents related to database, so that the LLM understands this better. But sometimes I feel that it's not necessary, I don't need to expose my
PAUL: complete database, probably certain part based on that, thing that I am doing, because exposing your database to LLMs is not a good practice, actually.
PAUL: then…
PAUL: Okay, so I feel that, yes, it is possible. You can go through, and then you can bring that data. It is possible.
PAUL: People have done. You can simply check your productvana.ai. It's one of the most famous products.
Saranya Sathanandam: Can I come back again? What is that?
PAUL: Ovana.
PAUL: So, when you think about the product, do you think that there will be any startup who is doing… you have that mentality?
PAUL: There will be some startup, no? In the…
PAUL: Who will be working in these type of things?
PAUL: Okay, I'm sharing this one.
PAUL: Always think in that prospect.
PAUL: I always look for startups who do this, like, Okay, so, yes.
PAUL: Okay, I've shared that you can explode.
Saranya Sathanandam: Okay.
Saranya Sathanandam: Okay. So, on my, next question is…
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, you would.
Saranya Sathanandam: This data, if this data, right, that we are referencing from the RAG, if it is of a dynamic nature, right, it keeps changing, so whatever the embedding that is there in the vector database can also get out of date, right? So how do we… is there… needs to be some kind of process that needs to be.
PAUL: simple words.
PAUL: And it's the same question somebody who last asked. It means that if your source data changed, then what I will do?
PAUL: We need to keep a track of that. So, for example, with respect to GitHub, I take care of the comments.
PAUL: Similarly, in your case, you'll be having some type of file virtual system. Based on that, you will be knowing that, okay, this file got changed. Once you know that this file has been changed, then you have to look into the chunks of that. Very specifically, your starting chunk or end chunk, if it is in between somewhere. You need to track that document at least.
PAUL: Okay, very specifically, where that happened. Generally, in GitHub, it really tells us. That is one of the best things about GitHub that I see. Okay, but you need to have that file versioning control. If you don't have that, it becomes a problem.
Saranya Sathanandam: So it is our responsibility as the developer.
PAUL: Yes, that you have pinned.
Saranya Sathanandam: And…
PAUL: Whenever you are doing an update operation, I have seen one startup, they don't really take care of version. They simply delete the entire embedding, and they will create it.
PAUL: There is a startup who does that.
PAUL: Okay, but it is a good practice if your document is of small sense.
PAUL: But it's a very bad practice if your document is of very big size, because embedding always comes with a cost.
Saranya Sathanandam: Right.
Saranya Sathanandam: So, other question is, somebody mentioned that there is also a course for agentic AI, so some of the use cases that we are trying to now explore, the first thing that we will be starting, we will
Saranya Sathanandam: be using some agentic AI workflow. So, do you think… This course is not about…
PAUL: Excellent.
PAUL: This course is much more about RAG.
PAUL: You have one part very specifically with respect to AI agents. That is the end of the course, very specifically only where we'll be working with Lenka.
Saranya Sathanandam: Okay, so will there be anything that is coming up in the future for agentic AI?
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, Agentic 3.2 will come, but I think it will be in January or February. This year, RAG is the last batch that we'll be launching.
PAUL: If you feel, if you want to go through agents and other stuff, you can enroll in an Agentic 2.0 batch. The lectures are there. Later on, when the live class starts, you can switch to that.
PAUL: That's a common thing most students does.
PAUL: We'll be ahead of the batch. That's right.
Saranya Sathanandam: Okay, so another question is, how do I determine, like.
Saranya Sathanandam: For a… if you can give us some example of
Saranya Sathanandam: what could be a good use case, enterprise use case, when I should.
PAUL: See, I always try to keep it generic. Now, based on your domain, your SME, your expertise.
Saranya Sathanandam: So just to give us some basic understanding, if you can say that, okay, these are situations that may not be a candidate for a rack, there should be some… some simple enough concepts that you would use instead of going for… introducing some RAC complexity, right?
PAUL: See, the question that you asked, like.
PAUL: when we won't be using a rack.
Saranya Sathanandam: Right.
PAUL: The idea is very simple. When you don't want to bring your custom data, that's the main point. If you want to go with something generic, LLMs are always there. LLM does the generic stuff. But if you want your own custom data at any point of time, then you need right. Otherwise, you don't need RAM.
Saranya Sathanandam: Okay, so most of my projects I'm thinking about, say, always I need the data that we have, right? So… does that mean I always need the rack?
PAUL: If you are having custom data, and if you feel that the LLM is not having the knowledge about that, in that case, you need a rack for sure.
Saranya Sathanandam: Go.
PAUL: Because training and LLM is not a solution, that's right.
PAUL: I hope you get my point.
Saranya Sathanandam: Yeah.
Saranya Sathanandam: Thank you, sir. Thank you, I appreciate your time.
PAUL: Next, Venkatesh, then Rahul.
PAUL: Yes.
Venaktesh Gude: Pritesh, go ahead.
Venaktesh Gude: Yeah, so, thanks for the session, and, it's, it's, it's quite, explanative. And, so I have, no technical questions, so it's very good. Only one thing is, I would like to know if we have any,
Venaktesh Gude: You know, recommended book for these concepts.
Venaktesh Gude: So that, .
PAUL: care long.
PAUL: That one, I already shared the Stanford book.
Venaktesh Gude: That speech, and that has all these RAG implementations.
PAUL: That has some core fundamentals, like, if nobody has zero experience about NLP, okay, you can take up the topics, because…
PAUL: Leave the formulas, just the ideas, at least you know the concept.
PAUL: Okay, so we will skip the formulas for now. Basically, all the concepts are covered in that book.
Venaktesh Gude: Okay, yeah, anything specific to RAG or something, if you can…
PAUL: Rag part, I end everything with respect to rag, I will teach, because your rag is that ultimate rag pose.
PAUL: If anything is there with respect to it, that is my job.
PAUL: Starting, like, in 2020, what happened in 2019, what happened? Those things, if you want to know, then just follow that.
Venaktesh Gude: Okay, yeah, and not only this one, I've been following Chris's, you know, YouTube channel for some time. So, is there any place where you guys have the recommended books or something, that is noted down that will be good, we can share?
PAUL: I don't know, what do you want, exactly?
Venaktesh Gude: like, all other courses, like the machine learning, or, you know, RT learning, any books that…
Venaktesh Gude: If you guys have documented somewhere, like, you know, these are the recommended books that we can use.
PAUL: You can drop me a mail, okay, Vengat, I see, just drop me a mail regarding which books you want.
Venaktesh Gude: Okay.
PAUL: Because, see, like, probably I might have…
PAUL: Read some book back in 2017, again in 2021.
Venaktesh Gude: I know, I know, yeah, yeah, I know.
PAUL: That's right. Like, I will let you know based on, because I've not read a lot of books, but the major ones, like, which is very famous, those books only I have read.
PAUL: Okay.
Venaktesh Gude: Yeah, yeah, I just want to, you know, maintain the collection basically.
PAUL: Okay, so just drop me a mail related to which topic that you want. Based on that, I'll be sharing the book name and the author. Okay.
Venaktesh Gude: Definitely, yeah. Thank you. Thanks for the session, man.
PAUL: Thanks for having me.
Venaktesh Gude: to.
Rahul Parihar: Thanks, Paul. First of all, really appreciate your patience, man.
Rahul Parihar: This is really awesome. So my… I have two questions. First is, reading and understanding about the AI research papers.
Rahul Parihar: What sort of technique and step-by-step mechanism, like, the way you…
Rahul Parihar: First is abstract and intro, then the method. What are the key parameters that you would Try to analyze
Rahul Parihar: When reading those papers.
PAUL: upon the topics, really. Like, computer vision papers are a little bit different.
PAUL: NLP papers are a little bit different, so there is a common thing, but always, like, the abstract part, the experiment part, where they showcase all the benchmarks, I go to that part. And there is one part, which would be the architecture part, or the internal working.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is that where they try to compare their solution with some previously published solution.
PAUL: That might only be helpful.
PAUL: The other part I really don't focus on.
PAUL: Okay, because really, on different… 10 different type of data set, they have done the experiments. That, I can always look into a table, and I can… so I never read through those.
PAUL: Why really go through the abstract? Okay, their comparisons with the previous solutions, their internal architecture of the working part, and finally, like, how they are concluding it with the benchmarks. That is the main part. In any paper, you can only look into this.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah, you shared some of the papers in the initial discussion, like RAF Adaptive Language Models for Domain-specific RAG.
Rahul Parihar: And blended rag, and, you know, few other meta gen, you know, blended.
PAUL: Those are IBM research. I follow IBM research because I feel IBM research is good with respect to RAG and LLMs. So, in their research, a lot of things come. Like, really, in the whole world, nobody teaches about MetaChat.
PAUL: Okay, or blended methods.
PAUL: I know, because, like, I think, sometimes I do POCs, because, as, like, my job is sometimes, like, to do 10 POCs out of that, which one is working? It's only for those. If you are into research, then only… otherwise, nobody, like, people directly uses landing.
PAUL: True to say.
Rahul Parihar: Inc.
PAUL: In 2025, nobody really goes into the paper, it will take a Lanshan framework, starting with it.
Rahul Parihar: Okay.
Rahul Parihar: So you're going… if you're going into a deep research, then only it makes sense to select those…
PAUL: Now, my idea of research is just to showcase, because LamiChain is also updating. Recently, like, within the last few weeks, LanChain has updated.
PAUL: A big update has came in last year.
Rahul Parihar: Okay, so the code, probably, that I will be teaching, and if you will actually refer it to someplace.
PAUL: You might feel that, that is duplicate. That's why.
PAUL: Okay, I'm, just, because most of the things are the same, but few modules have changed that.
Rahul Parihar: Okay.
Rahul Parihar: And I'm… this is… second is a technical question. In terms of my understanding for RAC, motivation is coming from a question, going to indexing, going to retrieval, and then going to generation.
Rahul Parihar: And in that, I try to understand it, like, Curie Constructions is important.
Rahul Parihar: QUI translation is important. Routing…
PAUL: Those are advanced topics. Query decomposition is important. It depends, no, how much big is the query. Those are advanced topics. If I'm talking about Heidi.
Rahul Parihar: Are we going…
PAUL: Ring to confusion.
PAUL: Really, like, when you actually try to build a complex, then only those things come together.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah, decompositions and hide are… or step back, you know, when do… when do you use them, and… because if you're…
PAUL: When I use them, see, directly I don't start. I start always with a symbol.
PAUL: Then slowly, slowly, I try to add more conch.
Rahul Parihar: Okay, the idea is C.
PAUL: You add everything, then also it will not work if you don't have a good data passing.
PAUL: And a chunky milk. Just one.
Rahul Parihar: Okay.
PAUL: And really, what chunking will be applied in your data, nobody in this world can say. This is the formula. Take the spoon and take it.
PAUL: There is no fixed fund.
PAUL: You have to do it according to your own data. We have seen one.
Rahul Parihar: According to the data, or according to the domain, like, in terms of.
PAUL: Not domain data.
Rahul Parihar: data, okay.
PAUL: It's always about the data.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah, yeah. So, logical routing and semantic routing… I'm just trying to understand, are we going to touch those topics, or are we going.
PAUL: Probably after 3 months, not now.
Rahul Parihar: After 3 months, okay.
Rahul Parihar: Okay.
PAUL: Just look into the PDF or the syllabus. You will say whatever the thing that you get.
PAUL: That's why always keep it in mind. Module 1, Module 2, you will get to.
Rahul Parihar: If I'm trying to solve a use case specific to my problem, where one of the gentlemen asked the security question, which was very relevant.
Rahul Parihar: if you are sharing the prompts… I have a prompt service and a gateway service. The prompt services generates the prompt and go into the GenAI platform, and it reads to Azure and get the data out, you know? And then the metadata, it's loaded into Snowflake data source.
Rahul Parihar: And the Nexus Event Services, you know.
Rahul Parihar: produce and consume those datas, and break it down into pieces, you know?
PAUL: This is your office workman, really.
Rahul Parihar: But my question is about the security. If we… if we want to have.
PAUL: Security on which component you want to apply to.
Rahul Parihar: LLM.
PAUL: LLM.
PAUL: See, really, LLM security, on top of certain things you can do, on top of guardrails you can apply. Okay. Other than that, there is nothing that you can do.
PAUL: you can't ask OpenAI to do certain changes. If you are working with an open-source one, like Lava-based models or Mestral, then you have a lot of things that you can do. Okay, but if you are working with API-based models, very limitations, very nothing.
PAUL: Because they have certain rules and guardrails which is implemented. On top of that, you can apply your own cartras, that's the only level.
Rahul Parihar: And how…
PAUL: For low-level security, it's really hard to, like.
PAUL: You can host it, that's… on hosting, you can apply some type of rules.
PAUL: Other than that, you cannot do anything.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah.
Rahul Parihar: Are we going to talk about, like, anything concept of Elastic Cache on LLM QOD response prompts, like, from a rack service point of view?
PAUL: Ready sketching, user level, user profiles, those things I have not done.
PAUL: These are HDLC. This is not AI.
PAUL: You have to understand, you are here for AI stuff.
PAUL: You are not here for SDL system.
Rahul Parihar: No, no, overall, overall architect, overall.
PAUL: anybody's building any chatbot, that particular catching concept is being used, if you're using an ELK site very specific. Again, it's not necessary if you are using an ELK program, or catching, I might use only Redis, okay, or a service from AWS. It totally depends upon that.
PAUL: It's not related to that, the question that you asked.
Rahul Parihar: Like, the doc… the product that you're designing, you're not using Elastic Cash?
PAUL: No, we are not in.
Rahul Parihar: Got it.
PAUL: I've used ELQ stack probably, I think, 1.5 years back. I love Kibana, actually, that's why, log stations.
Rahul Parihar: Hmm,
Rahul Parihar: That's good.
PAUL: So, it totally depends upon your solution, like, how, because those are general LTSA stuff, it's nothing related to it.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah, yeah, yeah, I understand, but I'm just trying to see the holistic point of view to the projects…
PAUL: But the rules of SDLC never change. It is applied the same thing. It's about only the core part. I feel always like AI, because at the end of the day, your SDLC is there. AI, if I talk about 40% to 50% of the product.
PAUL: Risk 50% is actually the thing that people have been doing for the past 10 years.
PAUL: Brilliant.
PAUL: Not a lot of changes there.
Rahul Parihar: Like, rate limiter, configs, audit loggers, those topics we are going to…
PAUL: Rate limiting is done, just tell. Their RAG is done.
PAUL: or a user level through CloudShare, can you handle it?
PAUL: See, the question that you were asking is not related to that.
PAUL: It's related to STLC, like, how you are designing your system. I hope Rao will get it.
PAUL: I can apply rate limiting directly through Cloudflare.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah, but in…
PAUL: apply it through FastAPI.
PAUL: Yeah, that doesn't come into the picture.
Rahul Parihar: Yay.
PAUL: That's fine, you can do… always do load testing using locust.
PAUL: And you can actually check, okay, there are certain things that can be followed. This is not AI, the question that you are asking.
PAUL: If you are building a product, then only you are asking. Because there, this is SDNC.
Rahul Parihar: No, yeah, I understand what you're trying to say. The active… yeah.
Rahul Parihar: Not so as self-regs or RRR, those active retrievals, those topics? Okay, those will be later on covered.
PAUL: It will be there. RAG, if anything is related to RAG, if it's not there also, if I feel that it is useful, I will not.
Rahul Parihar: like, ranking.
PAUL: Don't worry about that. Rag, you can say anything. Paul, this is not there. Later on, I will keep it in the bucket list, probably after completing all the modules.
Rahul Parihar: Sure.
Rahul Parihar: Thanks, thanks, Courtney.
PAUL: Okay, next, Rajesh, David.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Oh, iPod?
Ritvij Maheshwari: Yeah, so Paul, first of all, thanks for the session. Actually, I have a confusion page number 3. There are two formulas for rack sequence model and rack token model. Are you able to share your screen so that I can tell you what I'm confused with?
PAUL: Just wait.
PAUL: Okay, yeah, okay.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Page 3.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Section 2.1.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Yeah, so for example, this is P theta and P Eta. What are these, what are these functions, and how… means P… from, I think, previous section, I got to know that P theta is somewhere that we are generating this, and P eta is somewhere that we are retrieving it, but what are the exact functions that, means what is the exact…
PAUL: These functions are responsible to fetch out the documents from your vector team.
Ritvij Maheshwari: to.
PAUL: Any sequence follows.
Ritvij Maheshwari: And the returning is the probabilities.
PAUL: Yes.
PAUL: Returning is always the top K documents.
PAUL: Whatever, that's why here also the top K documents, here are also the top K documents.
Ritvij Maheshwari: What is this top K document? Because in the, in the previous section, in the, I think, page number 2, the last second line went, that is a top K truncated. What is this top K truncated, and is it something related that I need to first learn upon?
PAUL: No, no, no, no, see, just focus on, say, top K documents, it means that K is a number that you give.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Like, K can be 20, K can be 10, K can be 15, K can be 100.
PAUL: It means that when you are searching for a similar context, you try to fetch that certain number of documents.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, for example, certain number of documents is simply, with respect to RAG, is basically the chunk. If I'm going with Langchen, if I say that, okay, I need 20 documents, that 20 becomes the top K.
PAUL: Later on, you can rearrange those documents which is better through re-ranking.
PAUL: So this is basically the top, similar chunks, based on the similarities score.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Got it. And here, I think, in both formulas, I think P eta is constant on the first, and in the second, it is changing on a variable basis, right? Because I think you said that we are using the different document in the second token-based part, and sequence we are using the first means there would… that would be constant throughout, right?
PAUL: Yes.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Got it. So, this is a repetitive question, but yeah, I am not good in NLP. You have shared certain kind of links. Is it possible that you might have also taught in the previous session? Is it available on Udemy, or is it available on…
PAUL: Now, see, in your batch, this is the first batch, actually, for RAC, that I applied for the last 4 or 5 months. So this is the first RAC batch. So these things in… nobody is there.
PAUL: No academic course, nowhere.
PAUL: But the NLP concept, if you are looking for, there is a course which Vesaj created. I think there will be getting the fundamentals of NLP.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Okay, would it be possible to share that link, on the chat? Or maybe I can… yeah, if it is possible, can you share that link?
PAUL: I don't remember exactly the course name, but .
Ritvij Maheshwari: It's available on Udemy.
Ritvij Maheshwari: It's available on Udemy, right?
PAUL: Yeah… just wait.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Yep.
PAUL: It is, Krishna… In the summer.
PAUL: Okay, I think this is the main one, the first course that he launched.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Perfect, perfect. Just one thing, would it be possible that which sections I have to definitely cover to follow on this course? Means, this is about this course.
PAUL: Mmm… really, if I talk about…
Ritvij Maheshwari: And if I tell you till the next week, it…
PAUL: For next week, a few topic comes.
PAUL: Generally, only the fundamentals of penalty, that only I feel. And, as you can see here, attention mechanism and transformers, okay.
PAUL: So… Like, I feel only this last part that you need to focus on.
PAUL: If I'm sharing this link also.
PAUL: Okay, these are the only stuff that you need to focus on.
PAUL: The last part.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Perfect, perfect. I'll try that next… till next week. Actually, the thing is that today, many of the concepts were going above my head, and many of the terms, but I wasn't aware that I have to go with the NLP part as well, but next week, I'll definitely try to catch it.
PAUL: If, like,
PAUL: See, that's why I started with the fundamental, it's deep learning at the end of the day.
PAUL: If somebody is not familiar with deep learning, it becomes a little bit hard.
PAUL: That's all. Because when I say parameters, what are parameters, these are weights and biases. Those simple stuff, actually, everything is covered in deep learning. So, relating stuff becomes easier.
PAUL: In your place.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Sure. Paul, just one last thing. Actually, my manager… so I'm working somewhere in the finance and the portfolios side of sections. We have basic econometrics kind of models in our organization, not the proper ML and AI.
PAUL: I know, I know, those are probabilistic or stochastic-based models, I know.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Yes, yes. So, basically, my manager asked me, two days back, can you tell me… means I said that I'm pursuing this course, and he said to me that how would this, means impact, this AI impact in our index industry? I can mail you as well, this is a personal question only, but would it be, means, can I ask you the… means, are you able to provide those insights about this, or any of your team members who is working on
Ritvij Maheshwari: same domain.
PAUL: And, not related to this, I know a few folks, because my friends are working, basically.
PAUL: Okay, very specifically in that finance model, standing, and others, okay, where they are very specific, but…
PAUL: they don't use AI.
PAUL: Okay, if they are using AI, they have a very specific set of instructions through which they try to do the evaluation.
PAUL: Because the result of the AI? Totally neglect that you can think about. There are certain rules that needs to be followed. If the rules are followed, then only they take that.
PAUL: So, it's not AI directly, I can say, but an evaluation. It means that at every step, a human in the loop chat comes in the picture.
PAUL: Okay. I think you could… And that is a POC, not a production.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Yeah, correct. And I think it's more about the explainability as well, because we have to explain.
PAUL: Yes, advent of the… that's why in India also, simple stuff. Just think, I know Pradaib, one of my friends, okay?
PAUL: In HSBC, in other banks, okay. So, simply, he knew that XZBoost will work good.
PAUL: Okay, but at the end of the day.
PAUL: They need linear regression, because pen and paper.
PAUL: If he could explain that. Exiboost, nobody can do it on paper and paper.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Go ahead.
PAUL: Okay, that's why the explainability, you are exactly correct.
PAUL: That's why simply they rejected, and he left the organization in 3 months.
PAUL: It happens in India, because the idea is to be much more secure, to be much more explainable, so in those conditions, yes.
PAUL: It happens.
Ritvij Maheshwari: sort. Got it. Thanks a lot.
PAUL: Operator's wish, let's move to next.
PAUL: Aarti, David, You guys can go ahead.
aarti kulkarni: Unas.
PAUL: Yeah, go ahead.
aarti kulkarni: Yeah, hey, hi, thank you, thanks for the session. It was very much, like, I learned a lot.
aarti kulkarni: But there are many concepts over my head, but I will, look into the, you know, links that we have shared.
aarti kulkarni: I have a question, like, I have, like, I'm working on one POC project in my company, and we have used RAG, but to be honest, this RAG as provided by the, you know, AI engineers, like, they have given us a common,
PAUL: Am I correct?
PAUL: Yeah.
aarti kulkarni: leisure.
aarti kulkarni: So we are more into the application of it, like, we haven't, never looked into, never got a chance to look into the RAG, actually, what they have done, and what buildings they have used inside, and we were mostly from the part of land chain and land graph side. But, like, after this lesson, I…
aarti kulkarni: after this session, I thought that we have to go and check how they are building…
PAUL: Just have a talk with the engineering team and just, try to…
aarti kulkarni: They have given us a number of embedding models, just whatever they make us available for.
aarti kulkarni: So, like you said before, that to use that in POC, we have to use each and every model, like, embedding models and data, and check which one is giving a good result.
PAUL: No, no, no, no, no, not every model. The idea is to pick up something from the top 10.
aarti kulkarni: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, so generally, the works good, always look into the benchmarks. When I'll be talking about embeddings and these stuff, I'll be telling you exactly how to… because, see, at the end of the day, I look after 9 months, cost estimation, a lot of things comes, then I take the decision. It's not only
PAUL: Which is doing the good. Because I know the best one, probably to hold that model, it can be very costly for me.
PAUL: Okay, so I have to work around in between price, in between performance, that middle ground I need to speak to.
aarti kulkarni: Okay, okay. And then, one more thing that you mentioned before, that versioning of the… this file, because I had same questions, and I asked my, the team…
PAUL: We have broad questions, complete.
aarti kulkarni: Yeah, huh.
PAUL: We have a version. This is quite common language.
aarti kulkarni: Once I understand the version, then we have to inject it again in my project?
PAUL: So, for example, whenever there is a change with respect to the file, okay, you have to understand, like, where is the change? Okay, like, through metadata, you can track… you can keep a track of all the chunks for a certain document.
aarti kulkarni: Okay.
PAUL: If you feel that something is added at any point of time.
aarti kulkarni: Yay,
PAUL: Okay, now that addition part, it's easy. Like, at the end of the document, it's very easy. The logic is simply, like, you have to look into whatever was your last chunk. Based on that, you have to just add in a new chunk.
PAUL: That is the only thing.
PAUL: But now the concept comes, like, if something has happened, like, if a complete chunk has changed, okay, if something has changed, then probably the tracking, through tracking, you need to actually look into what are the line numbers that has been changed.
PAUL: Okay, now that's why exactly how you're keeping your metadata, these type of information we keep in metadata.
PAUL: Through metadata, we keep that track. Okay, this is this, and this is that.
PAUL: In metadata, I've seen people keeping line numbers also, that's why. So that they can track changes very specifically. Like, if I'm working with GitHub, generally, I build a system where I have to take the entire GitHub, and I need to keep track of a certain rate.
PAUL: In that conditions, you know, GitHub always tells you which file has changed.
PAUL: it has not changed. Similarly, in your case also, you need to have a file version system. If there is no file version insisted.
PAUL: you will only not know what files are changed, then how you can update it. So, a proper file versioning system that needs to be maintained.
aarti kulkarni: Okay, okay. And then, the thing is, like, when we ask a query, right? When we build a chatbot-type POC, then it's very easy that user provide a query, and we can
aarti kulkarni: you know, get the RAT context out of it. But when there are some products where we don't have specific query, but they are, like, in API and this stuff, I wanted to use data in search on RAG. That can be possible, like, in next lectures, I can look forward to it, like, how can…
PAUL: It means I could not get, like, give some.
aarti kulkarni: Like, like,
aarti kulkarni: in chat, like, we have query to be provided to get the rack context out of it, right? Then, I'm saying, like, suppose there are multiple APIs, and based on whatever APIs I'm fixing, the rack context should be replaced. So that… that can be possible, right?
aarti kulkarni: In this?
PAUL: Okay, it means that, in your initial knowledge sources, there is no context.
PAUL: So, probably, you want to use some type of external APIs or tools through which you will get the content, then you will pass it to the LLM to get it.
PAUL: Yes, that's a small implementation.
aarti kulkarni: Yeah, it is.
PAUL: Yes. Tools we'll be talking about. In LangChain when we'll be talking, yes, tools will come into the picture.
aarti kulkarni: Okay, okay, thank you, thank you, Paul.
PAUL: Next, debit.
David E: Yeah, hi, Paul, thanks for what you're doing. My question revolves around Xenodocs and, Context 7.
PAUL: Right, yeah, go ahead.
David E: Yeah, I've used Context 7 within Cursor, but I'm trying to understand how Xenodox, works within, Cursor. Could you give us a small, demo of it?
David E: A whole to you.
PAUL: It's just like… it's just like, context 7 only.
PAUL: it will have an MCP server. That MCP server you will set up with cursor or VSP.
PAUL: category. So, like, in our case, like,
PAUL: We have kept, like, in context, if you have looked, okay, very specifically, there are a lot of depots.
PAUL: It can be from the documentation pages, it can be. They have really missed that, I feel.
PAUL: Just because they have kept it open source somehow.
PAUL: We are actually measuring that, exactly what is change and what is…
PAUL: risk, it's pretty much the context 7, and even we are given the option to directly connect it to LMs.
PAUL: Okay, through our plan. It means that you don't need to take care of the LLM part directly through our API, you can use that.
PAUL: So, that's the complete MCP package dynamic.
PAUL: context, only context. Here, we are providing the context as well as that LLM integration.
David E: As well as merely.
PAUL: all the options you will get, like, you can bring your own LLM also. Okay, so all those features will become…
David E: Okay. At the end of that day, MCP server will come, so you can test it.
PAUL: Okay. Wait for 7 days or 10 days, it will work.
David E: Oh, alright. Okay, thanks.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Next, Jonas.
Yonas: Hello?
PAUL: Yes.
Yonas: Hello? Yeah.
PAUL: Yes, you will not.
Yonas: I'm coming through, I'm coming through.
PAUL: Okay.
Yonas: I wanna ask her some questions, like,
Yonas: My question is, like, it's mostly related to… not… I'm not going to deep dive into technicals, so I want to ask it in general.
PAUL: Please go ahead, please go ahead.
Yonas: My question is, like, in our courses, I should have to be known as LLM fine-tuning? This was for my first questions, like, in RAG, you are talking about more LLMs, like, just like Arctic Press, so…
Yonas: I should have two be notes about fine-tuning of LLM.
PAUL: No.
PAUL: You don't need. In this course, you don't need… I'll be taking only one class, just to show you the fine-tuning.
PAUL: Okay, just to give you a rough idea exactly how it is done.
PAUL: Okay, that's the only part. You don't need to know about fine-team. Really, it is not required.
Yonas: Okay, that's good. What about, like, actually, but my background is, like, academic. It's not, like, I'm no good, like, bugging and fronting, like, for development, so I need to know about,
Yonas: fast repair some stuff, is that… is that mandatory?
PAUL: I feel that if you're building an application, You need APIs.
PAUL: So, yes, it is mandatory. I will be working with Fast API in the schools.
PAUL: See, at the end of the day, if you're building some product, the idea is to somebody will use it.
PAUL: to that somebody, however, the most conventional be, I feel that it is REST ETS.
PAUL: So, using FastAPI, I can build the REST API. So, I feel that, yes, it is somewhere important.
Yonas: like, now, like, in our courses, like, when I was seeing the modules in syllables, I think all start talking…
PAUL: Auto.
Yonas: are both… projected…
PAUL: Jetfire will be doing FastAPI. That's right.
Yonas: So, I think I have a term, like, you are… does first prepare knowledge, or…
Yonas: release API at the end of the course somewhere else, like…
PAUL: not end. In between only, I think, at least.
PAUL: one month or somewhere, I will start with Project 1. In Project 1, why will we be working with Fast eBay? Fast efepe is not a big deal. Don't think
PAUL: something. It's pretty easy, just like Flask only. The core functionalities and those things I'll be discussing in class, so don't worry.
Yonas: No, I know that, like, actually, I understand, like, the gates, post, I know that's bad, you know, that some things, like, if deep dev, you know, there's a little.
PAUL: Yes, we will go deep dive. When I will be discussing a project, it will be pretty deep dive. You can think about one project means at least I need 3 to 4 classes.
Yonas: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, so it will be deep dive.
Yonas: So my question is, my last question is, like, RAG means as a part of generative AI engineer, or, like, RAG is…
Yonas: out of that, like, if to be… if we… actually, I would… if someone to be, like, a genetically engineer.
Yonas: you should have to be known, so what's LLM some stuff in Iraq, so… does that make sense, or…
Yonas: Yo, I'm leaving.
PAUL: It's not necessarily only generative AI engineers. He can be a data scientist, he can be a deep learning engineer, NLP engineer, any type of profile that works. Gen AI engineer just came around, like, I feel 1.5 years to 2 years back.
PAUL: Okay, but there are profiles like Senior Data Scientist, okay, these guys also work, so the profile really doesn't matter.
PAUL: What's exactly in the job description that matters most?
Yonas: Yeah, that makes sense. Okay, actually, for last sentence, for expansions and the way of teaching, I very appreciate… I like it, so…
Yonas: Thank you. Keep it going, Gohan.
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, thanks, Ivanas. Okay, next move to… Hari Kumar.
PAUL: Okay, Argya, Deb Chyoti Mukavatai.
Hari Kumar: Yeah.
PAUL: Ricky is there. Yeah, Ricky. Yes, go ahead.
Hari Kumar: Thanks for the session. I was about to ask the same question. One of the guys asked, like.
Hari Kumar: The type of documents are different, right? I mean, when you see, when you are trying to solve a problem, there are,
Hari Kumar: various types of documents come into picture, not only text, it may be tables, images, images with text. So when we are trying to implement a real-time solution, definitely, there are various ways, where you can.
PAUL: That is the main pain point.
Hari Kumar: Yeah, yeah.
PAUL: That is only the main pain point.
Hari Kumar: Make that happen.
PAUL: I think.
Hari Kumar: Right, right. So, for example, like, if the number of documents are these many, and these stack techniques work better, and if these documents contain these kind of tables and images, these stack techniques, I mean, at every stage of retrieval augmented generation.
Hari Kumar: these techniques work better in these areas. Are there any, kind of, standard techniques do you think, like, we can follow so that we can get the right information? Because at the end of the day, if you could not be able to retrieve the information, blindly, like, it says, like, rack fails, I mean.
Hari Kumar: That is where, in many of the scenarios we can see, down the line, because of these huge billion parameter models, we can provide the document as an in-context and retrieve the responses. So, how we can make a rag so that, we will be able to retrieve the information rightly?
Hari Kumar: At different techniques, using different techniques.
PAUL: See, few components can be standardized.
PAUL: But really, like, I cannot say that for this data type, okay, or for this particular document type, okay, I can fix, my parsing strategy.
PAUL: That is the main problem that we do face.
PAUL: Okay, like, few components you can standardize, it means that everybody follows those rules. Okay, but few things with respect to data parsing, it cannot be standardized.
PAUL: Okay, because really, like, data… it totally depends upon… you need to analyze. We sit and analyze data for hours. Then we see. Then, based on that, we try to define the chunking strategy, then it… the chunking might not work, then I have to check
PAUL: different, all 8 to 10 chunking strategies that I have in my…
PAUL: basket, one by one, I will apply, I will see. So, it takes time. It's an incremental thing. Okay, you will experiment, then you will come, experiment, experiment, that's why.
PAUL: So, few components can be standardized, but few things, really. It is pretty much dynamic. Nobody can define it in one shot.
Hari Kumar: Things which are standard in maybe one or two examples.
PAUL: Generally in the retrieval phase.
PAUL: In the interval phase, a lot of things, like re-ranking, ID, those things pretty much can be standardized.
PAUL: But not, in the data ingestion phase.
PAUL: The Phase 1 is the most complex one, because Phase 2, everybody builds, but the Phase 1, how you can make it better.
PAUL: That comes with a lot of expert.
Hari Kumar: Sure.
Hari Kumar: Okay.
Hari Kumar: Yeah, so in our organization, we are trying to build, we are trying to reuse some of the Git repository, like RAG anything, Ragflow, and then trying to understand the capabilities of, RAG.
PAUL: That goes to direct, so most of the things are already there.
Hari Kumar: Yeah, that's what we are trying to reuse, and then we are trying to open.
Hari Kumar: Thanks, Tentacle.
PAUL: Alright, hurry. Next.
ARGHYA: Hey, son.
PAUL: Yeah. Okay.
ARGHYA: Hey, first I'd like to ask a question about the session that we did. So, the profit of trans passenger, you know, thing, yeah. So, can you explain the difference between DPR and fence, you know? I did a Google search, it tells me it's not a single thing.
ARGHYA: So, can we just elaborate a little on that?
PAUL: Like, very specific to which part?
ARGHYA: intense.
PAUL: Dense passage retrieval.
ARGHYA: Passage retrieval versus tense retrieval. What is the difference?
ARGHYA: I understand that density fuel is just, like.
PAUL: Dense retrieval versus dense passage retrieval.
ARGHYA: Retrieving, yeah.
PAUL: It's the same stuff only. Passage means documents at the end of the day.
PAUL: Okay, got it, so…
ARGHYA: So, my understanding is it's a similarity search that we are doing based on the query from the database.
PAUL: Yeah, so…
ARGHYA: Doctor documents first.
PAUL: Correct intuition, correct intuition. Hence, whenever we are talking, it means that it has been converted into embeddings and saved in some type of vector database. That's the main idea of that.
ARGHYA: And the GPR techniques, right, with the transformation model, it's just to evaluate, right, which, which, which embedding model gives me what kind of activation. If you physically.
PAUL: It's not about evaluation, that's the backbone, like, how you do compare embeddings, instant bittings that we talked about.
ARGHYA: It is basically, for my use case, I'll take some sample query, and I'll see what… which one gives me what kind.
PAUL: Yes, are you getting higher similarity scores for relevant documents? That's the main thing.
ARGHYA: So, not necessarily the MPB1, rank 1, embedding model will be best for my.
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes. See, generally, I've seen the top 10 works pretty good, so that's why I picked, like, the… generally, I've seen the top one is…
PAUL: Really costly to host.
PAUL: Okay, like, I have to use GPUs to not use.
ARGHYA: sucked out.
PAUL: That is the main problem that I do feel. So I always select something in between the top 10, which is just like a middle ground with respect to cost and performance.
ARGHYA: So, so, so here's another… another question that I have. I think…
ARGHYA: It's nothing to do the case.
ARGHYA: If you look at it. The other thing is, we were talking about incremental and data, right? So, here's a way that I was qualifying that.
ARGHYA: OpenAI, whatever I had, right? So, I was working on a project where I was kind of getting
ARGHYA: These are students, but from Jira or, like, similar repository, right?
ARGHYA: And, I did not put a chair.
ARGHYA: that, every time I initiated that, it did a, like, external policy.
ARGHYA: the… the external API, so it's like, I get what I'm doing, right? And every time.
ARGHYA: It's a huge data, right? And to embed that, it's a… it costs a lot of money every day.
ARGHYA: So, what I observed was, like, I didn't accidentally twice.
ARGHYA: So, what I saw was that the reports got completed. So, my top key documents, whenever I was doing a query, I received the same records come up again and again. Is it because that, that the root cause was that I… I did not handle the…
ARGHYA: Obviously, I did not handle it properly, and it got appended in my index. Like, every time I ran.
PAUL: Yes, it can happen. Like, even… I have faced this issue, okay, like, where I didn't handle, like, the same document, probably, if I do chunking twice.
ARGHYA: It can happen.
ARGHYA: Yeah, and in my top 20 documents, like, 18 documents are, like, the same…
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, yes, I can get… I can relate. This has happened to me also.
ARGHYA: So, apart from that, so let's say we are working with, the part of, like, like, like, Rally, or… not the father, Rally, Jiva, already, like, whatever we are working with. So, it's not possible to worship all of these things, like, the, like.
PAUL: Probably, you have to look for webhooks. Through webhooks, you need to actually, look into the changes. If there is any change in there through webhooks, you need to actually track that.
PAUL: Generally, like, GitHub provides, okay, like, similarly, like, Jira also provides.
PAUL: You need webhooks. Without webhooks, it becomes very hard, because every time you even don't know when you have to make the API call.
ARGHYA: We cannot… and it's very expensive to return. I cannot spend, like, 10, 20 dollars every time I…
PAUL: Yes, yes, I know, for every meeting, I know, it's…
ARGHYA: Let me, so, Dr.
PAUL: Tons of the cost.
ARGHYA: Okay. Nope.
ARGHYA: Thanks.
PAUL: Alright, Argan, next.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Yeah, hi, Paul, DevJ this side. Yeah.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Just having a couple of questions. For example, you are completely emphasizing on the NLP part, whereas,
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: I find a couple of algorithms you spell out, a bag of words, or TFIDF and all, right? So, we… we have to have the theoretical knowledge, or we should have the clear implementation knowledge on all these.
PAUL: theoretical knowledge just for the schools, really. Nobody is going… you won't be implementing those stuff.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Just kidding.
PAUL: The idea is, say, how things change, the idea is that you should have in your mind that, okay, now, this is the change, and how this helps. So, in that way, you should have just the pros and cons.
PAUL: So that you know internally that you should have a strong foundation. So for that, you should know the consent.
PAUL: That's the only thing I'm looking for.
PAUL: Because these concepts are just like you spend 2 to 3 minutes and you will understand the concept. These are the most basic and simple concepts.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Yes, yes. Okay, one more question, probably. So, to understand the RAG as a flow, we have to have a deep understanding of the LLMs?
PAUL: Oh, really, like, in this course, it will be much more about directly consuming the LLMs. So, really, how LLMs are built, that part you really don't need to worry about. It's something like here, it's all about the consumption of the LLMs, rather than building LLMs.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Okay, that means… okay, that… okay, so that means a pre-built LL, kind of?
PAUL: Yes, we'll be always working with some type of foundational models.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Okay, okay, fun, okay. Okay, and one last question, maybe you talked on the context level, right?
PAUL: So… so the… so the part of chunkings and all these things, that will not be cover-up. It will… it is a prerequisite, or you will somewhat touch it? No, what is the chunking in detail.
PAUL: Beautiful.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Oh, okay.
PAUL: algorithms, I will talk about that.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Yes, yes. Okay, okay, okay.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Thank you so much.
PAUL: Alright, next.
PAUL: Srinath reddi.
PAUL: And Pavan Khan Vitalik.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Paul, just one… sorry, just one more minute.
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, please go ahead.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: You send, many links out of each. One is VANA 2.0. I missed out that part, actually. How that is being used here, actually?
PAUL: Actually, if you're working with RTBMS, in that case, very specifically using VANA, you can create, like, SQL posthag and other stuff.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Okay, okay, okay, okay.
DEBAJYOTI MUKHOPADHYAY: Yeah, thanks.
PAUL: Yes, Trinath?
PAUL: Quickly, guys, gone, and 5 minutes, I have to close. 2 o'clock, another session starts.
PAUL: And how you open that book.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: disposal.
PAUL: Yes, Lord.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: Yeah, Paul, in the research paper, you have, there's a sentence, like.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: Even though the… the context is not found in the retreat documents, there… the…
Pavankanna Polavarapu: whether access don't be prepared, expect a correct answer.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: How could that be possible?
PAUL: the one that I showed in the class, that line…
Pavankanna Polavarapu: Yeah, I am.
PAUL: See, probably, it, very specifically, it was telling that
PAUL: from the documents, it means that they are referring to the non-parameter.
PAUL: Okay, but you are getting the correct result because, probably, the data on which the language model was trained on, so basically the parametric memory has that information.
PAUL: So, because of that, it is showing you the correct response.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: In that case, the memory, in the LLM come in handy.
PAUL: Yes, it's very, very handy.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: No, is it required to have a pre-trained model which is already trained on, like, similar to mine, something like that?
PAUL: Yes, that's why people are building domain-specific LLMs, no? Nowadays.
PAUL: It's very, very important, and it becomes much more handy also.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: No, if we are… I'm just not getting this. If we are using a domain-specific analog, why we need a…
Pavankanna Polavarapu: a rag…
PAUL: Then also, a domain-specific LLM, there will be certain limitations with respect to the proprietary data.
PAUL: It will be open source.
PAUL: Okay, now when you try to host it in your own platform and for your own organization data.
PAUL: The open… that domain-specific knowledge will be pretty much limited, and on top of your own proprietary data if you want to add it. For that, you need rank.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: And we have to do one more thing now.
PAUL: If you think about your project as an open source
PAUL: complete work that you are doing. In that case, you can ignore. If you feel that, okay, my domain-specific LLM is working fine, and I don't need RAC, that is fine, because for general tasks, for generic tasks, nobody need a domain-specific LLM.
PAUL: ChatGPT, Claude, Anthropic, these type of models, generally, they work good. Imagate to Moonshot.
PAUL: I hope you get my point.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: Yeah, yeah, yeah, I'm ridiculous.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: And one more thing on retrieval step in the RAG architecture. And you have mentioned, like, DPR, right? The tense bars, the retrieval…
PAUL: Yes.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: Is it one kind of technique used for the retrieval, or is that the technique which we use for every kind of retrieval.
PAUL: It is a style, it is a technique for retrieval of similar embeddings.
PAUL: having similar context from some type of data source here, which is vector DB9.
PAUL: That is the only thing.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: Are there any other kinds that we use, to perform those similarities?
PAUL: There are other type of retrievals.
PAUL: But we don't use it in RAC. Very specifically, those are used in deep learning and LP.
PAUL: Because, see, right now I told you about encoder, very specifically, bi-encoder architecture, but there can be bi-decoder architecture also.
PAUL: There are other techniques also.
PAUL: Yes, for sure there will be other techniques, yes. This technique is very specifically from the Facebook research.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: Oh, okay. But for red, we are using…
PAUL: Because the… you have to understand, RAG came from Facebook research, from Meta, that's right.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: people.
Pavankanna Polavarapu: Yeah, yeah, well, that's, that's…
PAUL: Alright, guys, so, looks like I've taken all the questions, no more queries, okay? So, I will be adding a few more content, so keep a track in Notion, always.
PAUL: Okay. Mudassar, you have to eat your aunt, I think.
Mudassar Hakim: Hey, Paul, so sorry. The point is, Paul, I was just suggesting here one thing. This Notion link, right? I'm definitely bookmarking it, and being very candid here, my bookmarks are overflowing, so I don't know when I will lose this item. Is it a possibility in the…
PAUL: It will be available in your dashboard also, like.
Mudassar Hakim: In the course description, maybe? Yeah, I was just wondering.
PAUL: Not in course description.
PAUL: See, I think the team has done it. Yesterday, I told them.
Mudassar Hakim: Yeah, because then, you know, I'm sure pretty much others… for some reason, they keep missing those links for some reason.
PAUL: No, no, it will be here, so when you go to the course, just click, let me just share this.
Mudassar Hakim: And we'd automatically.
PAUL: Courses…
PAUL: View as customer… Okay, so when, for example, like, tools and installation, no, here you will be getting this.
Mudassar Hakim: Acha, sorry, so you're adding it in the videos, the resources.
PAUL: resource under this, okay?
Mudassar Hakim: Got it, got it. Shalega, that works. Thanks, thanks, Paul.
Mudassar Hakim: Take care, man, and once again, thanks for the session.
PAUL: Alright, so, everyone, so let's meet, okay? So, okay…
PAUL: See, guys, you should have raised your hand quickly, Jay, and ask your question, Jay and Saitija.
Jay More: Hello?
PAUL: Hello, sir. Hello, sir.
Jay More: I'm… I will not take your much time, but…
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, food.
Jay More: excellent session, you said to me that as a fresher, if you want to apply in any AI job, you must know cloud also. So, right now.
PAUL: Basic requirement.
Jay More: Yes, yes. So, can you please guide me? How can I start, to learn cloud? Where should I…
PAUL: Put my.
Jay More: time.
PAUL: check in Udemy, there will be a course with respect to, like, AWS.
PAUL: certified ML specialty paper, okay, or an AI practitioner. These two papers, any one of this, go through the content.
PAUL: From there, you will get the idea. The idea is to know the services much more.
PAUL: Okay, in the interview, they will ask you about their services very specifically. So you should know the services at least, okay? Just as you will.
Jay More: Thank you.
PAUL: And in offer, when you get it in 300, purchase it. It's a good course.
Jay More: Yes, sir. Thank you, thank you, sir.
PAUL: Alright. Yeah, Scytheja…
saiteja: Sorry, sir, I will not take much time. So, you said, that course of, that, yeah, I have to learn, NLP, no, sir, should I buy it, or,
saiteja: It will provide something.
PAUL: Wait, wait, let me say, let me consult, at least with Chris, okay, whether that, coupon has been released for that course for November. If that has been released, nothing I can do, it will be again released in December, so let me talk to him, then probably on Saturday, I will let him.
PAUL: In the meantime, these things, the topics I know, are available directly in Chris Channel, or there are a lot of good vlogs or anything. Just try to use ChatGPT, nothing.
saiteja: Okay, thank you, sir.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Srinath, Reddy, I don't know, there has been no response, and nearby Rana. Quickly, guys, go on. 150, I have to close.
Nirbhay Rana: Yeah, hi.
Nirbhay Rana: Yeah, hi Paul. My question is regarding, like, enterprises solutions, like, it's basically, like, will you be telling us about, like, guardrails and the Arena SDK stuff as well?
PAUL: I'll be talking about gardens.
Nirbhay Rana: Okay.
Nirbhay Rana: Okay, no, that's fine.
PAUL: the other thing that you told? I could not get it.
Nirbhay Rana: VK? .
PAUL: SDK.
Nirbhay Rana: Arena SDK means, like, a firewall.
PAUL: Okay, no, no, no, no, no. Right now, it will be much more limited to that.
Nirbhay Rana: Okay, okay, that's helpful. Thank you.
PAUL: Oh, great.
PAUL: Alright guys, so I'll be concluding the session for today. Okay, so let's meet next week and continue the second research paper discussion.
PAUL: All right, everyone, so bye-bye. Thanks for joining.